<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<presentation><title>Special Considerations In Orthodontics for Adults</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>William R. Proffit<br/>Dept. of Orthodontics, UNC School of Dentistry</additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="adultortho/images/titlepage2.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Demand for Treatment / Motivation</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Demand for Adult Treatment</title><pageText><p>Adult orthodontics was quite rare in the United States until the 1970s, then 
became the fastest growing area in orthodontics (image 1). By 1990, 25% 
of all patients receiving comprehensive treatment were age 19 or older.</p>

<p>Since then, the number of adult patients in the United States has remained 
relatively constant, but the proportion of adults has dropped to 20% because 
of growth in the number of children receiving treatment (image 2). For more 
than two decades now, adults with fixed braces on their teeth have been 
commonly observed at all levels of American society.</p>

<p>The same trend toward more adult orthodontics occurred somewhat later in 
Western Europe and Japan, where adult orthodontics now frequently is done. 
It is happening now in other countries as economic advances occur, for 
example, in the Eastern European countries formerly behind the 
Iron Curtain.</p>

<p>Having braces on their teeth is no longer a social problem for most adults. 
Increasingly, this is accepted as nothing special or even a sign of upward 
social mobility.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_03_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, 1990 demand</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_04.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_04_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, current demand</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Motivation for Treatment: Improve Present Situation</title><pageText><p>Adult orthodontic patients can be placed into two groups: those whose motivation 
is to improve their present situation, and those whose goal is to keep 
what they have.</p>

<p>The first group often had wanted treatment as adolescents and didn’t 
get it for some reason. Their motivation almost always includes eliminating 
the social handicap created by their dental and facial appearance 
(image 1).</p>

<p>This motivation makes them candidates for comprehensive orthodontic treatment 
to obtain the best result possible (image 2). It often also makes them 
candidates for ceramic brackets, lingual orthodontics, or perhaps 
(if they’re particularly insecure socially) the transparent plastic 
aligners recently advertised on TV.</p>

<p>For the doctor, a danger with this group is that the real reason they are 
seeking treatment may be concealed--in other words, there may be a hidden 
agenda. If treatment does not produce what the patient wanted, he or she 
will be disappointed--and the doctor, who wasn’t directly told, may 
not have figured out the patient’s real goal. When esthetic improvement 
is sought, ascertaining what the patient really wants is an important part 
of the diagnostic evaluation. That’s true with all types of esthetic 
dentistry, not just orthodontics.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_05.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_05_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, motivation</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_06.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_06_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, treatment desired</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Motivation for Treatment: Maintaining Present Situation</title><pageText><p>In contrast, the motivation for a second group of adults is not to improve 
their present situation, but to keep it from getting worse--their goal 
is to maintain what they have (image 1). The threat typically is loss 
of teeth and the facial soft tissue/dental appearance changes that accompany 
tooth loss and aging.</p>

<p>These adults tend to be older (usually age 35 and up, but sometimes younger). 
Their motivation makes them candidates for treatment involving multiple types 
of dentistry (image 2). Typically, treatment of periodontal problems and 
restoration of damaged/missing teeth is required, and the goal of orthodontic 
treatment is to facilitate the other treatment that the patient needs, not to 
comprehensively make occlusion and alignment as ideal as possible. The 
appearance of the orthodontic appliance often is only a minor concern.</p>

<p>Recent experience makes it clear that including orthodontics in the treatment 
plan for such patients can produce better results than otherwise would have 
been possible, and in the last decade this has been the fastest growing area 
in orthodontic treatment. The average age of adult orthodontic patients 
has increased.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_07.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_07_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, motivation</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_08.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_08_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, treatment desired</label><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Periodontal Considerations</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Periodontal Problems by Age</title><pageText><p>A third important area, which requires even greater emphasis in orthodontics 
for adults than it does in children, is the health of the periodontium. 
Several health-related considerations are important.</p>

<p>First (image 1), let’s review the prevalence of periodontitis/periodontal 
pockets and mucogingival problems (lack of adequate attached tissue) at 
various ages.</p>

<p>The graph in image 2 is derived from examination of 1000 patients with severe 
malocclusion who were evaluated through UNC’s Dentofacial Clinic for 
possible orthognathic surgery.</p>

<p>Note that the prevalence of periodontal pocketing, reflecting bone loss, 
doubles between age 20 and 26 and doubles again by age 33-39. The odds are 
that potential orthodontic patients who are over age 30 will have some 
evidence of periodontal disease. The severity of malocclusion is not a major 
factor in whether periodontal problems develop, so these prevalence numbers 
are reasonable estimates for adult orthodontic patients with less severe 
problems.</p>

<p>Note also that mucogingival problems, typically a lack of attached gingiva, 
are much more prevalent than pocketing in the 10-19 age group who are the more 
frequent candidates for orthodontics--but this peaks in the early 20s and 
actually declines thereafter.</p>

<p>The bottom line: It’s critically important to be sure that periodontal 
disease is under control before any orthodontics begins--and periodontal 
problems, though perhaps of different types, are likely to be present in 
both younger and older adults.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_09.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_09_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, outline</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_10.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_10_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, prevalence graph</label><caption>Periodontal pocketing and mucogingival problems in patients seeking treatment for severe malocclusion.</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Detection of Periodontal Problems</title><pageText><p>A second important aspect of periodontal health in adults who are candidates 
for orthodontic treatment is the detection of periodontal problems 
(image 1).</p>

<p>The guideline for any sort of orthodontics is simple: Orthodontic treatment 
is quite feasible for patients who have had periodontal disease and bone 
loss--but tooth movement cannot begin until active disease is brought under 
control.</p>

<p>Of course the best indicator of active disease is bleeding on gentle 
probing (image 2).</p>

<p>It is equally important to remember that expansion of the dental arches 
stresses the gingival attachment and can lead to further loss of gingival 
tissue. The primary trouble area is the lower incisor region, where alignment 
of crowded incisors tends to move them facially (image 3). Arch expansion in 
other areas, however, also stresses the gingival attachment.</p>

<p>Tooth movement that stresses the attachment is risky in children who do not 
have good gingival attachment before treatment starts--and it's even riskier 
in adults. Areas of reduced attachment must be evaluated carefully when 
tooth movement is planned.</p>

<p>Measuring the amount of attached tissue, and noting areas that already are 
at risk, are important steps in detecting potential mucogingival problems. 
Repositioning frenum attachments and/or placing a gingival graft before 
orthodontics begins may be needed.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_11.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_11_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, outline</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_12.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_12_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, active disease</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_13.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_13_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, mucogingival</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Orthodontics and Periodontal Health (cont.)</title><pageText><p>A third important periodontal consideration in adult orthodontics is the 
effect of bone loss on the amount of force for orthodontic tooth movement 
(image 1). If bone loss has occurred in an adult patient, both the amount 
of force and the magnitude of the moment to control root position must 
be adjusted.</p>

<p>By now you are quite familiar with the optimal force for various types of 
tooth movement, as shown in image 2. Remember that there is only one 
optimal pressure in the PDL. The amount of force for the various tooth 
movements varies because the force distribution in the PDL varies, hence 
the force variation keeps the pressure at the optimum.</p>

<p>But these forces are based on the assumption that the amount of periodontal 
ligament area is normal, i.e., that the amount of root supported by alveolar 
bone is normal.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_14.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_14_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, outline</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_15.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_15_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, orthodontic force</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Effect of Bone Loss on Orthodontic Force (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Consider the force system to move a premolar bodily (image 1). For bodily 
movement, a force of 100 grams is appropriate. If this force is applied 
against the crown, however, the tooth will tip, because force against 
the crown is at a distance from the center of resistance, which is about 
the midpoint of the part of the root supported by bone. Typically, that 
distance is about 10 mm, so a 100-gm force against the crown creates a 
1000 gm-mm moment (moment of the force, MF). To obtain bodily movement, 
a moment in the opposite direction with a magnitude of 1000 gm-mm must 
be created, by applying a couple on the bracket (moment of the couple, MC).</p>

<p>Now look at the situation when significant bone loss has occurred (image 2). 
If the bone level is halfway down the root, the area of the periodontal 
ligament over which the force will be expressed is half what it would be 
normally, so now 100 grams would produce twice the optimal pressure. 
Further, the center of resistance now would be 15 mm from the bracket, not 10, 
so the moment of the force would be 1500 gm-mm, and a 1000 gm-mm moment from 
the couple on the bracket would not be enough to prevent tipping.</p>

<p>For bodily movement of a premolar with loss of half the alveolar bone, the 
optimal force would be 50 gm, not 100 gm (image 3). Since the moment of this 
force would be 750 gm-mm (50 gm x 15 mm to the center of resistance), the 
moment of the couple on the bracket would have to be 750 gm-mm. The force 
was reduced by half, but the moment of the couple only decreased 25%.</p>

<p>You might have thought that since adults have harder heads, it would take 
more force to move their teeth. It’s just the opposite. Successful 
tooth movement in adults, especially those who have had bone loss, requires 
careful use of light forces and relatively larger moments to control 
root position.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_16.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_16_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, normal</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_17_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, bone loss</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_18.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_18_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, corrected for bone loss</label><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Patient Management</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Patient Management</title><pageText><p>As people get older, lots of things aren’t as easy as they once were. 
Tolerating orthodontic treatment definitely falls into that category (image 
1). If you're the family dentist and one of your adult patients has orthodontic 
treatment, you’re very likely to hear about how difficult it was 
to get through the first couple of weeks.</p>

<p>Don’t tell adults, “Oh, there’s nothing to it 
really--you’ll do just fine.” Tell them there will be all kinds 
of things that are problems during those first 2 weeks, but fortunately 
after that it gets better. Expectations affect the reaction to most 
treatment. Often it’s not so much that things are good or bad that 
determines your reaction, it’s the extent to which the reality 
matches what you expected.</p>

<p>It’s important to provide medication for pain control (image 2). 
Adults have sore teeth initially to an extent that children don’t, 
and also are more likely to complain about mucosal lesions where some part 
of the appliance touches the lips or cheek.</p>

<p>Reminding patients to keep wax on any irritating part of the appliance 
until they get used to it, and giving them a small tube of a topical 
anesthetic, can prevent “emergency” appointments during those 
first 2 weeks.</p>

<p>Ibuprofen, on balance, probably is the best choice for pain control. The 
new COX-2 inhibitors have the potential advantage for adults that they 
reduce stomach irritation and require only one tablet per day, but their 
safety still is questionable for long-term use and at present their cost 
is considerably higher.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_19.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_19_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, difficulties</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_20.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_20_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, pain control</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Reassurance and Explanation</title><pageText><p>Finally, children and adolescents often are somewhat indifferent about 
their orthodontic treatment. That doesn’t happen with adults. 
They’re intensely interested, and the clinician has to be prepared 
for questions and discussion about how the treatment is going.</p>

<p>As one adult orthodontic patient put it, "You might as well go ahead and 
tell me all about it while you’re doing the treatment, because if 
you don’t I’m going to ask you before I leave."</p>

<ul><li> What has happened since last time? How am I doing?</li>
<li> What are you doing today? Why?</li>
<li> What’s going to happen between now and next time?</li>
<li> Will I have any special difficulty?</li>
</ul><p>If you’re the family dentist and your patient now is seeing an 
orthodontist, be prepared. The patient is going to tell you all about it, 
ask if you think things are going well, and seek your opinion about whether 
the orthodontist will finish the treatment on time.</p>

<p>It’s just part of patient management--easier to handle if you 
expect it.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_21.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_21_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Case #1: Incisor Intrusion / Build-Ups</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Incisor Intrusion, Incisor Build-Ups</title><pageText><p>Now let’s consider three patients who illustrate specific areas 
of interest for adult orthodontics, beginning with a young adult who 
needs intrusion of maxillary incisors and build-ups for small incisors.</p>

<p>Steve’s chief complaint (image 1) was the appearance of his 
upper incisors. He said, “I try never to smile showing my front 
teeth.” After graduation from college, he was working as a research 
technician in the orthodontic department and became aware that this could 
be corrected.</p>

<p>Facial proportions generally were normal (images 2 and 3), but note that 
there is a mild mandibular asymmetry, with the chin off to the left. 
This isn’t a problem, but it is something that should be observed. 
It explains why the dental midline also is slightly off in the same 
direction.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="300" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_03_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, smile</label><caption><p>Steve, age 22, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="300" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_04a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_04a_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, frontal</label><caption><p>Steve, age 22, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="300" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_04b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_04b_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, profile</label><caption><p>Steve, age 22, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Initial Records</title><pageText><p>In the frontal view of the dentition (image 1), note the elongation of the 
maxillary central incisors, deep overbite, and incisor spacing.</p>

<p>The molar relationship is normal (Class I), but the maxillary incisors are 
very upright, almost in a Class II, division 2 pattern (images 2 and 3).</p>

<p>The upper and lower teeth are well aligned (images 4 and 5), but spacing 
around the small maxillary incisors is apparent. Tooth size analysis 
confirmed that both the maxillary central and lateral incisors were small 
relative to the other teeth.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="501" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_05a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_05a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Steve, age 22, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="500" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_05b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_05b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right lateral</label><caption><p>Steve, age 22, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="500" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_05c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_05c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, left lateral</label><caption><p>Steve, age 22, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="501" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_06a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_06a_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, maxillary occlusal</label><caption><p>Steve, age 22, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="500" resourceHeight="302" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_06b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="132" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_06b_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, mandibular occlusal</label><caption><p>Steve, age 22, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Initial Records</title><pageText><p>On the panoramic radiograph (image 1), it is apparent that the dentition 
is generally healthy, with no restorations and no evidence of alveolar 
bone loss.</p>

<p>Note the elongated maxillary left third molar. A tooth in this position can 
be the cause of a mandibular shift on closure. As a general rule, removal 
of third molars is indicated before comprehensive orthodontics for 
adults begins.</p>

<p>The cephalometric radiograph and tracing (images 2 and 3) confirm the 
upright/elongated position of the maxillary central incisors. The 
anteroposterior jaw relationships are normal, and lower face height is 
slightly decreased.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="319" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_07.jpg" thumbnailWidth="150" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_07_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, pan</label><caption><p>Steve, age 22. Note the elongated maxillary 3rd molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="374" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_08a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_08a_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, ceph</label><caption><p>Normal jaw relationships, upright/elongated maxillary incisors.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="340" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_08b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="60" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_08b_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, tracing</label><caption><p>Normal jaw relationships, upright/elongated maxillary incisors.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Treatment Plan</title><pageText><p>The plan for Steve was to address his primary problem of elongated/spaced 
maxillary incisors and excessive overbite, using segmented arch mechanics 
to intrude the central incisors (this is the only way to obtain the very 
light force necessary for intrusion), then build-ups of the small incisors 
with composite resin to bring them to normal size and eliminate spacing.</p>

<p>The first step in treatment would be to remove the elongated maxillary left 
third molar. A tooth in this position creates a potential occlusal 
interference, and even if it is tolerated prior to treatment, it can become 
a problem during treatment.</p>

<p>When arch segments are created, and especially when intrusion of maxillary 
incisors is desired, a transpalatal lingual arch becomes an important 
stabilizing/anchorage part of the orthodontic appliance.</p>

<p>Because of the deep bite anteriorly, it would not be possible to place 
brackets on the lower incisors until the upper incisors had been 
repositioned, so treatment for the upper arch would have to start first.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_09.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_09_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Incisor Intrusion</title><pageText><p>The first step in the orthodontic treatment was to align the teeth within 
segments. In this case, the two central incisors were one segment, and 
the molar-lateral incisor portions of the arch on either side were separate 
segments.</p>

<p>Intrusion of upper incisors requires a lingual arch. At the first appointment, 
mandibular and maxillary molar bands were fitted, and the upper molar bands 
were sent to the lab for fabrication of the lingual arch. These bands and 
the lingual arch were placed at the next appointment.</p>

<p>A continuous arch wire must not be used when the goal is intrusion. Such arch 
wires always are extrusive, not intrusive, because when steps are placed in 
the arch wire to change the vertical relationship of brackets, the force is 
far above the amount needed for intrusion. The relationship of the teeth 
changes, but the tooth movment is extrusion of the presumed anchor teeth, 
not intrusion of the ones where this was desired.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="501" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_10a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_10a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>First appointment, begin alignment within segments.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_10b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_10b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right lateral</label><caption><p>First appointment, begin alignment within segments.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_10c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_10c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, right lateral</label><caption><p>First appointment, begin alignment within segments.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Incisor Intrusion (cont.)</title><pageText><p>After initial alignment, an intrusion arch was used, first to deliver 
a precisely measured 20 grams (10 grams/tooth) to the maxillary central 
incisors. Intrusion requires light force to obtain the optimal pressure in 
the small PDL area around the apex of the tooth. If the force is too 
heavy, cells in the periapical area of the PDL become necrotic, recruitment 
of osteoclasts is slow, and the bone remodeling necessary for intrusion 
does not occur.</p>

<p>The intrusion arch fits into auxiliary rectangular tubes on the first 
molar bands and is tied to the wire segment in the incisor segment. The 
position of the intrusion arch in the anterior vestibule (images 1 and 2) 
is adjusted until bending it downward to the level of the teeth produces 
20 gm force (images 3 and 4). A force gauge is used to measure the force 
created by deflecting the wire.</p>

<p>Intrusion of maxillary incisors requires the use of a transpalatal lingual 
arch to control the position of the upper molars (image 5).</p>

<p>Note that in this case, the intrusion arch is tied in the midline (image 3). 
The point of attachment of the intrusion arch to the segment wire can be 
varied, depending on what change in tooth position in addition to 
intrusion is desired.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="499" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_11a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_11a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Intrusion arch prior to activation.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="499" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_11b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_11b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, frontal view, activated</label><caption><p>Intrusion arch tied to incisor segment, to deliver 20 grams force.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="499" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_11c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_11c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, lateral view</label><caption><p>Intrusion arch prior to activation.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="499" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_11d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_11d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, lateral view, intrusion arch activated</label><caption><p>Intrusion arch tied to incisor segment, to deliver 20 grams force.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="501" resourceHeight="302" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_12.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_12_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, occlusal view</label><caption><p>Transpalatal lingual arch for stabilization, intrusion arch tied in midline.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Intrusion Progress</title><pageText><p>Two months later (image 1), the maxillary centrals had been intruded somewhat 
and tipped facially. Compare the pretreatment and progress vertical position 
of these teeth (image 2).</p>

<p>Tying an intrusion arch in the midline places the point of force 
application anterior to the center of resistance of the incisors, so they 
would tip facially as they intrude unless the intrusion arch were tied 
back against the molars to prevent this. In Steve’s case, facial 
movement of the incisors was desired, so the intrusion arch was left 
free to slip forward as the teeth responded to the force system.</p>

<p>This tooth movement allowed enough space to place brackets on the lower 
arch without occlusal interferences, and treatment for the lower arch 
began soon thereafter.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="501" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_13b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_13b_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, progress</label><caption><p>Frontal view, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="368" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_13.jpg" thumbnailWidth="65" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_13_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, comparison</label><caption><p>Pretreatment vs progress: note the vertical position of the maxillary 
central incisors.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Extrusive Leveling, Lower Arch</title><pageText><p>Later in treatment, leveling of the lower arch was needed to complete 
correction of the deep overbite. Because a slight increase in face height 
was desired, this was done with a continuous arch wire and an auxiliary 
leveling arch that delivered 150 grams, so that the lower molars would 
be extruded.</p>

<p>An important concept: Intrusion of incisors requires the use of segmented 
arch wires and light force. Continuous arch wires and heavier force 
produce extrusion of posterior teeth, not intrusion of incisors.</p>

<p>Steve had intrusive mechanics in the upper arch, extrusive mechanics in 
the lower arch. The important differences:</p>

<ul><li>Arch wire segments tied into the brackets in the upper arch, continuous 
arch wire tied into the brackets in the lower arch</li>
<li> Light (20 gm) force from the auxiliary wire in the upper arch, 
heavier (150 gm) force from the auxiliary wire in the lower arch</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="498" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_14a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_14a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, not activated</label><caption><p>Auxiliary leveling arch, not activated.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="380" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_14b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="126" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_14b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, activated</label><caption><p>Auxiliary leveling arch, activated by tying to main arch wire.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Maxillary Incisor Torque/Spacing</title><pageText><p>Then active torque was placed in a rectangular maxillary arch wire to bring 
the roots of the incisors to the lingual, and space was distributed around 
the upper incisors to allow build-up of these teeth to normal size (images 
1-3).</p>

<p>Note that space between the maxillary incisors is being adjusted by coil 
springs that were slipped over the arch wire before it was inserted.</p>

<p>A cephalometric radiograph near the end of treatment (image 4) shows the 
change in incisor position, and the cephalometric superimposition 
(image 5) documents both intrusion and torque of the maxillary central 
incisors. The lower incisors were tipped facially slightly as the lower 
arch was leveled.</p>

<p>Now he is ready for the incisor build-ups, which must be coordinated with 
the completion of the orthodontic treatment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="498" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_15a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_15a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Progress: rectangular arch wire for torque, coil springs to adjust 
incisor position.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="498" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_15b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_15b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right lateral</label><caption><p>Progress: rectangular arch wire for torque, coil springs to adjust 
incisor position.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="498" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_15c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_15c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, right lateral</label><caption><p>Progress: rectangular arch wire for torque, coil springs to adjust 
incisor position.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="377" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_16a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_16a_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, ceph</label><caption><p>Cephalometric radiograph near end of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="346" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_16b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="62" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_16b_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, superimp tracing</label><caption><p>Cephalometric superimposition tracing--note the changes in 
incisor position.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Incisor Build-Ups</title><pageText><p>In order to allow the best restorative dentistry, the orthodontist provides 
slightly excessive space before incisor build-ups are done. The ideal 
sequence is:</p>

<ul><li>the brackets are removed from the upper incisors,</li>
<li> the patient goes immediately to the restorative dentist, and</li>
<li> the brackets are reapplied after the restorations are completed, 
so that the excess space can be closed with complete control of tooth 
positions. </li>
</ul><p>A less satisfactory alternative is to position the teeth to be built up as 
precisely as possible as the orthodontic treatment is completed and provide a 
retainer until the restorations are completed. Any excess space then would 
have to be closed with a modified retainer--which is possible but more 
difficult and less precise.</p>

<p>Steve’s maxillary incisor brackets were removed early in the morning, 
the restorations were done the same morning (by Dr. Harald Heymann), and the 
brackets were replaced that afternoon so that closure of the remaining 
space could begin.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_17a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_17a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, pre-buildup</label><caption><p>9 AM, just prior to removal of the arch wire and incisor brackets.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="499" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_17b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_17b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, buildups completed</label><caption><p>1:30 PM same day, back to orthodontist after build-ups.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="498" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_17c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_17c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, continuation</label><caption><p>2 PM same day, brackets and arch wire replaced.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Incisor Build-Ups (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Image 1 shows the appearance of the teeth at 1:30 PM, after completion of the 
restorations, just before the brackets and arch wire were replaced.</p>

<p>Note that as planned, there is still some space in the incisor segment. The 
last step in the orthodontics is final space closure and positioning of the 
teeth.</p>

<p>Image 2 shows the appearance of the teeth at 2 PM the same afternoon, with 
brackets reapplied, the arch wire replaced, and the appliance activated for 
closure of the residual space.</p>

<p>Close coordination of the restorative and orthodontic treatment at this 
stage is important for best results. Any delay between removal of the arch 
wire and brackets and the build-ups is an opportunity for uncontrolled 
shifting of the teeth, which can compromise the quality of the restorations. 
A delay in reapplying the orthodontic appliance is not as critical, but 
orthodontic finishing should proceed as rapidly as possible.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="385" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_18.jpg" thumbnailWidth="125" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_18_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, build-ups</label><caption><p>After completion of build-ups, before the arch wire and brackets 
were replaced.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="398" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_19.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_19_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, treatment continuation</label><caption><p>Same day, continuation of orthodontics.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Treatment Completed</title><pageText><p>Images 1-3 show the appearance of the dentition at the removal of the 
orthodontic appliance five months later. After completion of the incisor 
build-ups, the residual spaces were closed and the teeth were put into 
their final position.</p>

<p>When a space between maxillary central incisors has been closed, long-term 
retention usually is needed. Like most adults, Steve did not like wearing a 
removable retainer that covered the palate. Children tolerate these much 
better than adults.</p>

<p>A fixed retainer, contoured to allow easy flossing and with vertical stops 
to control overbite, was used instead (image 4). After correction of 
excessive overbite, the retainer must maintain the correct bite depth as 
well as alignment. It would be expected to remain in place at least for a 
time equal to the duration of active treatment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="501" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_20a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_20a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, post-tx frontal view</label><caption><p>5 months after build-ups, just after removal of the orthodontic appliance.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_20b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_20b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right lateral</label><caption><p>5 months after build-ups, just after removal of the orthodontic appliance.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_20c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_20c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, left lateral</label><caption><p>5 months after build-ups, just after removal of the orthodontic appliance.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="402" resourceHeight="263" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_21.jpg" thumbnailWidth="122" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_21_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, fixed retainer</label><caption><p>Bonded maxillary retainer.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #1: Treatment Completed</title><pageText><p>Facial proportions were essentially unchanged during the nearly 2 years 
of treatment (image 1). The mild mandibular asymmetry was not corrected, 
because it was not a problem to the patient, and indeed is noticed only 
on careful examination.</p>

<p>A comparison of the smile appearance before and after treatment (image 2) 
shows the esthetic effect of this combination of orthodontic and 
restorative treatment.</p>

<p>Cephalometric radiographs before and after treatment (image 3) show the 
changes in incisor position and overbite that were obtained. Note that the 
roots of the maxillary incisors were torqued lingually, improving the 
inclination of these teeth.</p>

<p>The effect of this tooth movement on the position of the teeth can be seen 
in the comparison views of before and after treatment (images 4 and 5).</p>

<p>Total treatment time was just over 2 years.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_22.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_22_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, post-tx face</label><caption><p>Posttreatment facial proportions.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_23.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_23_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, smile comparison</label><caption><p>Smile comparisons pre- to posttreatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_24_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, cephalometrics</label><caption><p>Pre- and posttreatment cephalometric radiographs.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="198" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_25a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="55" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_25a_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, frontal change</label><caption><p>Pre- and posttreatment occlusion, frontal view.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="198" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_25b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="55" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_25b_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, lateral change</label><caption><p>Pre- and posttreatment occlusion, lateral view.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Case #2: Severe Perio / Fiber Section</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Case #2: Severe Perio/Fiber Section Surgery</title><pageText><p>Now let’s look at a second case, a young adult whose main reason for 
treatment was the control of severe periodontal problems and who had an 
adjunctive periodontal surgical procedure to facilitate orthodontic 
retention.</p>

<p>Nancy was only in her 20s when she developed severe periodontal disease. 
After treatment brought the disease under control, she was referred for 
orthodontics by her periodontist, who felt that maintaining control would 
be more likely if her severe crowding were corrected.</p>

<p>Nancy would not have sought orthodontic treatment otherwise, but said she 
would appreciate the dental esthetic improvement from aligning her upper 
incisors, which detracted from her smile (image 2). On profile examination, 
no disproportions were apparent (images 3, 4).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_26.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_26_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, outline</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="243" resourceHeight="311" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_27a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="63" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_27a_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, frontal view</label><caption><p>Irregular maxillary incisors were apparent on smile.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="225" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_27b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_27b_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, profile</label><caption><p>Normal jaw proportions are seen in the profile view.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="397" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_27.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_27_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, combined</label><caption><p>Esthetics: a consideration but not the main reason for treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #2: Initial Records</title><pageText><p>Although her molar relationship was Class II bilaterally, Nancy had 
minimal overjet with severe crowding and rotation of the maxillary 
incisors. There was only moderate crowding in the lower arch.</p>

<p>The upper lateral incisors were very large, and the central incisors 
were each rotated 45 degrees. The severe crowding in the maxillary arch, 
therefore, had two causes: (1) the Class II molar relationship with 
minimal overjet, and (2) the tooth-size discrepancy created by the large 
lateral incisors.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="324" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_28a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="148" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_28a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 27, prior to orthodontics.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="379" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_28b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="127" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_28b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right lateral</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 27, prior to orthodontics.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_28c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_28c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, left lateral</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 27, prior to orthodontics.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="320" resourceHeight="258" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_29a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="99" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_29a_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, maxillary occlusal</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 27, prior to orthodontics.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="334" resourceHeight="230" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_29b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="116" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_29b_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, mandibular occlusal</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 27, prior to orthodontics.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #2: Initial Records (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The intraoral radiographs (image 1) showed the extent of bone loss in 
multiple areas. Note particularly the extensive pocketing on the distal 
of the upper right 2nd premolar.</p>

<p>A major indication for a full series of periapical radiographs is the 
presence of widespread periodontal disease. For a patient like Nancy, a 
panoramic radiograph prior to orthodontic treatment is not sufficient. 
Detailed images of areas with potential disease are necessary.</p>

<p>The cephalometric radiograph and tracing (image 2) confirmed a dental but 
not a skeletal Class II malocclusion, i.e., the Class II molar relationship 
was due to a forward position of the upper molars.</p>

<p>For an adult patient, cephalometric analysis has two purposes: (1) to allow 
a more refined diagnosis (for example, in Nancy's case, so that the cause 
of the Class II malocclusion could be described more precisely), and (2) 
to make it possible to use superimposition tracings to follow the course 
of treatment.</p>

<p>The second reason is the compelling one for cephalometric radiology in most 
orthodontic treatment. You often can make the diagnosis accurately enough 
for appropriate treatment planning without cephalometric analysis, but it 
is impossible to know exactly what is happening in treatment without serial 
radiographs that can be superimposed.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="238" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_66.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="66" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_66_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, intraoral radiographs</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 27, intraoral radiographs.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="258" resourceHeight="307" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_31a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_31a_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, ceph</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 27, cephalometric radiograph.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="255" resourceHeight="322" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_31b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="63" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_31b_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, ceph tracing</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 27, dental but not skeletal Class II.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #2: Treatment Plan</title><pageText><p>The treatment plan for Nancy emphasized continued treatment to keep periodontal 
disease under control. A patient like this who has orthodontic treatment 
needs frequent recall for periodontal maintenance, perhaps as frequently 
as she sees the orthodontist, certainly at not more than 2-3-month 
intervals.</p>

<p>The plan was to extract the maxillary right 1st premolar and the maxillary 
left 2nd premolar, which was selected for extraction because of its poor 
periodontal prognosis (see the intraoral radiographs, previous screen) even 
though the orthodontic treatment would have been easier if both first 
premolars could have been removed.</p>

<p>Because of the limited posterior anchorage, a maxillary transpalatal arch 
to stabilize the position of the upper molars was planned, and the canines 
were to be retracted separately before the incisors were aligned, which 
would also reduce the strain on the posterior teeth.</p>

<p>Gingival surgery to section the gingival elastic fibers was planned because 
it would be critically important in maintaining the rotation correction 
for the maxillary central incisors. The fiber section procedure is most 
effective if it is done after the teeth are in their final position (i.e., 
rotations have been corrected) but before the orthodontic appliance is 
removed, so that the teeth can be held in position while healing occurs.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_32.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_32_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #2: Progress, 18 Months Treatment</title><pageText><p>After 18 months, the maxillary incisors had been aligned and the extraction 
spaces were closed. The improved alignment was apparent on smile (image 
1). On the maxillary occlusal view, note that the transpalatal lingual 
arch has been removed after completion of closure of the extraction space. 
The large maxillary lateral incisors were reduced in width as much as 
feasible without going all the way through the proximal enamel (image 
2), and the mild mandibular incisor crowding was corrected by slight expansion 
of the arch (image 3).</p>

<p>At this point (image 4), she was ready for the fiber section surgery, 
to release the tension in the gingival elastic fibers created by correcting 
the rotation of the incisors.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="355" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_33a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="63" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_33a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, progress smile</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 28, after incisor alignment and space closure in the upper arch.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="356" resourceHeight="231" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_33b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_33b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, maxillary occlusal</label><caption><p>Incisor alignment and space closure in the upper arch.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="356" resourceHeight="268" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_33c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="106" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_33c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, mandibular occlusal</label><caption><p>Nonextraction alignment of lower arch.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="382" resourceHeight="204" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_34.jpg" thumbnailWidth="150" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_34_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, frontal</label><caption><p>Progress, ready for fiber section surgery.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #2: Fiber Section Surgery</title><pageText><p>With the orthodontic appliance in place, the periodontist (Dr. Ray Williams) 
carried out the gingival surgery.</p>

<p>The first step was facial (image 1) and lingual (image 2) incisions within 
the gingival sulcus to section gingival fibers and allow repositioning of 
the frenum.</p>

<p>Then the gingival papillae were sectioned almost but not quite to the tip 
(image 3) and sutured into position (image 4), to minimize shrinkage of 
the papillae during healing.</p>

<p>Two weeks later, healing was essentially complete (image 5).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="395" resourceHeight="228" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_35a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="139" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_35a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, facial incisions</label><caption><p>Facial incisions, for repositioning of the frenum.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="387" resourceHeight="270" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_35b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="115" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_35b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, lingual incisions</label><caption><p>Lingual incisions to base of gingival sulcus.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="387" resourceHeight="228" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_36a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="136" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_36a_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, papilla split</label><caption><p>Incisions in gingival papillae to section gingival elastic fibers.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="390" resourceHeight="215" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_36b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="145" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_36b_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, papillae sutured</label><caption><p>Papillae sutured after incisions.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="402" resourceHeight="202" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_36c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="159" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_36c_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, healing at 2 weeks</label><caption><p>Healing at 2 weeks.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #2: Completion of Treatment</title><pageText><p>Treatment was completed and orthodontic appliances were removed at 24 
months. Periodontal control had been maintained successfully, and the 
fiber section procedure also succeeded in maintaining papilla height, which 
is important in esthetically sensitive areas like the maxillary incisor 
region. She liked the change in her dental and facial appearance 
(images 1, 2). The change in smile esthetics was particularly pleasing 
(image 3).</p>

<p>The maxillary premolar extraction spaces were closed largely by retraction 
of the canines, so that the Class II molar relationship was maintained 
and overjet did not develop (image 4). Note the improved contours and 
color of the gingiva, reflecting an improvement in periodontal health 
even though significant bone loss still is present.</p>

<p>At this point the teeth were well aligned in both arches, but retention 
would be important. In patients who have had bone loss, deep undercuts 
around the teeth make palate-covering retainers impractical. Like most 
adult patients, Nancy had thermoplastic suckdown retainers for both arches, 
made with undercuts waxed out. These were worn full-time initially, then on 
a decreasing part-time basis after the first 4 months.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="235" resourceHeight="294" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_37a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="64" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_37a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, post-tx frontal</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 29, at completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="229" resourceHeight="334" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_37b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="55" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_37b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, post-tx profile</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 29, at completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_38.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_38_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, smile comparison</label><caption><p>Smile before and after treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_39.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_39_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, dental relationships</label><caption><p>Dental relationships after treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #2: Completion of Treatment (cont.)</title><pageText><p>In the posttreatment panoramic radiograph (image 1), areas of bone loss 
related to the original periodontal disease can be seen, but there has been 
no progression during the orthodontic treatment, and some improvement can 
be observed especially in the maxillary right premolar area.</p>

<p>Comparison with the pretreatment radiographs (image 2) shows that extraction 
of the maxillary right 2nd premolar and closure of the extraction space 
eliminated one of the worst periodontal defects. Note the bone fill-in in 
the old 2nd premolar extraction site.</p>

<p>Fortunate results of this type can occur if the area of a periodontal defect 
is curetted regularly as the orthodontics proceeds, but cannot be expected 
routinely. On the other hand, with good periodontal maintenance, the 
periodontal condition should not become worse during even extensive 
orthodontic treatment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="374" resourceHeight="170" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_40.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="75" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_40_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, post-tx pan</label><caption><p>Posttreatment panoramic radiograph.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="342" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_41.jpg" thumbnailWidth="140" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_41_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, x-ray comparison</label><caption><p>Pre- and posttreatment radiographs showing improvement in 2nd premolar area.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #2: Two-Year Recall</title><pageText><p>On 2-year recall, Nancy was wearing retainers only at night, and her 
periodontal condition was being maintained quite nicely. Her smile 
esthetics remained good (image 1).</p>

<p>The alignment and occlusion of the teeth were well maintained after 2 
years (image 2). Although she admitted that her retainer wear had become 
sporadic after the first year, the severely rotated maxillary incisors 
were still well aligned.</p>

<p>Almost surely, that would not have been the case without the fiber section 
surgery. Sectioning stretched gingival fibers after rotated teeth have been 
corrected is critically important for long-term retention. Teeth that have 
been severely rotated, like Nancy’s upper central and lateral incisors, 
simply will not stay aligned without surgical release of the pull of gingival 
elastic fibers.</p>

<p>In this case, perio surgery was needed not only before orthodontics to help 
bring disease under control but also as an adjunct to successful 
orthodontics.</p>

<p>Given the severity of bone loss in several areas, Nancy will need to be 
followed carefully long term--but her periodontal prognosis is significantly 
better after the orthodontics.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_42.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_42_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, 2 year facial</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 31, 2-year recall.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="426" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_43.jpg" thumbnailWidth="113" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_43_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, 2 year dental</label><caption><p>Nancy, age 31, 2-year recall.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Case #3: Adjunctive Cosmetic Surgery</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Case #3: Adjunctive Cosmetic Surgery</title><pageText><p>Now let’s look at a third adult patient, for whom adjunctive facial 
cosmetic surgery was an important part of the treatment plan.</p>

<p>Ronald (image 2) inquired at age 48 about the possibility of cosmetic bonding 
of his incisor teeth to improve their appearance. His motivation definitely 
was to improve his facial and dental appearance--and though it was not said 
in so many words, to improve his social image and interactions.</p>

<p>His mustache took attention away from what in novels often is described as 
a “weak chin.” He had poor throat form, with a quite obtuse 
lip-chin-throat angle (the ideal is near 90 degrees) and minimal throat 
length.</p>

<p>His chief concern was the appearance of his maxillary incisors (image 3). 
The left lateral incisor was congenitally missing, and the midline was 
shifted severely to that side.</p>

<p>Despite the missing maxillary lateral incisor, the maxillary incisors 
were crowded and malaligned. There was severe crowding in the mandibular 
arch, with a malformed mandibular right second molar (image 4).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_44.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_44_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, outline</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="438" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_45.jpg" thumbnailWidth="110" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_45_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, pre-tx face</label><caption><p>Ronald, age 48, prior to treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="378" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_46.jpg" thumbnailWidth="127" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_46_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, front teeth</label><caption><p>Maxillary incisor crowding, left lateral incisor missing, midline off.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_47.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_47_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, occlusal views</label><caption><p>Moderate maxillary, severe mandibular crowding.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #3: Initial Records</title><pageText><p>His periodontal condition generally was good, except for bone loss and 
pocketing on the distal of the mandibular right second molar, where a 
partially impacted third molar still was present (image 1).</p>

<p>Current research has shown that the chance of periodontal breakdown 
adjacent to a third molar in this position is quite high. A partially 
erupted mandibular third molar is a greater risk for long-term problems 
than a completely impacted one.</p>

<p>Multiple restorations were present, and the mandibular left second premolar 
had a root canal filling. An endo-treated tooth can be moved, but its 
poorer long-term prognosis must be considered in treatment planning.</p>

<p>Cephalometric analysis (image 2) showed a skeletal Class II jaw 
relationship, with chin deficiency and somewhat increased face height. 
The relationship of the upper incisors to the maxilla is reasonably 
normal; the lower incisors are severely protrusive relative to the 
deficient chin. For this reason, overjet was normal.</p>

<p>The rotation of the palatal plane (which should be tipped in the other 
direction, intermediate between the occlusal plane below and true 
horizontal line above) indicates a skeletal open bite tendency.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="270" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_48.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="75" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_48_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, panoramic radiograph</label><caption><p>Note the periodontal problem area distal to the mandibular right second molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_49.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_49_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, ceph/tracing</label><caption><p>Chin deficiency, prominent lower incisors, rotated palatal plane.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #3: Treatment Plan</title><pageText><p>Aligning the maxillary incisors and correcting the midline would require space 
to bring the central incisors around to the right, and extracting the 
right lateral incisor would allow the greatest improvement in the midline. 
The major esthetic problem with using canines to replace missing lateral 
incisors is their greater crown height, but Ronald’s low lip line 
meant that the gingival margins were not visible even on smile, and the 
cusp tips could be reshaped. The decision, therefore, was to extract the 
right maxillary lateral incisor and substitute the canines for the 
laterals.</p>

<p>The goal in the lower arch was to align the teeth without retracting the 
lower incisors, which would create excessive overjet, so extraction of 
mandibular second premolars was chosen. Extraction of the remaining third 
molar was an important aspect of bringing periodontal disease 
under control.</p>

<p>Because of the deficient chin and poor throat form, a lower border osteotomy 
of the mandible to bring the chin forward (a type of genioplasty) was 
suggested. He agreed to consider this as the orthodontic treatment came 
to a close.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_50.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_50_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #3: Progress</title><pageText><p>After 16 months of orthodontic treatment, the teeth were aligned. In the 
maxillary arch, there was still a small amount of space to bring the 
maxillary central incisors around to the right to improve the midline 
discrepancy, and the mandibular second premolar extraction sites were not 
quite closed. The cusp tips of the maxillary canines had not yet been 
flattened to make them look more like lateral incisors.</p>

<p>Ceramic brackets were used on the maxillary incisors to reduce the 
esthetic impact of the orthodontic appliance. Although these brackets 
are more esthetic, they make treatment more difficult, and their use 
is limited to highly visible teeth only.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="341" resourceHeight="222" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_51a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_51a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Age 49, 16 months progress, teeth aligned, space nearly closed.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="399" resourceHeight="258" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_51b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="124" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_51b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right lateral</label><caption><p>Age 49, 16 months progress, teeth aligned, space nearly closed.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="369" resourceHeight="247" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_51c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_51c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, left lateral</label><caption><p>Age 49, 16 months progress, teeth aligned, space nearly closed.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="378" resourceHeight="269" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_52a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_52a_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, maxillary occlusal</label><caption><p>Age 49, 16 months progress, teeth aligned, space nearly closed.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="378" resourceHeight="268" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_52b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="113" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_52b_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, mandibular occlusal</label><caption><p>Age 49, 16 months progress, teeth aligned, space nearly closed.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #3: Progress (cont.)</title><pageText><p>At that point, the issue of genioplasty was brought up again. His appearance 
on smile was significantly improved (image 1), but he was now aware that 
chin deficiency was a major part of his esthetic problem.</p>

<p>The cephalometric radiograph (image 2) clearly shows the protrusion of the 
lower incisors relative to the chin. Cephalometric superimposition 
(image 2, right) shows that the alignment in both arches was done with 
little change in incisor position--the incisors in both arches had been 
retracted very slightly. In this tracing, the pretreatment position is 
the solid line.</p>

<p>Ronald requested further information about surgical repositioning of 
his chin.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="408" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_53.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_53_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, progress, face</label><caption><p>Improved smile, obvious chin deficiency, and poor throat form on profile view.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="407" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_54.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_54_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, ceph / tracing</label><caption><p>Protrusive lower incisors, little change in incisor position during treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #3: Computer Image Prediction</title><pageText><p>It is possible now to use computer technology to show patients the probable 
outcome of a procedure like moving one of the jaws or the chin. The prediction 
is based on making the bony change on the cephalometric tracing and using 
algorithms that relate soft tissue to hard tissue change to create the 
predicted soft tissue image.</p>

<p>For Ronald, a cephalometric prediction tracing was prepared in a computer 
imaging software program (Dolphin Imaging) (image 1). Note that the chin has 
been moved forward. Then the prediction algorithms were used to produce 
the soft tissue profile change (image 2). At the chin, the soft tissue moves 
forward almost 1:1 with the hard tissue--note the corresponding amount of 
change in the bony and soft tissue chin created within the computer 
program. In the absence of growth, the predictions are quite accurate for 
chin position and reasonably accurate for lip changes.</p>

<p>Ronald was pleased with the orthodontic progress, and when he was shown the 
predicted effect of repositioning his chin (image 3), he liked it, so a 
lower border osteotomy to augment the chin was planned.</p>

<p>Research has shown that showing patients computer image predictions of this 
type greatly improves their ability to understand the esthetic implications 
of orthognathic surgery procedures. The research also shows that (if the 
predictions are realistic) there is little or no risk of raising 
expectations that cannot be met.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="397" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_55a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="71" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_55a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, ceph prediction</label><caption><p>Cephalometric prediction of chin augmentation.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="362" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_55b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="64" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_55b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, profile prediction</label><caption><p>Ceph / soft tissue profile predictions.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_55c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_55c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, profiles compared</label><caption><p>Present profile compared to prediction.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #3: Lower Border Osteotomy</title><pageText><p>These radiographs show the cut in the lower border of the mandible that is 
used to slide the bony chin forward. This improves both the projection of the 
soft tissue chin and throat form. The angle of the cut controls the extent 
to which the chin also moves upward as it is advanced.</p>

<p>The surgery is done under general anesthesia, working intraorally from an 
incision in the depth of the mandibular vestibule. It does not require 
overnight hospitalization, and morbidity is equivalent to extracting 
premolars or molars bilaterally. If desired, submental fat can be removed 
at the same time to improve throat form--that was not done in this case.</p>

<p>In the superimposition tracing, note the change in the position of the bony 
chin and in the profile. With a lower border osteotomy to reposition the 
bony chin, the soft tissue chin is augmented quite predictably.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="370" resourceHeight="166" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_56.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="74" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_56_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, post-surg pan</label><caption><p>Age 49, after lower border osteotomy to augment chin.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="381" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_57.jpg" thumbnailWidth="126" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_57_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, ceph/tracing</label><caption><p>Cephalometric radiograph and superimposition tracing after chin augmentation.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #3: Treatment Outcome</title><pageText><p>Treatment was completed and the orthodontic appliances were removed 5 
months after the genioplasty, with a total treatment time of 19 months. 
With the canines in the lateral incisor positions, the midline was almost 
completely corrected (image 1). Because the lower incisors were not 
appreciably retracted, overjet remained nearly ideal (image 2).</p>

<p>Toward the end of the orthodontic treatment, the canines were recontoured 
to make them look more like lateral incisors. Note that the high gingival 
margin of the canines is noticeably different from what would be expected 
for lateral incisors--but Ronald does not show the gingival margins 
when he smiles, so only the morphology of the lower two-thirds of the 
crown is important in his smile esthetics.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="336" resourceHeight="201" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal intraoral</label><caption><p>Age 50, completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="250" resourceHeight="246" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="81" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, profile intraoral</label><caption><p>Age 50, completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="356" resourceHeight="199" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="143" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, right lateral view</label><caption><p>Age 50, completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="362" resourceHeight="209" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="139" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, left lateral view</label><caption><p>Age 50, completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="414" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58.jpg" thumbnailWidth="116" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_58_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, composite views</label><caption><p>Age 50, completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Case #3: Treatment Outcome (cont.)</title><pageText><p>These images show the facial change at age 49, from just prior to the 
genioplasty to 5 months later.</p>

<p>Because the gingival margins of the upper teeth are not seen on smile 
(image 1), even on a broad smile beyond what is pictured here, the canine 
substitution for the lateral incisors is esthetically acceptable, and 
the midline deviation has been corrected to the point that it is no 
longer immediately noticeable.</p>

<p>The three-quarter view (image 2) shows the increased chin projection and 
the tightening of skin contours created by moving the chin forward, 
which contributes to a younger look after the genioplasty.</p>

<p>On the profile view (image 3), greater chin prominence and improved throat 
form are apparent. Although dentists often do not consider the esthetics 
of the throat area, it is an important factor in overall facial esthetics.</p>

<p>The presurgery profile, computer prediction and actual outcome are shown 
in image 4. The presurgery profile is on the left, the computer image 
prediction in the center, and the actual profile on the right. Patients 
usually consider, as Ronald did, that the actual result looks better than 
the computer image prediction. He was pleased with the outcome in terms of 
both his dental and facial appearance.</p>

<p>Did the treatment affect his life adjustment? After treatment, he left his 
previous job and started his own English-language newspaper in a European 
city. It is reported to be quite successful.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="430" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_59.jpg" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_59_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Frontal view before/after genioplasty.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="432" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_60.jpg" thumbnailWidth="111" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_60_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, oblique view</label><caption><p>Oblique view before/after genioplasty.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="423" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_61.jpg" thumbnailWidth="113" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_61_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, profile view</label><caption><p>Profile view before/after genioplasty.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="352" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_62.jpg" thumbnailWidth="136" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_62_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, prediction / result</label><caption><p>Prediction compared to actual result.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary/Conclusions</title><pageText><p>Orthodontics for adults makes up about 20% of specialty practice now. 
The motivation for adults is different, and sometimes difficult to 
ascertain. There are two distinct groups of adult orthodontic patients:</p>

<p><i>1) Those who want to improve their situation</i><br/>
They are: younger; motivated primary by psychosocial considerations (want 
to get ahead in the world); candidates for comprehensive rather than adjunctive 
treatment; and interested in the appearance of the orthodontic appliance, 
so are candidates for clear brackets, lingual orthodontics, or Invisalign.</p>

<p><i>2) Those who want to keep what they have</i><br/>
They are: older; motivated primarily by concerns about their oral health 
and jaw function; candidates for adjunctive rather than comprehensive 
treatment; and not particularly concerned about the appearance of the 
appliance (bonded metal brackets are just fine).</p>

<p class="noSpaceAfter">Periodontal considerations always are important:</p>
<ul class="noSpaceBefore"><li>Pocketing/mucogingival problems are likely to be present</li>
  <li>Bone loss affects orthodontic forces/moments</li>
</ul><p class="noSpaceAfter">Patient management can be more difficult:</p>
<ul class="noSpaceBefore"><li>Adults don't adapt as well to orthodontic treatment</li>
  <li>Pain control requires medication, with Vioxx 50 mg a good choice</li>
  <li>Explanation and reassurance take additional time</li>
</ul><p>But orthodontics for adults can be a highly gratifying part of all types of 
dental practice. It brings dentists in family practice and specialty practice 
into treatment teams, in a way that is stimulating to the practitioners and 
beneficial to the patients. Better dentistry is the result.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Self-Test Referral</title><pageText><p>The self-test section of this program is designed to help you be sure you 
have understood the material. Take it now, and use it as a guide for further 
study and review.</p>

<p>Copyright 2003, UNC Dept. of Orthodontics</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>What is the percentage of adults in the orthodontic patient pool in the United 
States at present?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>5%</choice><choice>10%</choice><choice>15%</choice><choice>20%</choice><choice>25%</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, as of 2000 about 20% of all orthodontic patients were 
adults. The percentage was down from the 25% of 1995, but the absolute number 
of adults seeking treatment has remained at the 1995 level, so it’s 
still a significant proportion of the total orthodontic treatment pool.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. As of 2000 about 20% of all orthodontic patients were 
adults. The percentage was down from the 25% of 1995, but the absolute number 
of adults seeking treatment has remained at the 1995 level, so it’s 
still a significant proportion of the total orthodontic treatment pool.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_03_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>Which of the following are characteristics of the group of adults who seek 
treatment to improve their present situation?</p>

<p>
a. Younger, usually between 20 and 40<br/>
b. Want comprehensive treatment<br/>
c. Motivation usually is psychosocial<br/>
d. Often concerned about visibility of braces
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, all these are characteristics of the group of adults 
who seek treatment to improve their present situation. They tend to be 
younger, want comprehensive treatment, have a primarily psychosocial 
motivation, and often are willing to pay extra for braces that are less 
visible, such as ceramic brackets, lingual brackets, or the clear plastic 
aligners advertised as “invisible braces.”</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. all these are characteristics of the group of adults 
who seek treatment to improve their present situation. They tend to be younger, 
want comprehensive treatment, have a primarily psychosocial motivation, 
and often are willing to pay extra for braces that are less visible, such 
as ceramic brackets, lingual brackets, or the clear plastic aligners advertised 
as “invisible braces.”</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_23.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_23_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>Which of the following are characteristics of the group of adults who 
seek treatment to maintain their teeth and their dental health?</p>

<p>
a. Older, usually over 30<br/>
b. Want treatment for specific problems<br/>
c. Motivation usually is psychosocial<br/>
d. Often concerned about visibility of braces
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the first two statements describe the patients whose 
goal is to maintain their dentition, but the last two do not. These patients 
tend to be older and want treatment for specific problems that require a 
multidisciplinary dental approach rather than comprehensive orthodontic 
treatment. They are motivated by health concerns more than psychosocial 
ones and usually are not concerned about the visibility of orthodontic 
appliances once they decide they need treatment.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The first two statements describe the patients whose 
goal is to maintain their dentition, but the last two do not. These patients 
tend to be older and want treatment for specific problems that require a 
multidisciplinary dental approach rather than comprehensive orthodontic 
treatment. They are motivated by health concerns more than psychosocial 
ones and usually are not concerned about the visibility of orthodontic appliances 
once they decide they need treatment.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_08.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_08_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>Which of the following statements accurately describe the prevalence of perio 
problems in patients with severe malocclusion?</p>

<p>
a. Periodontal pocketing is more prevalent than mucogingival problems at 
all ages.<br/>
b. The prevalence of mucogingival problems peaks at about age 40, then 
declines.<br/>
c. By age 25, the majority of patients with severe malocclusion have evidence 
of mucogingival problems.<br/>
d. For patients with severe malocclusion, the prevalence of periodontal 
pocketing doubles between the early 30s and the early 40s.
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>none of the above</choice><choice>a and b</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, for patients seen in the dentofacial clinic where those 
with very severe malocclusion are evaluated, none of these statements are 
correct. The data show that mucogingival problems are more prevalent than 
pocketing below age 25. The prevalence of mucogingival problems peaks in the 
early 20s, not at age 40, and declines in the late 20s. At age 25, about 
one-third of dentofacial patients have evidence of mucogingival problems, 
but it never becomes a majority. The prevalence of pocketing is about the 
same (nearly two-thirds of the patients) in the age 33-39 and over 40 age 
groups—the rapid increase in perio problems is over by the mid-30s.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. For patients seen in the dentofacial clinic where those 
with very severe malocclusion are evaluated, none of these statements are 
correct. The data show that mucogingival problems are more prevalent than 
pocketing below age 25. The prevalence of mucogingival problems peaks in 
the early 20s, not at age 40, and declines in the late 20s. At age 25, about 
one-third of dentofacial patients have evidence of mucogingival problems, 
but it never becomes a majority. The prevalence of pocketing is about the 
same (nearly two-thirds of the patients) in the age 33-39 and over 40 age 
groups—the rapid increase in perio problems is over by the mid-30s.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_10.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_10_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>(A) Stripping of gingival tissues away from the facial surface of incisors is 
a particular risk when nonextraction orthodontic treatment is performed 
because (B) Expansion of the arches to obtain space moves the teeth facially 
and stresses the gingival attachment.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct, these statements are true and related. When the arches 
are expanded in nonextraction treatment, the teeth have to be moved 
facially. Then stripping of the gingival tissues is a risk, even more in 
adults than in children. This is a major limitation of how much the 
dental arches can be expanded to bring teeth into alignment.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. These statements are true and related. When the arches 
are expanded in nonextraction treatment, the teeth have to be moved facially. 
Then stripping of the gingival tissues is a risk, even more in adults than 
in children. This is a major limitation of how much the dental arches can 
be expanded to bring teeth into alignment.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_11.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_11_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>What is optimal force for tipping a tooth to a new position when half 
the alveolar bone support has been lost?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>10 grams</choice><choice>25 grams</choice><choice>50 grams</choice><choice>75 grams</choice><choice>100 grams</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, when half the alveolar bone has been lost, half the 
periodontal ligament area over which force would be distributed has also 
been lost, so the optimal force would be half the amount for tipping with 
normal bone support (50 grams), or 25 grams.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. When half the alveolar bone has been lost, half the 
periodontal ligament area over which force would be distributed has also 
been lost, so the optimal force would be half the amount for tipping with 
normal bone support (50 grams), or 25 grams.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_14.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_14_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>For a premolar to be moved bodily after half the alveolar bone support 
had been lost, how would the ratio between the force to move the tooth and 
the moment to control root position be affected?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>No effect on this ratio</choice><choice>Increased force relative to the moment</choice><choice>Increased moment relative to the force</choice><choice>Necessary to double the moment, otherwise the tooth would tip</choice><choice>Effect unpredictable, would depend on the shape of the root</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct. The force would need to be reduced from what would 
be used with normal bone support, but because bone loss increase the 
distance from the point of force application to the center of resistance 
of the root, the moment would have to be increased relative to the force.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The force would need to be reduced from what would be 
used with normal bone support, but because bone loss increase the distance 
from the point of force application to the center of resistance of the root, 
the moment would have to be increased relative to the force.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_17_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>(A) Adults tend to tolerate the irritations of orthodontic treatment better 
than children because (B) Almost all adults have a higher pain tolerance.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, both of these statements are false. As a rule, adults 
don’t tolerate the irritations of orthodontic treatment as well as 
children, and it’s not true that older patients necessarily have a 
higher tolerance for orthodontic pain. One of the modern pain-relieving 
agents is needed routinely for adults at the beginning of treatment, and 
the addition of a mild tranquilizer can help some of the more severely 
affected adults—something that’s almost never needed 
with children.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. Both of these statements are false. Adults don’t 
tolerate the irritations of orthodontic treatment as well as children, as 
a rule, and it’s not true that older patients necessarily have a 
higher tolerance for orthodontic pain. One of the modern pain-relieving 
agents is needed routinely for adults at the beginning of treatment, and 
the addition of a mild tranquilizer can help some of the more severely 
affected adults—something that’s almost never needed with children.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/con_19.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/con_19_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>What amount of force would be required to intrude a pair of elongated maxillary 
central incisors?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>10 grams</choice><choice>20 grams</choice><choice>50 grams</choice><choice>75 grams</choice><choice>100 grams</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the correct force for intrusion of a single tooth 
would be 10 grams, so for two central incisors 20 grams would be needed. 
The only way to obtain the precisely calibrated force necessary for this 
type of tooth movement is to use an auxiliary spring to deliver the force 
just to those two teeth. A continuous arch wire must not be used.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The correct force for intrusion of a single tooth 
would be 10 grams, so for two central incisors 20 grams would be needed. The 
only way to obtain the precisely calibrated force necessary for this type of 
tooth movement is to use an auxiliary spring to deliver the force just to 
those two teeth. A continuous arch wire must not be used.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="376" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_64.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_64_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>Why should an elongated maxillary third molar be extracted before orthodontic 
treatment begins?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>Probable periodontal disease around such a tooth</choice><choice>Periodontal breakdown likely to develop during orthodontics</choice><choice>Occlusal interference from its position likely to complicate treatment</choice><choice>No reason to extract it if it’s healthy</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, an elongated maxillary third molar, even if healthy, 
is likely to cause occlusal interferences as tooth movement proceeds. That 
would be the major reason for removing it, especially in the maxillary arch 
where retained third molars are less likely to lead to periodontal problems. 
But in the orthodontic treatment of adults, removal of upper and lower 
third molars before the orthodontics begins usually is needed to minimize 
the chance of problems of some type.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s not the best answer. An elongated third molar, even if 
healthy, is likely to cause occlusal interferences as tooth movement 
proceeds. That would be the major reason for removing it, especially in the 
maxillary arch where retained third molars are less likely to lead to 
periodontal problems. But in the orthodontic treatment of adults, removal 
of upper and lower third molars before the orthodontics begins usually is 
needed to minimize the chance of problems of some type.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="319" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_07.jpg" thumbnailWidth="150" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_07_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 11</title><pageText><p>Which of the following characteristics would be needed in a bracket/wire 
appliance to torque the roots of central incisors lingually?</p>

<p>
a. Rectangular arch wire that nearly fills the bracket slots<br/>
b. Torsional force of 75 grams per tooth<br/>
c. Precious metal wire material<br/>
d. Ceramic, not metal, brackets
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the first two statements describe a torquing arch wire, 
but precious metal is not necessary and is obsolete in modern usage, and 
metal rather than ceramic brackets would be preferred. Depending on the 
size of the bracket and therefore the dimensions of the wire to fill 
the bracket slot, a modern torquing wire would be either stainless steel 
or beta-titanium (nearly pure titanium). Ceramic brackets look better, 
but everything else about them is a disadvantage, not an advantage. That's 
why metal brackets are preferred when torque is needed.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The first two statements describe a torquing arch wire, 
but precious metal is not necessary and is obsolete in modern usage, and 
metal rather than ceramic brackets would be preferred. Depending on the 
size of the bracket and therefore the dimensions of the wire to fill the 
bracket slot, a modern torquing wire would be either stainless steel or 
beta-titanium (nearly pure titanium). Ceramic brackets look better, but 
everything else about them is a disadvantage. That's why metal brackets 
are preferred when torque is needed.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="497" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_65.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_65_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 12</title><pageText><p>When restorative build-ups of incisors are needed in an adult patient to bring 
small teeth to normal size and allow proper alignment/occlusion, at what 
point in treatment should this be done?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>Before any orthodontics begins</choice><choice>Immediately after initial alignment is obtained</choice><choice>Near the end of orthodontics, with slightly excessive space provided</choice><choice>Immediately after the orthodontic treatment is completed</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the best integration of the orthodontic and restorative 
phases of treatment is obtained by doing the build-ups near the end of the 
orthodontic treatment, with the teeth close to their final position but 
with slightly excessive space provided for the convenience of the 
restorative dentist. This allows ideal contouring of the restorations, 
and then the residual space can be closed in the final months of the 
orthodontic treatment. The alternative is to wait until the orthodontics 
is completed, but it can be difficult to have just the right amount of 
space available in that circumstance.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The best integration of the orthodontic and restorative 
phases of treatment is obtained by doing the build-ups near the end of the 
orthodontic treatment, with the teeth close to their final position but 
with slightly excessive space provided for the convenience of the restorative 
dentist. This allows ideal contouring of the restorations, and then the 
residual space can be closed in the final months of the orthodontic treatment. 
The alternative is to wait until the orthodontics is completed, but it can 
be difficult to have just the right amount of space available in 
that circumstance.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="448" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_17_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 13</title><pageText><p>For a patient with severe malocclusion and periodontal disease, at what point 
would orthodontic treatment be indicated?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>As soon as possible, to facilitate the perio treatment</choice><choice>As soon as initial perio treatment is completed</choice><choice>When active disease has been eliminated</choice><choice>When perio control has been established and can be maintained</choice><choice>Not until at least one year after periodontal disease has been eliminated</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct, orthodontics should not begin until perio control has 
been established and can be maintained. Control of the perio problems must 
be maintained throughout any orthodontic treatment. Beginning orthodontics 
before that time risks exacerbation of periodontal breakdown--but there is 
no need to wait for a year after control has been established.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. Orthodontics should not begin until perio control has 
been established and can be maintained. Control of the perio problems must 
be maintained throughout any orthodontic treatment. Beginning orthodontics 
before that time risks exacerbation of periodontal breakdown--but there 
is no need to wait for a year after control has been established.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="238" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_66.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="66" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_66_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Orthodontic treatment accetpable only when control of periodontal disease 
has been established and can be maintained.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 14</title><pageText><p>(A) Gingival surgery to section the elastic gingival fibers is important in 
maintaining the correction of severe rotations because (B) These fibers 
are the major cause of relapse after rotation correction.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, these statements are both true and related. Stretched 
elastic gingival fibers cause relapse after correction of rotations unless 
they are sectioned and allowed to heal with the tooth in the correct 
position, so this adjunctive perio surgical procedure is important when 
rotations have been corrected.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. These statements are both true and related. 
Stretched elastic gingival fibers cause relapse after correction of 
rotations unless they are sectioned and allowed to heal with the tooth in 
the correct position, so this adjunctive perio surgical procedure is 
important when rotations have been corrected.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_36.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_36_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 15</title><pageText><p>What is the relation of exposure of gingiva on smile to the decision to 
use canines as replacements for missing lateral incisors?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>Exposure of gingiva on smile is acceptable, but not exposure with lips relaxed.</choice><choice>Successful canine substitution requires reshaping the crown.</choice><choice>Gingival surgery to change the contours often is needed for canine substitution.</choice><choice>Canines look more like laterals if their greater crown height is not observed.</choice><choice>There is no relationship, shape of crown is the key.</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct. Because of their greater crown height, it is very 
difficult to make canines look like laterals if the entire crown height 
is observed on smile. But if the lip line is low and only part of the 
crown is seen even on smile, that makes canine substitution more esthetic. 
Dental esthetics are particularly important on smile, and exposure during 
smiling, not at rest, is the important criterion.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. Because of their greater crown height, it is very 
difficult to make canines look like laterals if the entire crown height 
is observed on smile. But if the lip line is low and only part of the crown 
is seen even on smile, that makes canine substitution more esthetic. 
Dental esthetics are particularly important on smile, and exposure during 
smiling, not at rest, is the important criterion.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="262" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_67.jpg" thumbnailWidth="47" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_67_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 16</title><pageText><p>Surgery to move the chin forward improves facial esthetics in which of 
the following ways?</p>

<p>
a. Decreases the appearance of a weak chin<br/>
b. Improves throat form and throat length<br/>
c. Decreases the amount of wrinkles in the lower face<br/>
d. Makes the nose look less prominent in the face
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>a, c, and d</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, moving the chin forward improves facial esthetics in 
all these ways. Not only does it make the chin itself more prominent, it 
improves throat form and throat length and stretches the skin in that area 
so that the amount of wrinkles in the lower face decreases. The nose always 
is viewed in relation to the chin, so making the chin more prominent 
decreases the relative prominence of the nose.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. Moving the chin forward improves facial esthetics 
in all these ways. Not only does it make the chin itself more prominent, 
it improves throat form and throat length and stretches the skin in that 
area so that the amount of wrinkles in the lower face decreases. The nose 
always is viewed in relation to the chin, so making the chin more prominent 
decreases the relative prominence of the nose.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="432" resourceLocation="adultortho/images/cas_60.jpg" thumbnailWidth="111" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adultortho/images/cas_60_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>