<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<presentation><title>The Development of Occlusion in the Primary and Transitional Dentition</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>Lorne D Koroluk DMD, MSD, MS, FRCD(C)<br/>UNC Department of Orthodontics &amp; Pediatric Dentistry</additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/titlepage.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Primary Dentition Occlusion</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Purpose of This Module</title><pageText><p>The purpose of this module is to review the development of occlusion in the primary and transitional dentition. In addition to pages 86-91 (5th Ed) or 97-103 (4th Ed) in <i>Contemporary Orthodontics, </i>carefully review Table 3-1 (5th ed)/Table 3-2(4th ed), Figure 3-2 (5th ed)/Fig 3-13 (4th ed), and Fig 3-35 (5th ed)/Fig 3-43 (4th ed). After this preparation and viewing the teaching program, be sure you are able to:</p>
<ul><li>describe the primary to permanent dentition pathways, especially the early and late mesial shifts</li>
<li>describe the location and significance of dental spacing in the primary dentition</li>
<li>discuss the pre-eruptive position of the permanent teeth and its significance</li>
<li>identify the canine and molar relationships that can occur in the primary dentition and discuss the implication of each for development of the permanent dentition occlusion</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Pre-Eruptive Development of the Dental Arches</title><pageText><p>All infants  have a small, relatively under-developed mandible that gives them 
a very convex profile (image 1). As growth progresses, the mandible will grow forward 
more than the maxilla. This leads to a straighter facial profile and increased 
mandibular projection compared to the maxilla.</p>

<p>Intra-orally the maxillary and mandibular arch forms have different shapes in the 
edentulous infant. The maxillary arch is ovoid in shape (image 2), while the mandibular 
arch is V-shaped (image 3). The alveolar ridges contain the developing primary and 
permanent tooth buds.</p>

<p>Initially the upper and lower gums pads touch together with no vertical space. Vertical 
growth of the maxilla and mandible produces an increase in face height which accommodates 
the eruption of the primary teeth. The erupting teeth don’t push the jaws apart; 
the jaws grow apart which creates space for the eruption of the teeth.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="599" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image1.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image1_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, Infant Profile</label><caption><p>The facial profile in an infant is very convex with the mandible being much less 
developed than the maxilla.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="594" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image2.jpg" thumbnailWidth="106" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image2_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, Infant maxillary arch form</label><caption><p>The maxilla in an infant is ovoid in shape.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="395" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image3.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image3_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, Infant mandibular arch form</label><caption><p>The mandible of an infant is V-shaped in comparison to the maxilla arch.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Dental Spacing</title><pageText><p>The eruption of the primary dentition is usually complete by 24-30 months of age. Spacing is common and desirable in the primary dentition and is usually noticeable in two locations called primate spaces (image 1). Why that name for these spaces? Because they are also found in non-human primates.</p>
<p>In the maxillary arch the primate spaces are found between the lateral incisors and the canines. In the mandibular arch they are found between the canine and first molar (image 2).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="333" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image4.jpg" thumbnailWidth="59" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image4_s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>The crowns of the developing permanent incisors lie lingual to the crowns of the primary incisors. The arrows indicate the location of the primate spaces.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image5.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image5_s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Right buccal occlusion of a child with arrows indicating the location of the 
primate spaces.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Dental Spacing (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Spacing between the primary incisors is the normal condition in young children. As they grow and the alveolar processes develop, the spaces may be become larger (image 1).</p>
<p>Lack of spacing in the primary incisor region is abnormal (image 2) and indicates future crowding problems in the transitional and permanent dentitions as the larger permanent incisors erupt.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="324" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image6.jpg" thumbnailWidth="148" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image6_s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Incisor spacing in the maxillary and mandibular arches is common and helps accommodate the larger permanent incisors.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="379" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image7.jpg" thumbnailWidth="127" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image7_s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>This child has no interdental spacing in the primary dentition, which indicates there 
will be future crowding problems when the larger permanent teeth erupt.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Incisor Liability</title><pageText><p>The combined mesiodistal width of the permanent incisors (centrals and laterals) is larger than the width of the primary incisors. This size differential is called the incisor liability. In the maxilla the four permanent incisors are on average 7.6 mm wider than the primary incisors; in the mandible the permanent incisors are 6.0 mm wider.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image8.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image8_s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>In the maxillary arch the sum of the widths of the permanent incisors is approximately 
7.5 mm greater than the sum of the widths of the primary incisors.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image9.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image9_s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>In the mandibular arch the sum of the widths of the permanent incisors is approximately 
6 mm greater than the sum of the widths of the primary incisors.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Overcoming Incisor Liability</title><pageText><p>If the permanent incisors are larger than the primary incisors, where does the space come from to allow their eruption? This lack of space appears also to be compounded by the fact that most jaw growth occurs posteriorly in the ramus of the mandible and the tuberosity region of the maxilla, and not anteriorly in the dental arches.</p>
<p>In the maxillary arch the larger permanent incisors are accommodated by:</p>
<ol><li>Utilization of any interdental spaces between the laterals and centrals. (image 1)</li>
<li>Utilization of the maxillary primate spaces between the laterals and canines. (image 2)</li>
<li>Labial eruption of the incisors increasing arch length and circumference. (image 3)</li>
<li>Increase in width of the dental arch across the canines (intercanine width)</li>
</ol><p>In the mandibular arch the larger permanent incisors are accommodated by:</p>
<ol><li>Utilization of any developmental spaces between incisors.</li>
<li>Increase in intercanine width.</li>
</ol></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="423" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image10.jpg" thumbnailWidth="113" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image10_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, Interdental spaces</label><caption><p>Interdental spaces between the primary incisors help to accommodate eruption of the 
larger permanent incisors.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image11.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image11_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, Primate spaces</label><caption><p>In the maxillary arch primate spaces between the primary lateral incisors and canines 
help accommodate the eruption of the larger permanent incisors.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image12.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image12_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, Labial eruption of the incisors</label><caption><p>In the maxillary arch the larger permanent incisors also erupt labially into a wider 
arc which increases arch circumference.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Classification of Molar Occlusion in the Primary Dentition</title><pageText><p>After eruption of all 20 primary teeth, occlusion of the primary dentition is 
established. The relationship of the distal terminal planes of the upper and lower 
second primary molars are used to classify posterior occlusal relationships. 
Three categories exist:</p>

<ol><li>Flush terminal plane  (image 1)<br/>
The distal surfaces of opposing primary second molars are in the same vertical plane.</li>
<li>Mesial step terminal plane (image 2)<br/>
The mandibular primary second molar terminal plane is located mesial to the terminal plane 
of the maxillary primary second molar. This corresponds to Angle Class I, the normal 
relationship in the permanent dentition.</li>
<li>Distal step terminal plane (Image 3)<br/>
The mandibular primary second molar terminal plane is located distal to the terminal plane 
of the maxillary primary second molar terminal plane. This corresponds to Angle Class II, 
a major type of malocclusion characterized by protruding upper incisors, in the 
permanent dentition.</li>
</ol><p>In the primary dentition the distribution of the categories is as follows:<br/>
Flush terminal plane – 37%<br/>
Mesial terminal plane – 49%<br/>
Distal terminal plane – 14%</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="500" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p07_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="89" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p07_01s.jpg"><label>Image 1, Flush Terminal Plane</label><caption><p>Flush terminal plane relationship with the distal surfaces of opposing primary 
second molars are in the same vertical plane.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="500" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p07_02.jpg" thumbnailWidth="89" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p07_02s.jpg"><label>Image 2, Mesial Step</label><caption><p>In a mesial step relationship, the mandibular primary second molar terminal plane is 
located mesial to the terminal plane of the maxillary primary second molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="540" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p07_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="96" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p07_03s.jpg"><label>Image 3, Distal Step</label><caption><p>In a distal step relationship, the mandibular primary second molar terminal plane is 
located distal to the terminal plane of the maxillary primary second molar terminal plane.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Canine Relationships in the Primary Dentition</title><pageText><p>The antero-posterior relationships of the upper and lower primary canines are also used to classify occlusion in the primary dentition, just as they are in the permanent dentition. There are four categories. The first two are:</p>
<ol class="spaced"><li>End-to-end (image 1)<br/> The long axes of the upper and lower canines are in the same anteroposterior plane.</li>
<li>Class I (image 2)<br/> The cusp tip of the upper canine occludes in the embrasure between the lower canine and lower first molar.</li>
</ol></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="540" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p08_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="96" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p08_01s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>In an end to end primary canine relationship, the long axes of the upper and lower 
canines are in the same anteroposterior plane.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="540" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p08_02.jpg" thumbnailWidth="96" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p08_02s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>In a Class I primary canine relationship, the cusp tip of the upper canine occludes 
in the embrasure between the lower canine and lower first molar.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Canine Relationships in the Primary Dentition (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The third and fourth categories are:</p>
<p>3. Class II (image 1)<br/> The cusp tip of the upper canine occludes mesial to the lower canine in the embrasure between the lower canine and lateral incisor.</p>
<p>4. Class III (image 2)<br/> The cusp tip of the upper canine occludes distal to the embrasure between the mandibular first primary molar and canine.</p>
<p>Different relationships can exist on the right and left sides of the mouth. As well, different combinations of molar and canine relationships are possible. These asymmetric differences may be due to differences in skeletal growth, tooth size differences, and different spacing on the left and right sides of the dental arches.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="540" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p09_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="96" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p09_01s.jpg"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>In a Class II primary canine relationship, the cusp tip of the upper canine occludes 
mesial to the lower canine in the embrasure between the lower canine and lateral incisor.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="540" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p09_02.jpg" thumbnailWidth="96" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s01_p09_02s.jpg"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>In a Class III primary canine relationship, the cusp tip of the upper canine occludes 
distal to the embrasure between the mandibular first primary molar and canine.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Primary to Permanent Dentition</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Transitions from Primary to Permanent Dentition</title><pageText><p>The relationship of the primary second molars and canines, and the position of the primate spaces, greatly influence the eruption of the first permanent molars.</p>
<p>One would expect that:</p>
<p>Mesial terminal plane → Class I molar permanent molars (image 1A)<br/><br/> Flush terminal plane → End-to-end permanent molars (halfway between Class I and II, image 1B)<br/><br/> Distal terminal plane → Class II molar permanent molars (image 1C)<br/><br/> However this is too simplistic. Sometimes it turns out that way, but often it doesn't.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="180" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s02_p01_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="50" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s02_p01_01s.jpg"><label>Transition from primary to permanent dentition</label><caption><p>Expected occlusal relationships of the permanent molars based on the primary molars.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Leeway Space</title><pageText><p>The difference in the combined mesial-distal width of the primary canine, first molar, and second molar and the succedaneous permanent canine, first premolar, and second premolar is called the leeway space. Surprisingly, the width of these three primary teeth is larger than the three permanent teeth. In the mandibular arch the leeway space is on average approximately 2.5 mm per side (5.0 mm per arch) and 1.5 mm per side (3.0 mm per arch) in the maxillary arch. Most of the leeway space is due to the size differential between the mandibular primary second molar and the succedaneous mandibular second premolar.</p>
<p>The variability in leeway space between individuals is quite large due to variability in tooth size.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="385" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image22.jpg" thumbnailWidth="68" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image22_s.jpg"><label>Leeway space</label><caption><p>The primary canine, first, and second molar occupy more space in each quadrant than their permanent successors.  The space left over is the leeway space.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Early Mesial Shift</title><pageText><p>Patients with a flush terminal plane molar relationship in the primary dentition can, and often do develop into a Class I permanent molar relationship when the first permanent molars erupt.</p>
<p>Recall that primate spaces exist distal to the mandibular primary canines. At 6 years of age, when the mandibular first permanent molars erupt, they may shift forward, closing the mandibular primate space. This results in a mesial shifting of the lower molar relative to the upper molar and early establishment of a Class I molar relationship. This is called the early mesial shift.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="250" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s02_p03_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="44" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s02_p03_01s.jpg"><label>Early mesial shift</label><caption><p>The mandibular primate space is used in the early mesial shift.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Late Mesial Shift</title><pageText><p>With the exfoliation of all the primary second molars (age 11-12 years of age), the 
permanent maxillary and mandibular molars shift mesially into the leeway space. Because 
the leeway space is larger in the mandibular arch, the permanent mandibular molars shift 
more mesially than the permanent maxillary molars. This is called the late mesial shift. 
This allows a flush terminal plane in the mixed dentition to transition to a Class I molar 
relationship  in the permanent dentition.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="250" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s02_p04_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="44" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/s02_p04_01s.jpg"><label>Late mesial shift</label><caption><p>The leeway space is used during the late mesial shift.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Influence of Jaw Growth</title><pageText><p>The early mesial shift and late mesial shift do not solely determine the occlusal outcomes during the transition to the permanent dentition. Differential growth of the mandible relative to the maxilla is also an important contributor to molar position. Growth of the jaws carries the dentition along with it, and if one jaw grows forward more than the other, this affects how the upper and lower teeth will be related in space.</p>
<p>In general, the mandible grows forward relative to the maxilla during the transition from the mixed dentition to the early permanent dentition, carrying the lower teeth with it, and this aids in the development of normal (Class I) occlusion of the permanent teeth.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Pathways of Development</title><pageText><p>This figure summarizes the possible pathways during the transition of occlusal relationships between the primary and permanent dentition.</p>
<p>The green arrow shows what will happen if there is more forward growth of the mandible than the maxilla and there is a mesial shift, either early or late. </p>
<p>The dashed green arrow shows what will happen if there is a mesial shift but little or no differential growth.</p>
<p>The blue arrow shows what will happen if there is neither differential growth nor a mesial shift.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="408" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="73" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Flush Terminal Plane Transition</title><pageText><p>Let's start with a child with a flush terminal plane, the most frequent relationship in the primary dentition.</p>
<p>For a child with a flush terminal plane, which is the norm in the primary and mixed dentition,  the transition to the normal Class I relationship in the permanent dentition requires a one-half cusp (3-4 mm) relative forward movement of the lower molar. This is accomplished most readily by a combination of more mandibular than maxillary jaw growth and a mesial shift of the mandibular molars (the solid green arrow).</p>
<p>If there is a mesial shift (early or late) (dashed green arrow) but no more mandibular than maxillary growth, there will be about half as much movement in the direction of Class I. If neither growth nor a mesial shift occurs, an end-to-end relationship of the permanent molars would persist.</p>
<p>About 75% of children with a flush terminal plane in the primary dentition will develop into a Class I molar relationship in the permanent dentition. Because of unfavorable jaw growth and/or minimal mesial shift, the other 25% will not complete the transition to a complete Class I relationship.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="408" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="73" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24_s.jpg"><label>Possible primary to permanent occlusal pathways</label><caption><p>A child with a distal step relationship in the primary dentition is likely to have a Class II relationship in the permanent dentition.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Distal Step Transition</title><pageText><p>With differential growth of the mandible and mesial shift of the molars, a distal step terminal plane in the primary dentition may develop into an end-to-end relationshipin the permanent dentition (which is usually described as a ½ cusp Class II), but that is about as much improvement as one could expect. If minimal differential jaw growth occurs, a full cusp Class II relationship in the permanent dentition will result. It is highly unlikely that a distal step terminal plane will develop into a Class I relationship in the permanent dentition.</p>
<p>This means that children with a distal step relationship in the primary dentition are quite likely to require appropriately timed orthodontic intervention in the future to have a Class I molar relationship in the permanent dentition.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="408" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="73" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24_s.jpg"><label>Possible primary to permanent occlusal pathways</label><caption><p>A child with a flush terminal relationship in the primary dentition is likely to have a Class I relationship in the permanent dentition.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Mesial Step Transition</title><pageText><p>For most children, a mesial step relationship in the primary dentition usually was due to an early mesial shift, and it develops into a Class I molar relationship in the permanent dentition--unless there is significantly more mandibular than maxillary growth during the transition period.</p>
<p>However, if excessive mandibular growth occurs, a mesial step may develop into a Class III molar relationship and Class III malocclusion (lower teeth in front of the upper teeth) in the permanent dentition.</p>
<p>In the primary and early mixed dentitions (before the period of transition from the mixed to the permanent dentition), mesial step relationships are quite uncommon and usually are a sign of excessive mandibular growth or deficient maxillary growth. These growth patterns usually persist during the transition periodinto the permanent dentition years, often changing the mesial step into a Class III occlusal relationship that becomes more severe with increasing age.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="408" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="73" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24_s.jpg"><label>Possible primary to permanent occlusal pathways</label><caption><p>A child with a mesial step relationship in the primary dentition is likely to have a Class I relationship in the permanent dentition unless jaw growth is unfavorable.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary</title><pageText><p>The purpose of this module was review the development of occlusion in the primary and transitional dentition. You should now understand:<br/><br/> a) Dental spacing in the primary dentition<br/> b) Classification of occlusion in the primary dentition<br/> c) Implications of occlusion in the primary dentition<br/> d) Possible pathways from the primary to the permanent dentition</p>
<p>In addition to pages 86-91 (5th Ed) or 97-103 (4th Ed) in <i>Contemporary Orthodontics, </i>carefully review Table 3-1 (5th ed)/Table 3-2(4th ed), Figure 3-2 (5th ed)/Fig 3-13 (4th ed), and Fig 3-35 (5th ed)/Fig 3-43 (4th ed) before you take the self-test. It's important to be sure you understand these important concepts.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>Primate spaces in the primary dentition are usually located:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>In the maxillary arch between the canine and first molar</choice><choice>In the maxillary arch between the lateral incisor and canine</choice><choice>In the mandibular arch between the canine and lateral incisor</choice><choice>In the mandibular arch between the first and second molar</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; in the maxillary arch the primate spaces are between the lateral incisors 
and canines while in the mandibular arch they are  between the canines and first molars.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. In  the maxillary arch the primate spaces are between the lateral 
incisors and canines while in the mandibular arch they are  between the canines and first molars.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage1.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage1_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>In the maxillary arch, which of following facilitates the eruption of the larger incisors 
to replace the primary incisors?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>Labial eruption path of the permanent incisors</choice><choice>Primate spacing between the primary canine and first molar</choice><choice>Expansion of the midpalatal suture</choice><choice>Increase in arch length due to growth in the tuberosity region</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; in the maxillary arch, gaining space for eruption of the larger permanent 
incisors is facilitated by their facially directed eruption, which increases arch length and 
circumference. The maxillary primate space also helps their eruption, but it is located between 
the canine and lateral incisor, not the canine and first molar. Midpalatal suture expansion and 
growth in the tuberosity are important aspects of maxillary growth but they play a minimal role 
in the eruption of the permanent incisors.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. In the maxillary arch, gaining space for eruption of the larger 
permanent incisors is facilitated by their facially directed eruption, which increases arch length 
and circumference. The maxillary primate space also helps their eruption, but it is located between 
the canine and lateral incisor not the canine and first molar. Midpalatal suture expansion and 
growth in the tuberosity are important aspects of maxillary growth but they play a minimal 
role in the eruption of the permanent incisors.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage2.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage2_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>In the primary dentition, the terminal plane of the mandibular second primary molar is 
located behind the terminal plane of the maxillary second primary molar. What is the molar 
classification for this patient?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>Mesial step terminal plane</choice><choice>Flush terminal plane</choice><choice>Distal step terminal plane</choice><choice>Class III terminal plane</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; the classification would be distal step, because the lower molar is distal 
relative to the upper molar. The preferred relationship is a mesial step relationship where the 
terminal plane of the lower molar is mesial to the terminal plane of the upper molar.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. The classification would be distal step, because the lower molar is 
distal relative to the upper molar. The preferred relationship is a mesial step relationship where 
the terminal plane of the lower molar is mesial to the terminal plane of the upper molar.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage3.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage3_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>In the primary dentition which of the following relationships is most common?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>Mesial step terminal plane</choice><choice>Flush terminal plane</choice><choice>Distal step terminal plane</choice><choice>Class III terminal plane</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; mesial step terminal plane occurs in 49% of children while flush terminal plane 
occurs in 37% and distal step terminal plane occurs in 14%.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. Mesial step terminal plane occurs in 49% of children while flush terminal 
plane occurs in 37% and distal step terminal plane occurs in 14%.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>The early mesial shift occurs at the time of the:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>Exfoliation of the primary canines</choice><choice>Eruption of the first permanent molars</choice><choice>Exfoliation of the primary buccal segments</choice><choice>Eruption of the second permanent molars</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; the early mesial shift occurs at the time of the eruption of the first 
permanent molars or approximately 6 years of age. As the permanent molars erupt they drift 
forward closing the primate spaces, especially in the lower arch. The late mesial shift occurs 
with the exfoliation of the primary buccal segments in the late mixed dentition.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. The early mesial shift occurs at the time of the eruption of the first 
permanent molars or approximately 6 years of age. As the permanent molars erupt they drift forward 
closing the primate spaces, especially in the lower arch. The late mesial shift occurs with the 
exfoliation of the primary buccal segments in the late mixed dentition.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText>Leeway space is:</pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>Too small to help patients attain a Class I molar relations</choice><choice>A crucial part of the early mesial shift</choice><choice>Larger in the maxillary arch than the mandibular arch</choice><choice>Due to differences in the size of posterior primary and permanent teeth</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; leeway space is primarily due to the difference in the combined mesial 
distal widths of the primary canine, first molar, second molar and the permanent canine, first 
premolar and second premolar. The three primary teeth are wider than the permanent teeth. Leeway 
space is a crucial part of the late mesial shift which helps patients attain a class I molar 
relationship. The leeway space is larger in the mandibular arch (5mm) than the maxillary arch (3mm).</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. Leeway space is primarily due to the difference in the combined 
mesial distal widths of the primary canine, first molar, second molar and the permanent canine, 
first premolar and second premolar. The three primary teeth are wider than the permanent teeth. 
Leeway space is a crucial part of the late mesial shift which helps patients attain a class I 
molar relationship. The leeway space is larger in the mandibular arch (5mm) than the 
maxillary arch (3mm).</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="385" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image22.jpg" thumbnailWidth="68" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image22_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>What percentage of patients with a flush terminal plane relationship in the mixed dentition 
will develop into a Class I molar relationship in the permanent dentition?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>25</choice><choice>40</choice><choice>60</choice><choice>75</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; 75% of patients with a flush terminal plane relationship in the mixed 
dentition will develop into a class I molar relationship in the permanent dentition. This occurs 
due to the late mesial shift and differential mandibular growth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. 75% of patients with a flush terminal plane relationship in the 
mixed dentition will develop into a class I molar relationship in the permanent dentition. This 
occurs due to the late mesial shift and differential mandibular growth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="408" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="73" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24_s.jpg"><label>Transition of occlusal relationships from the primary to permanent dentitions</label><caption><p>The middle section of this diagram shows that flush terminal plane relationships in 
the primary dentition can become an end to end (25%) or class I relationship (75%) in the 
permanent dentition depending on growth of the mandible and late mesial shift.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>In the maxillary arch the incisor liability is approximately:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>3 mm</choice><choice>4 mm</choice><choice>5 mm</choice><choice>6 mm</choice><choice>7 mm</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; because the maxillary permanent incisors are bigger than their 
primary predecessors by slightly more than 7mm, so that amount of additional space must 
be gained in some way. The additional space needed to align the permanent incisors 
is called the incisor liability.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. The maxillary permanent incisors are bigger than their 
primary predecessors by about 7mm, so that amount of additional space must be gained 
in some way. The additional space needed to align the permanent incisors is called 
the incisor liability.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>The profile of a newborn infant can best be described as:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>concave</choice><choice>straight</choice><choice>convex</choice><choice>any of the above due to birth molding</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; the profile of a newborn infant is quite convex because of the 
relative underdevelopment of the mandible at the time of birth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. The profile of a newborn infant is quite convex because of 
the relative underdevelopment of the mandible at the time of birth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="599" resourceHeight="360" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage6.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage6_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>What is the chance that a child with a distal step relationship of the primary 
molars will self-correct to Class I permanent molars?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>Extremely small</choice><choice>10%</choice><choice>75%</choice><choice>very likely</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; the chance of spontaneous correction of a distal step relationship is 
extremely small, much less than 10%.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. The chance of spontaneous correction of a distal step relationship 
is extremely small, much less than 10%. The positive changes associated with the late mesial 
shift and differential growth of the jaws  usually are not large enough to overcome the 
distal positioning of the lower molars in a patient with a distal step relationship.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="408" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="73" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/Image24_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 11</title><pageText><p>The mandibular arch form of a newborn infant is:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>ovoid</choice><choice>V-shaped</choice><choice>trapezoidal</choice><choice>square</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; the mandibular arch form is rather V-shaped, which is noticeably different than 
the ovoid maxillary arch.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. The mandibular arch form is rather V-shaped, which is noticeably 
different than the ovoid maxillary arch.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="395" resourceLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage8.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="primaryocclusaldev/images/TestImage8_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 12</title><pageText><p>In a child, a lack of primate spaces in the dentition should be interpreted as:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>supernumerary teeth are likely to be present</choice><choice>spacing in the arch is likely to occur long term</choice><choice>crowding of the permanent teeth is likely to occur</choice><choice>child is evolutionarily advanced</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right; a lack of primate spaces strongly suggests that crowding of the 
permanent teeth will occur.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. A lack of primate spaces strongly suggests that crowding of the 
permanent teeth will occur. Even though the spaces are found in less evolved primates, a lack 
of the spaces doesn’t indicate a higher level of evolutionary status.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>