<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<presentation><title>Patterns of Facial Growth</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>Eric D. Bednar, DDS, MS<br/></additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/titlepage.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Facial Growth Patterns</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Introduction</title><pageText><p>Late childhood, from about age 5 or 6 to the age of puberty at ages 11-14, also can be called the preadolescent years and from a dentist’s perspective, the mixed dentition years. The first of those terms focuses on physical growth, the second on the dental changes that occur during that time.</p>
<p>Assessing the physical changes in this age range requires another look at Scammon’s curves, familiar by now but requiring a different focus. Note that the curve for general physical growth is a continuation of what happened during early childhood, with a steadily slowing rate. You didn’t notice, but your parents probably remember that you didn’t outgrow your clothes as rapidly in the elementary school years. But growth continued—you probably needed a new outfit for each school year. And your mandible slowly gained on your maxilla as it grew a little faster.</p>
<p>The dental changes as primary teeth are replaced by permanent teeth are extensive, and the chronology of these events is critically important knowledge for a dentist. They will be reviewed in detail.</p>
<p>After viewing this program and going through the assigned reading in <i>Contemporary Orthodontics</i>, (5th ed, pp. 96-104; 6th ed, pp. 88-96) you should be able to:</p>
<ul>
<li>describe the methods for determining skeletal age and the indications for using them</li>
<li>define dental age and describe the normal eruption timing and sequence for the permanent teeth</li>
<li>determine the dental age of a child age 6-16 from panoramic radiographs</li>
<li>describe common variations in eruption and their clinical significance</li>
<li>discuss the dimensional changes of the dental arches from the primary dentition to age 18</li>
<li>indicate the sources of space to overcome incisor liability</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Scammon's curves    <i><b>﻿Use the figure with page 7 below in this location--and then delete page 7</b></i></label><caption><p>Note the relative lack of change in the physical growth curve in this preadolescent time period--really a slow decline from the end of childhood to the beginning of adolescence</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Assessment of Developmental Age</title><pageText><p>With increasing age, differences between children increase due to the timing of growth. Assessing skeletal age rather than just relying on chronologic age becomes important in the planning of orthodontic treatment. This requires assessment of markers within the skeletal system. </p>
<p>As we have briefly noted in the introduction to this course in the first module, there are two major ways to evaluate skeletal age. The first is hand-wrist radiographs (Fig. 1), which have been the standard method for many years. A radiograph of this type shows 30 small bones, all of which have a predictable sequence of ossification. No single bone is diagnostic, but the relative status of the multiple bones gives an accurate indication of the level of skeletal development. This can be seen just by comparing the hand-wrist radiograph of your patient with the images in a standard reference book. </p>
<p>A similar sequence of maturation of the cervical vertebrae (cervical vertebrae method, CVM) has been developed in recent years. Since these vertebrae can be seen in a cephalometric radiograph, which is an all but universal component of orthodontic diagnostic records (Fig. 2), skeletal age now can be evaluated without an additional radiograph. Does this correlate as well with jaw growth as hand-wrist radiographs? Neither method is always accurate, but it appears that there is not a significant difference between them, and that both are better predictors than chronologic age.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 1, Hand-wrist radiograph</label><caption><p>Skeletal age is revealed by comparison of this radiograph with standard hand-wrist radiographs in a reference text on this subject.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 2, Cervical Vertebrae as Seen in a Ceph</label><caption><p>As with a hand-wrist radiograph, comparison with standard radiographs of the cervical vertebrae reveals the subject's skeletal age. A consensus judgment is that accuracy of hand-wrist and CVM is similar, perhaps slightly better with hand-wrist; but a ceph is taken for almost every orthodontic patient while hand-wrist is an additional radiograph. That pushes the balance of risk vs benefit toward CVM. Interpretation of these radiographs is discussed later in Level I.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>CVM illustrations, stages 1-3</title><pageText><p>Maturation of cervical vertebrae goes through six stages, as shown with a drawing of the stage beside a ceph showing that stage. Stage 1, &gt;2 years before the adolescent growth spurt is not shown.</p>
<p>Fig. 1 shows the drawings for Stage 2, which indicates that the growth spurt is about 1 year ahead. Stage 3 (Fig. 2) is less than 1 year to peak growth. </p>
<p>Fig. 3 shows the later stages: Stage 4, which indicates the peak of growth or a few months later; Stage 5, 1 year after the peak of growth; and Stage 6, &gt;2 years later. By then, the growth spurt has ended, but some growth, particularly of the mandible, continues to the late teens in girls and often to age 20 or so in boys.</p>

<p class="MsoNoSpacing">Maturation of cervical vertebrae goes through six stages, as shown with a drawing of the stage beside a ceph showing that stage. Stage 1, comparable to &gt;2 years before the adolescent growth spurt, is not shown. Stage 2 indicates that the growth spurt is about 1 year ahead; stage 3 is less than 1 year to peak growth.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="411" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_2-2.gif" thumbnailWidth="73" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_2-2_s.gif"><label>Sammon’s curves</label><caption><p>Lymphoid, neural, genital, and general somatic body growth follow different patterns.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig.1,  CVM Stage 2          <i><b>from C Orthod Fig 4.33 2nd drawing on top left side; ceph B beside it</b></i></label><caption><p>At this stage, the adolescent growth spurt has not yet started, or perhaps has just begun.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 2, CVM Stage 3          <i><b>from C Orthod Fig 4.33 CS 3 drawing, ceph B beside it</b></i></label><caption><p>This stage indicates that the adolescent growth spurt has started but it still is about a year to the peak. If Class II growth modification is the treatment plan, it should have started by now.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 3, CVM stage 5        <i><b>from C Orthod Fig 4.33 CS 4 drawing, ceph C beside it</b></i></label><caption><p>This is at or close to the peak of the growth spurt, perhaps slighly after it.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 4, CVM Stage 5.</label><caption><p>At this stage, about one year beyond the peak growth rate, rapid growth is still occurring but is slowing down.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 5, CVM Stage 6</label><caption><p>Stage 6 is about 2 years behond the peak of the growth spurt. At this point growth modification is not likely to succeed because the rate of growth has slowed, even though some growth remains.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>CVM Illustrations, Stages 4-6</title><pageText><p>CVM stage 4 (Fig. 1) is typically at or soon after peak growth; stage 5 (Fig. 2) is about 1 year after the time of peak growth, at about the time of menarche in females; and stage 6 (Fig. 3) is 2 years or more beyond peak growth, when growth is about complete in females but often is still continuing in boys.</p>
<p>Growth modification ideally would already have started by stage 4 but should still be effective if started then. Stage 5 indicates that there is still some but not much adolescent growth remaining for possible growth modification--so for patients with relatively mild skeletal problems, it may represent a last-chance opportunity for functional appliance or headgear therapy, but for patients with more severe problems, it's an indication that's too late to expect resolution of the problem with growth modification.</p>
<p>It is important to realize that stage 6 does not accurately predict the end of jaw growth in patients and readiness for surgery in patients who have excessive mandibular growth, and that hand-wrist radiographs also are not accurate predictors of the end of jaw growth. For that, serial cephs are best.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 1, CVM Stage 4</label><caption><p>Stage 4 is at or perhaps just past the peak of adolescent growth.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 3, CVM Stage 5</label><caption><p>Stage 5 is approximately 1 year beyond the peak of growth.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 3, CVM  stage 6</label><caption><p>Stage 6 is at least 2 years beyond peak growth, when some further growth still is likely (especially in boys) but is slow and limited in magnitude. By then the opportunity for effective growth modification no longer exists.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Correlations Between Biologic Ages</title><pageText><p>One way to think about the predictability of growth stages from biologic markers like CVM is to use the magntitude of the correlation coefficient between the marker and the growth stage. Correlation coefficients between adolescent growth and hand-wrist or CVM are not well established, but they probably are about 0.8, which is a high number for biologic correlations. The plot below shows the relationship between various biologic indicators and growth stage, and all are in the 0.8 range except for dental age.</p>
<p>What does that mean for predictability? Predictability is the correlation coefficient squared. (0.8)2 = 0.64, so you have two chances out of 3 of accurately predicting the growth stage from this indicator. Perhaps that puts CVM and hand-wrist in a more realistic perspective—they’re better than chronologic age, but not as precise as one would like.</p>
<p>Also, note that dental age (DA) doesn't line up so well with the other markers; it has a correlation coefficient of about 0.7. Dentists need to keep in mind that dental age can be determined accurately from examining the dentition with panoramic radiographs, and that predicting the skeletal growth stage from the dental age would have a prediction value of 0.49—about 1 chance in 2 of an accurate prediction. Bottom line: it's better to use other biologic markers to estimate skeletal age; dental age doesn't correlate well enough.</p>
<p> </p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>no label    <i><b>﻿this is Fig. 3.13 in C Orthod 6e</b></i></label><caption><p>Correlation between various markers and chronologic age for one normal child. Note that the dental age line (yellow) trails away from the other markers at about age 9, in the middle of the mixed dentition.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Craniofacial Growth: Cranium and Cranial Base</title><pageText><p>The cranium and cranial base follow Scammon's neural curve and complete most 
of their growth by age 7.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="411" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_2-2.gif" thumbnailWidth="73" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_2-2_s.gif"><label>Scammon’s curves</label><caption><p>Growth of the cranium and cranial base follow the neural curve.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Craniofacial Growth: Maxilla and Mandible</title><pageText><p>The growth pattern of the face is influenced by an interaction between neural and general body growth. The result is that the facial skeleton grows according to a cephalocaudal gradient--the structures closest to the brain, which follows the neural growth curve, grow faster initially and mature earlier than structures closer to the bottom of the head. At birth, the mandible is relatively underdeveloped relative to the maxilla, and it gradually catches up but really doesn't do so until the adolescent growth spurt is completed.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="411" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_4-2.gif" thumbnailWidth="73" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_4-2_s.gif"><label>Maxillary and mandibular growth curves with Scammon’s curves</label><caption><p>The cephalocaudal gradient of growth dictates that the maxilla grows earlier than the mandible which catches up later.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Craniofacial Growth: Facial Soft Tissue</title><pageText><p>It is also important to consider the growth of the facial soft tissues.</p>
<p>Of course the soft tissues that cover the cranium have to follow Scammon's neural curve. You will not be surprised to hear that the cephalocaudal gradient also can be seen in the nose. The nasal bone completes its growth around age 10, but the cartilage and soft tissues of the nose (which are further from the brain) grow and become more prominent during adolescence.</p>
<p>The mandibular musculature grows and becomes stronger during adolescence, as do the lips. The soft tissue chin is something of an exception-it becomes more prominent as the mandible grows forward but the soft tissue itself does not thicken appreciably.</p>
<p>Can you see these changes in the boy pictured in Figs 1 and 2?</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="317" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_13-1a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_13-1a_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 1, Age 11-10</label><caption><p>You'd consider him a moderately severe mandibular-deficient skeletal Class II, wouldn't you? So you'd hope for greater mandibular growth during the adolescent spurt. What would expect for growth of the nose?</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="317" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_13-1g.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Figure_13-1g_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 2, Age 14-4</label><caption><p>Note the forward projection and lengthening of the nose, which has the interesting effect of increasing his facial convexity. An important orthodontic consideration: you wouldn't want to retract his anterior teeth in correcting his Class II malocclusion, because that would make his nose even more prominent relative to his lower face.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Constancy of the Pattern</title><pageText><p>Although all children more or less follow Scammon's curves, it is obvious that facial proportions are different in different individuals. For example, some children have a relatively small mandible, some a relatively large nose, etc.</p>
<p>These differences tend to stay  constant during growth, which is another way of saying that the facial pattern in childhood tends to stay the same as a person grows and matures. For example, a child with mandibular deficiency is likely to remain mandibular deficient during adolescence and adulthood, while a child with true mandibular excess is likely to exhibit mandibular excess during adolescence and adulthood.</p>
<p>Although constancy of the facial pattern is the rule, there are exceptions. Trauma, hormonal disturbances, and a number of other growth problems can affect and change facial symmetry and proportions.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Assessing Skeletal Growth (cephalometrics)</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Cephalometrics</title><pageText><p>The structural components of the cranium and face can be distinguished well in a lateral projection (image 1). A lateral cephalometric radiograph (image 2) is an excellent way to document and understand the relationships between facial skeletal structures, or facial pattern. Note that you could outline the structural units on the radiograph (which we will call a ceph from now on) just as you could on the anatomic drawing. These radiographs are particularly valuable in evaluating how the five functional units relate to each other. </p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="449" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s02_p02_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s02_p02_01s.jpg"><label>Cephalometric film</label><caption><p>This type of radiograph allows for the visualization of the craniofacial hard tissues in the a-p and vertical planes of space.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cephalometric Tracings</title><pageText><p>A single cephalometric radiograph provides a snapshot of what the facial pattern and relationships are at any single point of time. In order to analyze facial pattern, it helps to make a tracing of the radiograph that outlines the functional units and other important structures of the facial skeleton. The tracing reduces the amount of information contained on a radiograph to the essential structures, and makes more apparent how these structures relate to each other.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="449" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s02_p03_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s02_p03_01s.jpg"><label>Cephalometric film traced</label><caption><p>By tracing key structures on the radiograph, important information is condensed and emphasized.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cephalometric Superimpositions</title><pageText><p>It is only by carefully comparing radiographs taken at different times that we can truly discover and understand the changes in facial proportions over time, the facial growth pattern.</p>
<p>When two cephalometric tracings from radiographs of the same individual are superimposed on stable structure, areas that do not overlap are areas where changes, typically growth, have occurred. The tracings shown here are superimposed on the cranial base, which completes its growth around age 7, and therefore is stable after that time. This makes the cranial base superimposition ideal for showing the growth of the face after the time that permanent teeth are beginning to erupt.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="317" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image04-05.gif" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image04-05_s.gif"><label>Cephalometric superimposition</label><caption><p>Superimposing cephalometric tracings from the same patient over time allows the visualization of craniofacial growth over time.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cephalometrics: Stable Landmarks</title><pageText><p>This comparison of radiographs shows how facial structures 
grow--the absolute amount for individual structures, and the relative 
amount compared to adjacent structures.</p>

<p>The superimposition shows that relative to the cranial base, the facial 
structures grew downward and forward. Note the somewhat greater growth 
of the mandible than the maxilla, which you would expect from the 
cephalocaudal gradient of growth that we discussed previously.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="317" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image04-05.gif" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image04-05_s.gif"><label>Cephalometric superimposition</label><caption><p>Superimposing on the cranial base, a structure which is not growing, makes growth in other areas evident.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Variations in Skeletal Growth</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Maxilla and Mandible</title><pageText><p>Variation in facial growth affects the relationship between the functional units of the craniofacial complex, and you are used to seeing differing facial patterns all around you.</p>
<p>Some degree of variation is normal, but extreme variation in the growth of one or more of the functional units can cause facial disharmony that creates problems for the affected individual and could be considered abnormal. These growth variations occur in varying degrees and directions. For our purposes, fairly extreme examples help to illustrate this important concept. It is obvious that the girl in image 1 has had less mandibular growth than normal, and that the boy in image 2 has had too much.</p>
<p>Differences in the facial pattern resulting from variations in facial growth are most easily understood when analyzing the functional units in separate planes of space: antero-posterior, vertical, or transverse.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="344" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p01_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="139" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p01_01s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>This boy has an obviously deficient mandible, and a Class II profile.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="396" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Class_III.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Class_III_s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>This young man has an impressively large mandible, and a Class III profile.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>AP Variations in Skeletal Growth: Class II</title><pageText><p>Antero-posterior growth variations are typically expressed in an altered A-P position of either the maxilla, mandible, or both jaws.</p>
<p>A skeletal Class II jaw relationship occurs when the maxilla is positioned a significant amount anteriorly relative to the mandible or the mandible is significantly posterior to the maxilla. This can have several causes that are illustrated below in block diagrams using the structural components:</p>
<ul>
<li>mandibular deficiency (image 1, image 4)</li>
<li>maxillary excess (image 2) </li>
<li>a combination of both (image 3, image 5). A Class II relationship typically results in increased overjet that is due to the displacement of the jaws, not to displacement of the teeth relative to their own jaw.</li>
</ul>
<p>By definition, a Class II growth pattern is one that leads to a skeletal Class II jaw relationship.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image06.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image06_s.gif"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Normal maxilla, deficient mandible</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image07.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image07_s.gif"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Prognathic maxilla, normal mandible</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image08.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image08_s.gif"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>Prognathic maxilla, deficient mandible</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="389" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image09.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image09_s.jpg"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>Severe Class II, deficient mandible</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="599" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p02_05.jpg" thumbnailWidth="106" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p02_05s.jpg"><label>Image 5</label><caption><p>Severe Class II, deficient mandible</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>A-P Variations in Skeletal Growth: Class III</title><pageText><p>A skeletal Class III jaw relationship occurs when the maxilla is positioned behind the mandible, and of course a Class III growth pattern leads to this condition.</p>
<p>This A-P relationship in the position of the jaws can have several causes: mandibular excess, which is also called mandibular prognathism (image 1); maxillary deficiency (image 2); or a combination of both (images 3,4,5). These jaw relationships usually result in no overjet (end-to-end incisors) or reverse overjet.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image11.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image11_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>Normal maxilla and prognathic mandible</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p03_02.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p03_02s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>Deficient maxilla and normal mandible</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image13.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image13_s.gif"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>Deficient maxilla and prognathic mandible</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="389" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image14.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image14_s.jpg"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>Deficient maxilla and prognathic mandible</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="448" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p03_05.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p03_05s.jpg"><label>Image 5 </label><caption>Deficient maxilla and prognathic mandible</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>A-P Variations in Skeletal Growth: Class I (Bimaxillary Protrusion)</title><pageText><p>Sometimes an individual can have normal skeletal relationship between 
the maxilla and mandible (image 1), but have both the upper and lower 
teeth and dentoalveolar processes displaced anteriorly relative to 
their skeletal bases (images 2,3,4).</p>

<p>In patients like this, the growth pattern of the jaws is normal 
(which is called a Class I growth pattern). The patient's condition, 
strictly speaking, is bimaxillary dentoalveolar protrusion, but it is 
called bimaxillary protrusion for short (except by anthropologists, who 
use bimaxillary protrusion to describe protrusion of both jaws relative 
to the cranium). The dentists' bimaxillary protrusion is characterized 
by proclined maxillary and mandibular incisors on normally positioned 
jaws (see image 2).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image16.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image16_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>Normal skeletal and dental relationships</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image17.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image17_s.gif"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>Bimaxillary dentoalveolar protrusion, normal jaw relationship</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image18.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image18_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>Bimaxillary dentoalveolar protrusion, normal jaw relationship</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="598" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p04_04.jpg" thumbnailWidth="106" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p04_04s.jpg"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>Bimaxillary dentoalveolar protrusion, normal jaw relationship</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Vertical Variations in Skeletal Growth</title><pageText><p>For normal jaw relationships, both the a-p and vertical positions of the jaws must be normal (image 1). Variations in vertical growth result in an altered vertical position of either the maxilla, mandible, or both jaws.</p>
<p>The two extremes are skeletal open bite (long face) and skeletal deep bite (short face) patterns (images 2 and 3, respectively). Naturally, the growth patterns that produce these conditions are called the long face (or open bite) and short face (or deep bite) growth patterns.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image20.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image20_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>Normal vertical (and A-P) jaw relationships</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="415" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image21.gif" thumbnailWidth="74" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image21_s.gif"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>Long face (skeletal open bite) jaw relationships</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Vertical Variations in Skeletal Growth: Open Bite / Long Face</title><pageText><p>Skeletal open bite, characterized by anterior open bite and a long face (increased vertical face height, see image 1), often is caused by a maxilla that has grown more in the posterior than anterior. This results in a palatal plane that appears tipped down posteriorly and downward-backward rotation of the mandible (image 2).</p>
<p>It can also be caused by a short mandibular ramus, which also leads to downward-backward rotation of the mandible, often with an increased gonial angle and steep mandibular plane (images 3 and 4).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image23.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image23_s.jpg"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>Long face pattern</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="415" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image22.gif" thumbnailWidth="74" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image22_s.gif"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>Skeletal open bite, downward-back rotation of mandible</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="446" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p06_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="108" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/s03_p06_03s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>Long face pattern, open bite</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="387" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image25.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image25_s.jpg"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>Long face pattern; note increased lower face height</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Vertical Variations in Skeletal Growth: Deep Bite / Short Face</title><pageText><p>At the other extreme is the skeletal deep bite pattern, characterized by a short face that almost always is accompanied by a deep bite (image 1).</p>
<p>This is often caused by a growth pattern that leads to a long mandibular ramus, decreased gonial angle and flat mandibular plane (images 2,3,4). This boy has maxillary incisors that are tipped forward and are protrusive. That's not uncommon in patients with a deep bite, but it's not part of the vertical problem--you can have a short face and deep bite without protrusion of upper incisors.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image27.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image27_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>Short face, deep bite anteriorly (excessive overbite)</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="389" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image28.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image28_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>Short face pattern</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image29.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image29_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>Short face pattern (same pt.)</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image30.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image30_s.jpg"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>Short face pattern (same pt.)</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Transverse Variations in Skeletal Growth</title><pageText><p>Transverse growth variations are typically expressed in an altered transverse position of the mandible. True maxillary asymmetry is rare, but mandibular asymmetry occurs frequently.</p>
<p>A mandibular asymmetry with the chin to the right side can result from excess growth on the left, decreased growth or degeneration on the right, or a combination of both. Conversely, a mandibular asymmetry to the left (as shown here) can result from excess growth on the right, decreased growth or degeneration on the left side, or a combination of both.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="374" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image31.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image31_s.jpg"><label>Transverse asymmetry, frontal view</label><caption>Note the chin is deviated to the left.</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Transverse Variations in Skeletal Growth: Patient Example</title><pageText><p>For this patient (image 1), the deviation of the mandible to her left can be seen even more clearly in a P-A cephalometric radiograph (image 2). She has a corresponding mandibular midline deviation to the left that can be seen in her intraoral photograph (image 3). Examination of her panoramic radiograph reveals a left mandibular condyle that is smaller than the right mandibular condyle (image 4).</p>
<p>Detecting the asymmetry may be easy in a case like this, but understanding the cause of the asymmetry can be much more difficult. Because her face height is abnormally long on the right side, the asymmetric mandibular growth was elongation of the neck of the ramus on the right, which pushed the chin to the left.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="374" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image31.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image31_s.jpg"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>Frontal photograph, note chin asymmetry</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="403" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image32.jpg" thumbnailWidth="72" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image32_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>P-A cephalometric radiograph, same pt.</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="348" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image33.jpg" thumbnailWidth="138" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image33_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>Frontal intraoral photo, note midline deviation</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image34.jpg" thumbnailWidth="160" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image34_s.jpg"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>Panoramic radiograph, note long condylar neck on right</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Complex Variations in Skeletal Growth</title><pageText><p>Disturbances in facial growth that affect multiple planes of space can create complex deformities. Analyzing facial and facial growth patterns using three distinct planes of space helps you fully analyze and understand the variation.</p>
<p>This patient (image 1), more obviously than the previous one, has hemimandibular hypertrophy (excessive growth of the mandible on one side). Notice how the excess growth of the right condyle and ramus (image 5) has caused problems in all three planes of space, including mandibular asymmetry, a dental midline discrepancy, and lateral open bite (images 2,3). In the lateral cephalometric radiograph (image 4), you can see two distinct mandibular planes because the ramus is longer on the right side. In addition, there is a Class III molar relationship on the right side.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image35.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image35_s.jpg"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>Frontal view, chin off to left</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="329" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image36.jpg" thumbnailWidth="146" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image36_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>Note unilateral posterior open bite</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="337" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image37.jpg" thumbnailWidth="60" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image37_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>P-A cephalometric radiograph (same pt)</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image38.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image38_s.jpg"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>Lateral cephalometric radiograph (same pt)</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image39.jpg" thumbnailWidth="160" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image39_s.jpg"><label>Image 5 </label><caption>Panoramic radiograph, note the long condylar process on the right</caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Dental Compensations for Skeletal Discrepancies</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Dental Compensations for Skeletal Discrepancies</title><pageText><p>Now let's look at the effect these skeletal variations have on the teeth and dentoalveolar processes. The dentition exhibits a remarkable ability to compensate for an unfortunate growth pattern of the jaws. These compensations allow individuals with different facial types to have teeth that fit together reasonably well despite the jaw relationships. Even if a severe malocclusion results from the growth pattern, often the dental compensations mask the severity of the skeletal problem, i.e., the jaw deviations are worse than the dental deviations.</p>
<p>Again, it is easiest to understand these dental compensations by analyzing in three planes of space the dental compensations that accompany different facial patterns.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Dental Compensations for Class II Growth Patterns</title><pageText><p>Class II patients often have upper incisors that are upright or more lingual relative to the maxilla, and lower incisors that are flared facially relative to the mandible (image 1).</p>
<p>Notice how this patient has a deficient mandible (image 2) but a relatively minimal increase in overjet because of forward movement of the lower teeth relative to the mandible and lingual tipping of upper incisors (image 3). The lower incisors are not as far forward as they would have been if the growth pattern were normal and the mandible were not deficient.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image40.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image40_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>Dental compensation for Class II growth</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image41.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image41_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>Skeletal Class II, mandibular deficiency</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image42.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image42_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>Forward position of mandibular teeth, decreasing overjet</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>AP Dental Compensations: Skeletal Class III</title><pageText><p>Class III patients often have upper incisors that are flared facially relative to the maxilla and lower incisors that are upright relative to the mandible (image 1).</p>
<p>Notice how this patient (image 2) has a Class III profile with the typical associated dental compensations. Her Class III skeletal problem (image 3) was so severe that even with the dental compensations she could not maintain a positive overjet. She was treated with surgical repositioning of the jaws.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image43.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image43_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>Dental compensation for Class III growth</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="386" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image44.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image44_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>Severe skeletal Class III</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image45.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image45_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>Note the proclined upper incisors and upright lower incisors (same pt)</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>AP Dental Compensations</title><pageText><p>Many patients with Class II and Class III jaw relationships can have fairly normal overjet, despite the fact that there is a significant discrepancy between the AP position of the maxilla and mandible.</p>
<p>These two patients (images 1,2 and images 3,4) have relatively small differences in overjet and similar dental occlusion, but widely different jaw structures and relationships.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image46.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image46_s.jpg"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>profile view, Class II patient</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image47.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image47_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>note the upright maxillary incisors and proclined lower incisors</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="387" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image48.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image48_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>profile view, Class III patient</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image49.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image49_s.jpg"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>note the proclined upper incisors and upright lower incisors</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Vertical Dental Compensations: Skeletal Open Bite</title><pageText><p>Vertical dental compensations are expressed in the vertical position of incisors relative to their skeletal bases (maxilla or mandible). Remember that a skeletal open bite pattern is often associated with a short mandibular ramus and steep mandibular plane.</p>
<p>In order to compensate for this skeletal pattern, more eruption of incisors than normal would decrease the open bite (image 1). Patients with these compensations (images 2,3,4) can have relatively normal overbite relationships, especially when compared to their underlying skeletal pattern. For this girl, incisor eruption almost totally compensated for the downward rotation of the mandible--but she would benefit from correction of her Class III and long face characteristics. This would require surgical repositioning of both jaws.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="415" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image50.gif" thumbnailWidth="74" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image50_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>dental compensation for skeletal open bite</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="389" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image51.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image51_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>long face, Class III facial pattern</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="389" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image52.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image52_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>long face, Class III facial pattern</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="330" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image53.jpg" thumbnailWidth="146" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image53_s.gif"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>anterior view of dentition: no open bite despite long face</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image54.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image54_s.jpg"><label>Image 5 </label><caption>note excessive eruption of incisors</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Vertical Dental Compensations: Skeletal Deep Bite</title><pageText><p>Remember that patients with a skeletal deep bite pattern typically have a decreased gonial angle and a flat mandibular plane. In order to compensate for this relationship, less than normal eruption of incisors would be required (image 1).</p>
<p>This short-face girl has reasonably normal overbite despite her short face (images 2,3,4,5). Note the facial tipping of the incisors in both arches.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image55.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image55_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>short face height predisposes a patient to anterior deep bite</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image56.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image56_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>short face patient</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="387" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image57.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image57_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>short face patient</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="328" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image58.jpg" thumbnailWidth="146" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image58_s.jpg"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>minimal overbite despite short face pattern</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image59.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image59_s.jpg"><label>Image 5 </label><caption>minimal overbite, but incisors are severely proclined</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Transverse Dental Compensations: Skeletal Asymmetry</title><pageText><p>As with the other planes of space, transverse dental compensations usually accompany asymmetric jaw growth. If the jaw deviates to one side, the teeth shift back toward the midline so that the dental midline discrepancy often is less than the jaw discrepancy.</p>
<p>For this patient the dental compensation is apparent but not nearly enough to create normal dental occlusion, and treatment would have to be surgery to reposition the jaws. In order to get good jaw relationships, however, the dental compensation would have to be removed by presurgical orthodontic treatment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="403" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image32.jpg" thumbnailWidth="72" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image32_s.jpg"><label>PA cephalometric film</label><caption><p>Note the mandibular asymmetry with the chin to the patient’s left.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="348" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image33.jpg" thumbnailWidth="138" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image33_s.jpg"><label>Same patient, intraoral view</label><caption><p>The position of the mandibular teeth are compensated to mask the skeletal asymmetry of the mandible.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Orthodontic Treatment in the Context of Growth</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Treatment for Growing Patients</title><pageText><p>For growing patients, it is important to recognize skeletal malocclusions so they can be treated at the appropriate time. Often this treatment will involve growth modification--trying to alter the position of the skeletal bases and/or dentoalveolar segments while an individual is growing. Of course, you can't modify growth that isn't happening, either because the child is in a period of slow growth prior to the adolescent growth spurt, or because an adolescent already is past the growth spurt.</p>
<p>For example, consider the problem presented by failure of the maxilla to grow forward as it should (image 1). This 7 year-old boy presented with the a convex profile and a facial appearance of maxillary deficiency and an anterior crossbite (images 2,3). Cephalometric analysis revealed a component of maxillary deficiency contributing to his Class III skeletal pattern and reverse overjet (image 4).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image60.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image60_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>maxillary deficient Class III</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image61.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image61_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>age 7, profile appearance</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="508" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image62.jpg" thumbnailWidth="90" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image62_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>age 7, cephalometric radiograph</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="330" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image63.jpg" thumbnailWidth="145" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image63_s.jpg"><label>Image 4 </label><caption>age 7, anterior crossbite</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Treatment for Growing Patients (cont.)</title><pageText><p>His treatment involved a reverse pull headgear to protract the maxilla and maxillary dentoalveolar segments (image 1). This resulted in elimination of the anterior crossbite (compare images 2 and 3), and a flattening of the profile convexity as the maxilla moved forward.</p>
<p>This treatment has to be done before the sutures of the maxilla become so interdigitated that the maxilla cannot be moved forward. The ideal time for most children is between ages 6 and 8 (depending on their physiologic maturity rather than chronologic age). If it is delayed beyond about age 10, the skeletal deficiency no longer can be treated without surgery.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image64.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image64_s.gif"><label>Image 1 </label><caption>growth modification treatment, moving maxilla forward</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="205" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image65.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="57" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image65_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 </label><caption>age 7, before growth modification treatment</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="198" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image66.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="55" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image66_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 </label><caption>age 8, after treatment</caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Treatment for Adults / Non-Growing Patients</title><pageText><p>In older patients who have completed the vast majority of their growth, there are fewer options for treating a skeletal malocclusion. Sometimes a jaw discrepancy is so great (image 1) that repositioning the jaws through orthognathic surgery is the only way to obtain an acceptable facial appearance (image 2) and get the teeth to fit together normally.</p>
<p>Early diagnosis of the facial pattern and growth pattern, and appropriate treatment at the ideal time are essential for effectively treating skeletal malocclusions. Unfortunately, it is almost impossible to control excessive mandibular growth, and an individual with this growth pattern is quite likely to end up needing surgery, despite efforts to treat it during growth.</p>
<p>Fortunately, as these pre- (image 1) and post-surgery (image 2) images show, it is possible now to correct jaw deformities with surgical repositioning of either or both jaws. Class III problems are more likely to require surgery because of the tendency of the mandible to grow after maxillary growth is nearly completed.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Class_III_pre-sx.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Class_III_pre-sx_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, A girl with a Class III skeletal relationship</label><caption><p>Her malocclusion was treated with surgical-orthodontics since she was no longer growing.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Class_III_post-sx.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Class_III_post-sx_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, Same girl post-surgery</label><caption><p>Her maxilla was moved forward surgically to correct her skeletal and dental Class III relationships.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary</title><pageText><p>In summary:</p>
<ul class="spaced">
<li>The pattern of facial growth reflects an interaction between the neural and general body growth curves, so that growth of the face trails behind growth of the cranium and cranial base, and growth of the mandible trails behind growth of the maxilla</li>
<li>Some individuals have a pattern of growth with excessive or deficient growth of the maxilla and/or mandible, which leads to what is best described as a skeletal malocclusion (by definition, a skeletal malocclusion means that the jaw position is abnormal and tends to create a dental malocclusion).</li>
<li>For mild skeletal discrepancies, dental compensation during growth may create normal dental occlusion, and if not dental compensation created by orthodontic treatment can be satisfactory. For moderately severe discrepancies, growth modification can be successful treatment; for the most severe ones, surgery is the only option.</li>
<li>Mandibular growth that is more downward and less forward leads to a Class II skeletal and dental relationship.</li>
<li>Mandibular growth that is more forward and less downward leads to a Class III skeletal and dental relationship.</li>
<li>The pattern of facial growth, whether normal or leading to skeletal malocclusion, is established early and rarely changes spontaneously.</li>
<li>In children with skeletal malocclusion, dental compensation for the skeletal discrepancy usually occurs so that the dental occlusion is less abnormal than the jaw relationship.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now take the self-test in the following section.  Before you do, be sure you have read pages 96-103 in the 5th edition of  <i>Contemporary Orthodontics</i> (or pages 111-119 in the 4th ed.). Then use the self-test to help you understand these concepts of evaluating patients and using that information to plan appropriate treatment.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>Growth pattern of the face refers to:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>proportional relationships during growth</choice><choice>changes in proportional relationships during growth</choice><choice>the rate of growth of the components of the head and face</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, growth pattern refers to the way proportional relationships 
in the face change during growth, not to the proportional relationships 
themselves or to the rate of growth of the components.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's incorrect, growth pattern refers to the way proportional 
relationships in the face change during growth, not to the proportional 
relationships themselves or to the rate of growth of the components.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>The major characteristic of a Class I skeletal relationship in a profile 
view is:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>cranial, facial and dental structures in a nearly straight line</choice><choice>facial and dental structures straight but prominent to the cranium</choice><choice>cranial and facial structures in a nearly straight line, teeth can be anywhere</choice><choice>maxilla forward relative to mandible</choice><choice>mandible forward relative to maxilla</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct. In a Class I (normal) relationship, the cranium, 
maxilla, maxillary teeth, mandibular teeth and mandible are in a 
nearly straight line.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. In a Class I (normal) relationship, the cranium, 
maxilla, maxillary teeth, mandibular teeth and mandible are in 
a nearly straight line.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image01.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image01_s.gif"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>The major characteristic of a Class II skeletal relationship is:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>cranial, facial and dental structures in a nearly straight line</choice><choice>facial and dental structures straight but prominent to the cranium</choice><choice>cranial and facial structures in a nearly straight line, teeth can be anywhere</choice><choice>maxilla forward relative to mandible</choice><choice>mandible forward relative to maxilla</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. In a Class II relationship the maxilla is forward 
relative to the mandible. This can occur because the maxilla grew 
normally while the mandible grew less than normal, or because the 
maxilla grew too much, or any combination of deficient mandibular 
and excess maxillary growth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. In a Class II relationship the maxilla is forward 
relative to the mandible. This can occur because the maxilla grew 
normally while the mandible grew less than normal, or because the 
maxilla grew too much, or any combination of deficient mandibular 
and excess maxillary growth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image06-07.gif" thumbnailWidth="160" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image06-07_s.gif"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>The major characteristic of a Class III skeletal relationship is:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>cranial, facial and dental structures in a nearly straight line</choice><choice>facial and dental structures straight but prominent to the cranium</choice><choice>cranial and facial structures in a nearly straight line, teeth can be anywhere</choice><choice>maxilla forward relative to mandible</choice><choice>mandible forward relative to maxilla</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. In a Class III relationship the mandible is forward 
relative to the maxilla. This can occur because the mandible grew 
normally while the maxilla grew less than normal, because the 
mandible grew too much, or any combination of deficient maxillary 
and excess mandibular growth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's incorrect. In a Class III relationship the mandible is 
forward relative to the maxilla. This can occur because the 
mandible grew normally while the maxilla grew less than normal, 
because the mandible grew too much, or any combination of 
deficient maxillary and excess mandibular growth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image11-12.gif" thumbnailWidth="160" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image11-12_s.gif"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>For which of the following is the adolescent growth spurt least prominent?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>weight</choice><choice>height</choice><choice>lower jaw length</choice><choice>upper jaw length</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. Because the maxilla is influenced by the neural 
growth curve, it has less response to the adolescent growth spurt 
that particularly affects general body growth than the mandible 
and weight / height.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. Because the maxilla is influenced by the neural 
growth curve, it has less response to the adolescent growth 
spurt that particularly affects general body growth than the 
mandible and weight / height.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>What would you expect to happen to the a-p position of the lower 
incisors in response to a Class II growth pattern?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>forward (facial) movement</choice><choice>little or no movement</choice><choice>backward (lingual) movement</choice><choice>vertical change more probable than a-p change</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct. If the maxilla grows forward more than the mandible 
in a Class II growth pattern, often the lower incisors partially 
compensate by moving forward (facially).</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. If the maxilla grows forward more than the 
mandible in a Class II growth pattern, often the lower incisors 
partially compensate by moving forward (facially).</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image40.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image40_s.gif"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>What would you expect to happen to the a-p position of the upper 
incisors in response to a Class III growth pattern?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>forward (facial) movement</choice><choice>little or no movement</choice><choice>backward (lingual) movement</choice><choice>vertical change more probable than facio-lingual change</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct. In response to a Class III growth pattern the upper 
incisors would tend to tip forward, moving facially. In a skeletal 
Class III patient, the forward movement of the upper incisors and 
the backward movement of the lower incisors both reduce the relative 
protrusion of the lower teeth. This is a classic example of dental 
compensation for a skeletal discrepancy. In Class III or Class II 
patients, the dental occlusion is often better than the jaw 
relationship at the end of growth for this reason.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. In response to a Class III growth pattern the 
upper incisors would tend to tip forward, moving facially. In 
a skeletal Class III patient, the forward movement of the upper 
incisors and the backward movement of the lower incisors both 
reduce the relative protrusion of the lower teeth. This is a 
classic example of dental compensation for a skeletal discrepancy. 
In Class III or Class II patients, the dental occlusion is often 
better than the jaw relationship at the end of growth for this reason.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image43.gif" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image43_s.gif"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>In a child with end-to-end permanent first molars at age 10 and a 
mild Class II growth pattern, what is the most likely molar 
relationship at age 12?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>Class I</choice><choice>end-to-end</choice><choice>Class II</choice><choice>Class III</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct. With a mild Class II growth pattern it is unlikely 
that the end-to-end permanent molars would make the normal shift to 
Class I, and most probably they would stay end-to-end. If the Class 
II growth pattern was really severe, they could move to Class II. 
Transition to Class III would require a severe Class III growth pattern.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's incorrect. With a mild Class II growth pattern it is 
unlikely that the end-to-end permanent molars would make the 
normal shift to Class I, and most probably they would stay 
end-to-end. If the Class II growth pattern was really severe, 
they could move to Class II. Transition to Class III would 
require a severe Class III growth pattern.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>In a child with Class I permanent first molars at age 10 and a 
Class III growth pattern, what is the most likely molar relationship 
at age 12?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>Class I</choice><choice>end-to-end</choice><choice>Class II</choice><choice>Class III</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct. With a Class III growth pattern, molars that were 
already Class I at age 10 (when many children with a normal growth 
pattern are still end-to-end) would be carried toward Class III, and 
that's the most probable molar relation after 2 more years of Class 
III growth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. With a Class III growth pattern, molars that 
were already Class I at age 10 (when many children with a normal 
growth pattern are still end-to-end) would be carried toward 
Class III, and that's the most probable molar relation after 2 
more years of Class III growth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>(A) A Class I malocclusion rarely becomes a Class III malocclusion 
during growth because (B) a Class II growth pattern rarely occurs in a 
Class I patient.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A false, B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. Both statements are true but they're not related. 
Class I rarely becomes Class III because Class III growth pattern 
rarely occurs in a Class I patient. A Class II growth pattern would 
turn Class I into Class II, not III.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's incorrect. Both statements are true but they're not 
related. Class I rarely becomes Class III because Class III 
growth pattern rarely occurs in a Class I patient. A Class II 
growth pattern would turn Class I into Class II, not III.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 11</title><pageText><p>What is the chance that a child with a Class II skeletal pattern would 
spontaneously grow out of it and become Class I as an adult?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>less than 10%</choice><choice>10-20%</choice><choice>20-40%</choice><choice>about 50%</choice><choice>totally unpredictable - no way to know</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. Spontaneous correction of a skeletal Class II or 
Class III pattern rarely occurs. The general rule is "constancy 
of the pattern", meaning that whatever the growth pattern is, 
it's unlikely to change (but of course unlikely things do happen, 
they just don't happen very often). The chance of spontaneous 
correction of a skeletal Class II or Class III is considerably 
less than 10%, in fact probably closer to 1%.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. Spontaneous correction of a skeletal Class II or 
Class III pattern rarely occurs. The general rule is "constancy 
of the pattern", meaning that whatever the growth pattern is, 
it's unlikely to change (but of course unlikely things do happen, 
they just don't happen very often). The chance of spontaneous 
correction of a skeletal Class II or Class III is considerably 
less than 10%, in fact probably closer to 1%.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 12</title><pageText><p>(A) In a child with a skeletal open bite growth pattern, positive 
overbite can be present because (B) increased eruption of incisors 
would compensate for the open bite tendency.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A false, B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, increased eruption of incisors could compensate for 
a skeletal open bite growth pattern, maintaining positive overbite 
even though the mandible was growing downward away from the maxilla.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. Increased eruption of incisors could compensate for a 
skeletal open bite growth pattern, maintaining positive overbite even 
though the mandible was growing downward away from the maxilla.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="415" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image50.gif" thumbnailWidth="74" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="patternsfacialgrowth/images/Image50_s.gif"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>
