<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<presentation><title>Meet Your New Young Patient</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>Carlos Nurko, DDS, MS<br/>William R. Proffit DDS, PhD<br/>Department of Orthodontics, School of Dentistry<br/>University of North Carolina<br/></additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="youngpatient/images/titlepage2.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Background</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Reading/Links</title><pageText><p>To get the most advantage of this program, it is highly recommended to have
reviewed the following information:</p>

<p>Ackerman-Proffit classification: <br/>
Computer Module, Level 2: Systematic Description of Malocclusion.</p>

<p>Interaction with orthodontists:<br/>
Computer Module, Level 4: Interaction with Orthodontic Specialists.</p>

<p>Orthodontic diagnosis: <br/>
The Development of a Problem List. <i>Contemporary Orthodontics</i>, 3rd 
ed., pp. 148-195.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Your Next Patient Is Here</title><pageText><p>After you enter dental practice, a common service to be rendered to the community 
where you will be practicing is to evaluate the orthodontic needs of a 
growing patient. Not far in the future, at your busy practice your assistant 
will be saying:</p>

<p>“Doctor, your next patient is here. She is an 11-year-old named 
Melissa, and her parents want to know if she needs orthodontic treatment” 
(video 1).</p>

<p>Orthodontic diagnosis requires a broad overview of the patient’s 
situation. The essence of the problem-oriented approach is the development 
of a comprehensive database of pertinent information so that no problems 
will be overlooked.</p>

<p>Let’s start developing the diagnostic database by going over to 
meet your new young patient (video 2). You can learn something about her 
general health and stage of maturity just by watching her walk into the 
clinic—and you should take the opportunity to do so.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/entering.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/entering.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Patient coming to the dental clinic.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/called.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/called.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Coming in and meeting the doctor.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Interview</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Interview: Initial Questions</title><pageText><p>The first step in evaluating the patient is an interview with the 
patient and parent. The objective is to understand the patient’s 
overall situation and evaluate specific orthodontic concerns. The specific 
goals are to establish the</p>

<ol><li>Patient’s chief complaint: why are they seeking consultation?</li>
<li>Medical and dental history</li>
<li>Physical growth status</li>
<li>Motivation, expectations, and other sociobehavioral factors </li>
</ol><p>So let’s interview your patient and her mother (video).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/waiting.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/waiting.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Chief Complaint</title><pageText><p>The first step in the interview is to establish the patient’s 
chief complaint, the reason for seeking this consultation. This usually 
is done best by direct questions:</p>

<ul><li>Tell me what bothers you about your face or your teeth?</li>
<li>Do you think you need braces? Why? (video 1)</li>
</ul><p>It is important to remember that what the dentist thinks is the major 
problem may not be what the patient/parent are concerned about (video 2). 
The major reasons for orthodontic treatment, of course, are to overcome some 
combination of psychosocial concerns related to dental and facial appearance, 
concerns about dental/jaw function, and health concerns.</p>

<p>You need to know “where they’re coming from,” in the 
“why are they here?” sense of that phrase.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/complaint_chief.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/complaint_chief.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Video Clip 1, Melissa chief complaint.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/complaint_mother.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/complaint_mother.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Video Clip 2, Mother chief complaint.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Medical and Dental History</title><pageText><p>Young patients interested in orthodontic treatment, like your patient 
Melissa, often are healthy and have a noncontributory medical history (video). But 
on occasion positive findings in the medical history can have relevance to orthodontic 
treatment, as in the following:</p>

<ul class="spaced"><li>Allergy to metal, especially nickel allergy, can be important if 
the patient will need fixed orthodontic appliances.</li>
<li> Other allergies can affect growth and treatment response.</li>
<li> Patients with actual or potential heart problems, such as those 
related to a history of rheumatic fever, need antibiotic coverage 
during banding and debanding (but not for noninvasive orthodontic 
procedures like changing an arch wire).</li>
<li> Juvenile arthritis, if it affects the TM joints, can create severe 
growth problems—and involvement of the TM joints is likely in 
a child who has multiple affected joints, so this would be an immediate 
matter of concern in a child with any arthritic joints.</li>
<li> Some children with small stature are treated with growth hormone, 
which can have implications for growth modification possibilities 
and treatment timing.</li>
<li>Other medications can affect treatment, so all should be noted 
carefully.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/history.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/history.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Orofacial Trauma</title><pageText><p>“Have you ever injured your teeth, jaws, or face?” (video)</p>

<p>Your patient and mother are reporting a negative history of orofacial 
trauma, but remember that children frequently sustain injury to their 
primary and permanent teeth and to their jaws. Twenty-five percent of 
17-year-olds in the United States are reported to have sustained some 
type of trauma to the teeth and face in the past.</p>

<p>Let’s review why orofacial trauma is important in relation to orthodontic 
treatment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/trauma.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/trauma.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Trauma to the Teeth</title><pageText><p>First, think about trauma to the teeth. Why is a history of trauma to the 
teeth important?</p>

<ul class="spaced"><li>Increased overjet with protrusion of maxillary incisors is a significant 
predisposing factor for trauma to the teeth. Note that the patient 
in image 1 traumatized her maxillary left central incisor in the past. 
That’s more likely if 10 mm of overjet is present, as for her. 
One reason for beginning orthodontic treatment early (in the mixed 
dentition), though not a major one for most patients, is to reduce 
the chance of injury to protruding incisors. </li>
<li>Previous trauma to the permanent incisors, even minor, can produce 
devitalization of the pulp of the injured tooth. The patient shown 
in image 2 has history of traumatic injuries in her incisors due to 
seizures. A negative pulp response was obtained from the maxillary 
right central incisor, and a periapical radiograph of her maxillary 
incisors reveals external root resorption, which of course would be 
exacerbated by orthodontic tooth movement.</li>
<li> Severe displacement of the incisors can cause extensive damage 
to the periodontal ligament, and as that heals, ankylosis of the tooth 
is quite possible. Ankylosis (image 3) leads to gradual infraocclusion 
and arrested development of the alveolar process. Remember, an ankylosed 
tooth cannot be moved orthodontically. Often the best plan is to extract 
it before it drops well below the plane of the other teeth to minimize 
the size of the eventual alveolar defect in that area.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="522" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="93" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/03_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, increased overjet</label><caption><p>Increased overjet with protrusion of incisors increases the chance of 
trauma to the protruding teeth.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="523" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/04.jpg" thumbnailWidth="93" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/04_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, nonvital pulp</label><caption><p>A history of dental trauma also increases the chance of external root 
resorption that would preclude orthodontic tooth movement.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="203" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/05.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="56" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/05_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, ankylosed incisor</label><caption><p>Ankylosed permanent incisors due to previous trauma. As these teeth 
fail to erupt, an anterior open bite is developing.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Trauma to the Face and Jaws</title><pageText><p>Why is a history of trauma to the face and jaws important?</p>

<ul class="spaced"><li>The condylar neck of the mandible in childhood is vulnerable when 
there is a blow to the face, and a fracture of this area can result 
in a growth deficit that causes facial asymmetry as the injured side 
lags behind. A condylar fracture often goes undiagnosed. Remember 
that this is the most likely cause of a mandibular asymmetry with 
deficient growth of one side, even if the child and family don’t 
remember the traumatic event.</li>

<li> At age 5, the patient in images 1 and 2 suffered a subcondylar 
fracture of his left condyle in a car accident. Note in the panoramic 
radiograph that the condylar fragment is displaced. It will remodel 
and regenerate in most instances. A removable appliance was fabricated 
to reposition his mandible and guide jaw movement during healing, 
to maximize the chance of normal growth afterward. </li>

<li>When the mandible can’t translate after an injury (remember, 
the condyle must be able to move out of the fossa to grow), there’s 
a major growth problem. The patient in images 3 and 4 suffered a subcondylar 
fracture as an infant. The asymmetric and reduced growth noted at 
age 9 is severe enough to require early mandibular surgery to improve 
the skeletal problem.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="341" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/06.jpg" thumbnailWidth="141" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/06_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, panoramic and frontal cephalometric radiograph, subcondylar</label><caption><p>A subcondylar fracture on the left can be seen in the panoramic radiograph 
taken soon after the accident. Note the displacement of the fractured condyle.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="531" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/07.jpg" thumbnailWidth="94" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/07_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, subcondylar fracture</label><caption><p>Following the accident, a removable appliance was fabricated, to reposition his 
mandible and facilitate growth on the affected side.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="348" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/08.jpg" thumbnailWidth="138" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/08_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, old fracture, asymmetric growth</label><caption><p>Young patient with reduced mandibular growth as a result of early mandibular 
fracture and restriction of translation of the condyles. Early orthognathic surgery 
(at age 9) was indicated.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="288" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/09.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/09_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, old fracture, early mandibular advancement</label><caption><p>Cephalometric radiographs before/after mandibular advancement at age 9. 
Additional surgery later probably will be required—subsequent normal growth 
cannot be expected.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Physical Growth Status</title><pageText><p>The child’s physical growth status (where is he or she relative 
to the adolescent growth spurt?) is an important factor in determining the 
timing of orthodontic treatment. How do you evaluate that in an interview? 
The appropriate questions:</p>

<ul><li>How rapidly have you grown recently? (video)</li>
<li>Have your clothes sizes changed?</li>
<li>(For girls) Have you reached menarche?</li>
</ul><p>In addition, of course, you would look for signs of sexual maturation. 
Before sexual maturity, continuing growth of the face and jaws can be expected; 
after it, much less growth is anticipated.</p>

<p>Why is it important to evaluate physical growth status? Young patients, 
those who still have significant growth remaining, can be treated using 
growth modification. The patient in images 1 and 2 has a Class II malocclusion 
due to mandibular deficiency, and the patient in images 3 and 4 has 
a concave profile and a Class III malocclusion due primarily to a shift 
from centric relation to maximum intercuspation (if the Class III is 
mostly due to a shift, it’s called pseudo-Class III). For both, 
treatment during active growth offers the best possibility to correct 
the skeletal and dental discrepancy. The Class III patient needs treatment 
as soon as possible because the constant forward shift can displace 
erupting teeth and make the malocclusion worse. The Class II patient 
is best treated during the adolescent growth spurt and must be evaluated 
relative to his level of physical maturity rather than his dental age.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/growth.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/growth.jpg"><label>Video, Physical Growth Status</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="389" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/10.jpg" thumbnailWidth="124" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/10_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, Class II malocclusion</label><caption><p>Class II div I malocclusion in a boy entering the adolescent growth spurt, 
which is the ideal time for treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="378" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/11.jpg" thumbnailWidth="127" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/11_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, Class II growth modification</label><caption><p>Growth modification treatment during active growth: progress note the 
improved jaw relationship after 12 months of headgear treatment and braces in 
the anterior teeth.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="369" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/12.jpg" thumbnailWidth="130" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/12_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, pseudo-Class III malocclusion</label><caption><p>Young patient with anterior crossbite due to forward shift.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/13.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/13_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, crossbite/forward shift correction</label><caption><p>Crossbite/shift correction by relieving incisor interferences.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Motivation, Expectations, and Compliance</title><pageText><p>As the final step in the interview, it is important to explore two related but 
different factors: the motivation for treatment, and what the patient/parents 
expect as a result of treatment. Why? Because both relate strongly to cooperation 
with treatment and therefore to the chance of a successful treatment outcome.</p>

<p>Melissa shows genuine interest for treatment and demonstrates now that 
she understands a lot of what it is like to wear orthodontic appliances 
when she talks about her friends wearing braces (video). This suggests 
that she would cooperate with treatment.</p>

<p>Increased patient compliance has been associated with:</p>

<ul><li>more severe malocclusions and a greater desire to have treatment</li>
<li>positive parental attitude regarding the value of effective orthodontics</li>
<li>whether or not the child likes the dentist</li>
</ul><p>The patients in images 1 and 2 really wanted treatment and were very 
motivated to use extraoral appliances like the face mask or headgear. 
The patient in image 2 had a personal diary in which she recorded the 
hours she wore her headgear.</p>

<p>Cooperation is likely to be much better if the child genuinely wants 
treatment, rather that just putting up with it to please a parent. Indifferent 
patients, of course, are not likely to cooperate, and occasionally a 
child overtly refuses to cooperate with treatment, often because it 
is being forced on him or her by the parents and becomes a focus of 
adolescent rebellion. Sometimes orthodontic treatment has to be delayed 
until the patient is ready to accept it.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/motivation.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/motivation.jpg"><label>Video, Motivations and Expectations</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="358" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/14.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/14_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, Face mask to treat maxillary deficiency</label><caption><p>This young patient was very conscious of her facial appearance and was 
highly motivated to cooperate with reverse pull headgear (face mask) to bring 
her upper jaw and teeth forward.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="380" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/15.jpg" thumbnailWidth="126" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/15_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, Headgear to treat skeletal Class II</label><caption><p>This girl wanted her protruding teeth corrected and cooperated very well 
with headgear.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary of Interview</title><pageText><p>So what did we learn about Melissa from the interview?</p>

<ul class="spaced"><li>She and her parents think she needs orthodontic treatment, and 
their primary concern is the protrusive appearance of the teeth.</li>

<li>There’s nothing significant in the history—no history 
of trauma, no allergies/habits, no medications.</li>

<li>She has obvious secondary sexual characteristics and reports recent 
growth, so she’s entering the adolescent growth spurt even though 
she’s only 11.</li>

<li>Her expectations are realistic, and she appears to be motivated 
to be a cooperative patient.</li>
</ul><p>Now we are ready to perform the clinical exam.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/complaint_mother.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/complaint_mother.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Clinical Evaluation</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Step 1: Oral Health</title><pageText><p>In the clinical examination, look at the patient from general to particular 
(video, image 1). It’s a serious error to characterize the dental occlusion 
while overlooking a jaw discrepancy, developmental syndrome, periodontal problem, 
or systemic disease. It helps to have a mental checklist to avoid overlooking things. 
If you don’t see it, usually it’s because you are not looking 
for it.</p>

<p>This is the suggested checklist—look at these four things, in 
this order:</p>

<ul><li>Oral health</li>
<li>Jaw function</li>
<li>Facial proportions</li>
<li>Dental relationships</li>
</ul><p>For the prospective orthodontic patient, what are you looking for in the 
category of oral health? The same things you would be in any dental patient. 
Is there any oral pathology? What is the periodontal status? Is caries present? Are 
there missing teeth, tooth discoloration, enamel fractures, and or enamel defects?</p>

<p>Remember that even if the question is only whether the patient needs 
orthodontic treatment, any active disease or problem in the soft and 
hard tissues must be under control before any recommended orthodontic 
treatment can begin.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/chair.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/chair.jpg"><label>Video, clinical exam</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="410" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/16.jpg" thumbnailWidth="117" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/16_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, lateral / frontal 
      intraoral views</label><caption><p>Melissa, age 11, frontal/lateral intraoral views. Whether or not the questions 
relate to malocclusion, a careful examination of oral health is the first 
step in evaluation.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="328" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="58" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/17_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, occlusal intraoral views</label><caption><p>Melissa, age 11, occlusal intraoral views. Caries? Gingivitis/bleeding on 
probing? Attached gingiva?</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Step 2: Evaluation of Jaw Function and Habits</title><pageText><p>The key questions in evaluation of jaw function:</p>

<ul><li>What is the maximum voluntary opening?</li>
<li>Normal lateral/forward movements?</li>
<li>TMJ sounds?</li>
<li>Tenderness on palpation?</li>
<li> History of pain and habits?</li>
</ul><p>The answers should be recorded on an appropriate clinical form (image 1).</p>

<p>The most important single indicator of joint function is the amount 
of maximum opening (video 1). If any joint has reasonably normal motion, 
there is not a great deal wrong with it. If the mandible moves normally, 
the TM joint is unlikely to be significantly impaired.</p>

<p>It also is important to palpate the muscles of mastication and TM joints 
and to note any joint sounds or pain. In a patient with limitation of 
motion, looks for a scar in the chin as a sign of previous orofacial 
trauma that may have not have been thought to be important at the time.</p>

<p>Find out if the patient has any oral habits like thumb sucking (video 
2) or nail biting or a forward posture of the tongue. Both can disturb 
the development of the orofacial complex.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/opening.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/opening.jpg"><label>Video 1, Opening</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/thumb.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/thumb.jpg"><label>Video 2, Sucking habit?</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="257" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/18.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="71" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/18_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, functional data record</label><caption><p>Findings from the evaluation of jaw function = no problem.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Step 3: Evaluation of Facial Proportions and Esthetics</title><pageText><p>A critically important step in the clinical examination is the evaluation 
of facial proportions and esthetics. The goal is to detect disproportions 
and asymmetries that are major contributors to facial esthetic problems. 
Start by looking at your patient in the frontal view to evaluate the transverse 
proportions (image 1). Remember that a small degree of bilateral asymmetry 
exists in essentially all normal individuals. One way to show this is 
by creating an image of what the face would look like with the right and 
left sides duplicated (image 2). This “normal asymmetry” should 
be distinguished from a chin or nose that deviates enough to produce an 
esthetic problem. The guideline is that a deviation of more than 3-4 mm 
is enough to be noticed and therefore potentially a problem.</p>

<p>The relationship of height to width establishes the overall facial type. 
Robin Williams (relatively wide) and Dustin Hoffman (relatively narrow) 
illustrate the different types within the normal range (image 3). The 
width of the dental arches, not surprisingly, is related to the width 
of the face.</p>

<p>The relationship of the midline of each dental arch to the facial midline 
also should be noted during the clinical examination (image 4). Melissa’s 
dental and skeletal midlines are exactly coincident. It’s not enough 
to just note whether the midline of the upper and lower arches coincide—you 
need to know how the dentition fits into the face.</p>

<p>It is important to note the relationship of the dentition to the lips 
when a patient smiles (video). A video clip of the patient’s smile 
rapidly is becoming a standard part of the diagnostic records for orthodontics, 
as it becomes easy to include video in the digital record file for the 
patient. Melissa’s smile exposes all of her upper incisors and some 
gingiva, which is normal at her age but makes the upper incisor protrusion 
quite apparent.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/19.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/19_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, Melissa, frontal view</label><caption><p>Melissa, frontal view.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="287" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/20.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="79" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/20_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, Melissa, frontal facial composite views</label><caption><p>Melissa, actual view (left) and composite faces with 2 right and 2 left 
sides (center, right) showing normal asymmetry.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="399" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/21.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/21_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, Facial types</label><caption><p>Facial types: extremes of normal.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="389" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/22.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/22_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, Melissa, dental / skeletal midlines</label><caption><p>Melissa, dental / skeletal midlines.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/smile.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/smile.jpg"><label>Video, smile animation</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Evaluation of Facial Proportions and Esthetics (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>The next step in examining facial proportions is to look at your patient from 
the profile view. The goal now is to evaluate the anteroposterior jaw 
relationship, the vertical jaw relationship, and the lip prominence.</p>

<p>Let’s start by evaluating the relative prominence of the mandible 
to the maxilla. Put the patient in natural head position (relaxed, looking 
into the distance) (image 1). Then visualize where the maxilla is positioned 
in relation to the forehead. Normally we would see it slightly in front. 
Now what about the mandible? Locate the most anterior point of the chin 
and see how it relates to the forehead and the maxilla. Melissa’s 
chin is behind that line, so she has moderate mandibular deficiency. That’s 
why her profile is convex (image 2).</p>

<p>Another important aspect is the prominence of the lips and their relationship 
to each other (image 3). Note that Melissa’s lower lip is behind 
a line from the nose to the chin and well related to her chin (only slightly 
forward from the chin). So she doesn’t have protrusion of her lower 
teeth relative to the mandible that compensates for the skeletal mandibular 
deficiency.</p>

<p>Last but not least, look at the vertical proportions of her face. The 
easiest way to do this is to check to see if the facial thirds are proportional. 
The distances from the hairline to the bridge of the nose, bridge of nose 
to base of nose, and base of nose to chin should be very close to the 
same. Do you see any disproportions?</p>

<p>It also helps to visualize the mandibular plane (image 3) and relate it 
to the true vertical line. If the lower face is long, the mandibular plane 
angle usually is steep—so if you see a high mandibular plane angle, 
you should look again at lower face height. For Melissa, both the facial 
thirds and mandibular plane angle appear to be close to normal.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="395" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/23.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/23_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, Profile convex</label><caption><p>Profile evaluation in natural head position</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="301" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/24_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, Lip posture</label><caption><p>Lip position in reference to natural head position</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="388" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/25.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/25_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, Vertical thirds</label><caption><p>Vertical thirds proportion and mandibular plane inclination</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Step 4: Evaluation of Crowding/Alignment</title><pageText><p>Now evaluate the dental relationships, starting with the alignment of the 
teeth and the amount of space within each dental arch (image 1). At a 
quick look you can estimate the amount of crowding present. Is it mild 
(&lt;2 mm), moderate (2-4 mm), or severe (&gt;4 mm)? Look carefully at 
Melissa’s mandibular arch, where are the permanent canines related 
to the first primary molars? . . . No first primary molars present! space 
between canines and second primary molars nearly closed! So it looks as 
if at least moderate, probably severe crowding is likely. In the maxillary 
arch, in contrast, even though the incisors are somewhat crowded, it looks 
as if there should be enough (or nearly enough) room for the permanent 
teeth.</p>

<p>Mixed dentition space analysis at this point would quantify the space 
available for the permanent teeth. To interpret it, remember that you 
have to look again at the profile and evaluate lip protrusion (image 2). 
Is there excessive separation of her lips at rest? Is there any strain 
in bringing her lips together? How prominent are the lips relative to 
nasolabial and mentolabial concavities?</p>

<p>Since Melissa’s upper lip is a little protrusive, space analysis 
might understate her upper arch crowding. The lower lip isn’t at 
all protrusive relative to the chin, perhaps is a little retrusive, so 
crowding in the lower arch is fully expressed or even a little overstated 
by space analysis.</p>

<p>The bottom line: She’s short of space in both arches, and some of 
the potential crowding in the upper arch is concealed by protrusion of 
the upper incisors.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="328" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="58" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/17_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, occlusal views</label><caption><p>Melissa, mild maxillary, moderate to severe mandibular crowding.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="301" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/26.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/26_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, profile</label><caption><p>Melissa, profile: reasonably normal lip prominence, mandibular deficiency.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Evaluation of Occlusion</title><pageText><p>Then (image 1) look at the occlusal relationships in the three planes of space:</p>

<ol><li>transverse (posterior crossbites),</li>
<li>anteroposterior (overjet, molar and canine relationships), and</li>
<li>vertical (overbite or open bite).</li>
</ol><p>The objectives are to accurately describe the occlusion and then distinguish 
between skeletal and dental contributions to malocclusion.</p>

<p>Melissa has no posterior crossbite, so the transverse relationships 
are acceptable. She has 8 mm overjet, well above the normal 1-3 mm. 
Her overbite is 1-2 mm, normal. Her molars are Class I, but the canines 
are nearly Class II.</p>

<p>In her case the Class I molar relation was created by the mesial drift 
of her mandibular molars after premature loss of the first primary molars 
(image 2). Reference to her profile (image 3) confirms mandibular deficiency, 
so this is a skeletal Class II problem.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="410" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/16.jpg" thumbnailWidth="117" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/16_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, occlusal views</label><caption><p>Melissa, 8 mm overjet and 2 mm overbite, Class I molars but Class II canines.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="474" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/27.jpg" thumbnailWidth="84" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/27_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, posterior drift</label><caption><p>Mesial drift of molars after early loss of mandibular primary first molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="301" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/26.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/26_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, profile</label><caption><p>Melissa, profile: lack of chin prominence = mandibular deficiency.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Give Your Recommendations</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Which Diagnostic Records Are Needed?</title><pageText><p>After interviewing your patient and performing the clinical evaluation, you should 
be thinking about whether any diagnostic records are needed to provide more 
information before you give your recommendations about orthodontic treatment.</p>

<p>For this patient, which diagnostic records do you really need to provide 
an opinion?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>No further records needed</choice><choice>Panoramic radiograph</choice><choice>Cephalometric radiograph</choice><choice>Dental casts plus radiographs</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct, you need a panoramic radiograph. In the mixed dentition, a panoramic 
radiograph is the screening tool to evaluate pathology (for an orthodontic opinion, 
especially missing teeth and supernumerary teeth) and gain further insight into 
the timing of treatment.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. You really need, and should obtain, a panoramic 
radiograph to offer an informed opinion. In the mixed dentition, a panoramic 
radiograph is the screening tool to evaluate pathology (for an orthodontic 
opinion, especially missing teeth and supernumerary teeth) and gain further 
insight into the timing of treatment. The other records would be part of 
the complete set of records needed to plan orthodontic treatment but aren’t 
needed to give the parents a recommendation about treatment.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Which Diagnostic Records Are Needed? (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>Let’s review Melissa’s panoramic radiograph. She doesn’t have any 
pathologies, missing teeth, or supernumerary teeth. Look where the unerupted 
teeth are, and think further about whether there is enough space for them. 
The crowding in the lower arch looks pretty severe, doesn’t it?<br/>
How long will it be before the second premolars would be ready to erupt? 
You’d judge that by the amount of root development: They’re 
about a year away, given that they have half or less of their root formation, 
and normally would erupt when 2/3 of the root is formed.</p>

<p>Using the panoramic radiograph as a visual aid to explain space problems 
to the parents is an excellent way to help them understand. It doesn’t 
require a lot of training to see that space for the second premolars just 
isn’t going to be there.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="320" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/28.jpg" thumbnailWidth="150" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/28_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Mandibular crowding, slow development of second premolars.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Orthodontic Problems?</title><pageText><p>From your findings during the interview and the clinical evaluation, which of 
the following need to be discussed with Melissa and her parents?</p>

<p>
a. Melissa’s concerns about her teeth and appearance<br/>
b. Facial proportions and esthetics<br/>
c. Alignment and space<br/>
d. Dental relationships<br/>
e. Radiographic findings
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>a, c, and e</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice><choice>b, d, and e</choice><choice>a, b, c, e</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, your findings relative to all these areas should be discussed.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. Your findings relative to all these areas should be discussed.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Orthodontic Problems? (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>What should you tell them about each area?</p>

<ul><li> Melissa’s concerns are appropriate: The protrusive appearance 
of her front teeth can cause problems in social interactions. </li>
<li>One reason that her upper teeth appear protrusive is a problem with 
the growth of her lower jaw. It hasn’t grown forward as much 
as it should.</li>
<li> The crowding in the lower arch is worse than it appears clinically. 
This needs to be explained to the parents with the aid of the panorex, 
showing the lack of space for the succedaneous teeth.</li>
<li>All the upper teeth are too far forward relative to the lower teeth. 
This is part of the reason that she will need braces on all her teeth, 
not just the protruding front ones.</li>
<li> Melissa has a healthy mouth, which is necessary before you can 
have orthodontic treatment, so she is in good shape to go ahead with 
treatment if she wants it.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="video" resourceWidth="192" resourceHeight="144" resourceLocation="youngpatient/video/complaint_chief.mp4" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/complaint_chief.jpg"><label>Video, patient concerns</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="549" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/29.jpg" thumbnailWidth="98" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/29_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, composite pictures</label><caption><p>Melissa, extraoral and intraoral views.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="320" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/28.jpg" thumbnailWidth="150" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/28_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, panoramic radiograph</label><caption><p>Mandibular crowding, slow development of second premolars.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>To Refer or Not To Refer?</title><pageText><p>Would you refer Melissa to an orthodontist?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>Yes</choice><choice>No</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct, referring Melissa to an orthodontist is recommended.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s probably not good professional judgment. She certainly is a candidate 
for orthodontics, and her problems are severe enough to require extensive and 
prolonged treatment. Referring Melissa to an orthodontist is recommended.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>To Refer or Not To Refer? (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>Melissa is a candidate for orthodontics for three reasons:</p>

<p>1. the skeletal component of her Class II malocclusion,</p>

<p>2. the severity of the crowding, which is at least borderline for extraction, and</p>

<p>3. the excessive lip support in the upper arch, decreased lip support 
in the lower arch, and lip incompetence (lip separation at rest).</p>

<p>She will need comprehensive treatment with a complete fixed orthodontic appliance.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="549" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/29.jpg" thumbnailWidth="98" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/29_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Melissa, extraoral and intraoral views.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>When Would You Refer Her?</title><pageText><p>When would you refer her?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>Now</choice><choice>When menarche makes it definite that she is in the adolescent growth spurt</choice><choice>In another 12 months or so, when the premolars erupt</choice><choice>Between ages 12 and 13, depending on her level of maturity</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct, now is the right time to refer.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. Now is the right time to refer.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>When Would You Refer Her? (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>There are two reasons for referring her now:</p>

<p>1. Treatment for patients with skeletal Class II malocclusion should start 
no later than the time of the adolescent growth spurt, although some children 
may benefit from earlier treatment.</p>

<p>Remember that it’s the stage of physical development that’s important, 
not the stage of dental development. Many girls now undergo adolescence at surprisingly 
early ages. Melissa may be only 11, but she already has secondary sexual characteristics 
that indicate the onset of puberty.The general rule is that treatment of skeletal 
problems is most effective and efficient if done during the adolescent growth 
spurt, so you always want to refer children by the beginning of adolescence. Get 
them to the orthodontist before they are sexually mature.</p>

<p>2. Melissa also has problems in the transition from the late mixed dentition 
to the early permanent dentition, specifically the crowding in the lower 
arch and protrusion of upper incisors, which need to be addressed in the 
near future.</p>

<p>In short, she’s a candidate for treatment now for both growth modification 
and management of eruption of the teeth.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Referral Letter</title><pageText><p>In your referral letter, what would you tell the orthodontist about her problems?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>All the things included in the discussion with the parents</choice><choice>Only the positive findings from the patient’s evaluation</choice><choice>That she has a Class II crowded malocclusion</choice><choice>No referral letter with information is needed, the orthodontist will find out all the information</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct. Before seeing the child for the first time, there are a few 
things the orthodontist would like to know from you.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that is incorrect. All the things you discussed with the parent are things 
you should share with the orthodontist.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Referral Letter (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>Before seeing the child for the first time, the orthodontist would like to know from you:</p>

<ul><li>Anything useful about the child/parent’s expectations, social 
setting, etc.</li>
<li> What the orthodontic problems appear to be.</li>
<li> Whether you have taken radiographs recently that would be useful 
during the orthodontic evaluation. If so, of course, copies of those 
radiographs are needed and should be sent in advance if possible.</li>
<li>Your recommendations for treatment or recall in your practice. For 
Melissa, an appropriate referral letter might look like the one in 
the attached images, which show the sections of the letter (separated 
for greater enlargement and easier reading on the screen).</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="434" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/32.jpg" thumbnailWidth="111" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/32_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, referral letter</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="390" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/33.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/33_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, letter continued</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>What Treatment Do You Expect?</title><pageText><p>What treatment do you expect the orthodontist to suggest?</p>

<p>a. No treatment at this time, he or she will wait for all the teeth to erupt</p>

<p>b. Orthodontic treatment soon using headgear or a functional appliance 
growth modification</p>

<p>c. Comprehensive orthodontic treatment with possible extractions when 
the permanent teeth erupt</p>

<p>d. Orthognathic surgery in the future</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>a and c</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>b and d</choice><choice>a and d</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct. Because of her skeletal maturity relative to the eruption of 
the permanent teeth, growth modification treatment in the mixed dentition 
will be indicated in the near future. That could be either headgear to the 
maxillary arch or a functional appliance. It may be desirable to use a partial 
fixed appliance in the mixed dentition to reposition and align the incisors. 
If so, headgear might be the choice—and in fact, for Melissa it was 
(image 1).</p>

<p>After the permanent teeth are available, a second phase of comprehensive 
treatment to deal with the alignment/space problems definitely will be needed. 
Orthognathic surgery, however, is not needed for a patient with moderately 
severe problems like Melissa’s.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. Because of her skeletal maturity relative to the 
eruption of the permanent teeth, growth modification treatment in the mixed 
dentition will be indicated in the near future. That could be either headgear 
to the maxillary arch or a functional appliance. It may be desirable to 
use a partial fixed appliance in the mixed dentition to reposition and align 
the incisors. If so, headgear might be the choice—and in fact, for 
Melissa it was (image 1).</p>

<p>After the permanent teeth are available, a second phase of comprehensive 
treatment to deal with the alignment/space problems definitely will be needed. 
Orthognathic surgery, however, is not needed for a patient with moderately 
severe problems like Melissa’s.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="350" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/30.jpg" thumbnailWidth="137" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/30_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Melissa, age 11, beginning orthodontic treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Length of Treatment</title><pageText><p>How long do you think Melissa’s orthodontic treatment will take? That’s 
almost surely something the parents will ask you, so you need to have an 
answer—what will you tell them?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>Less than 12 months</choice><choice>12-15 months</choice><choice>15-24 months</choice><choice>More than 24 months</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct, treatment for Melissa almost surely will take more than 2 years.</p>

<p>The first phase of treatment, still in the mixed dentition, needs to start 
now, but the second phase of treatment can’t start until the remaining 
permanent teeth erupt. That won’t be for at least a year (image), 
and phase 2 will take more than a year, so the total will be greater than 
24 months.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. Treatment for Melissa almost surely will take more than 
2 years.</p>

<p>The first phase of treatment, still in the mixed dentition, needs to start 
now, but the second phase of treatment can’t start until the remaining 
permanent teeth erupt. That won’t be for at least a year (image), 
and phase 2 will take more than a year, so the total will be greater than 
24 months.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="320" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/28.jpg" thumbnailWidth="150" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/28_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Melissa, age 11, dentition at beginning of phase 1 orthodontic treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Feedback from the Orthodontist</title><pageText><p>What feedback do you expect the orthodontist to provide after he or she sees 
Melissa?</p>

<p>
a. acknowledgment of the referral and thanks for it<br/>
b. summary of problems<br/>
c. recommendations for treatment<br/>
d. copies of photographs<br/>
e. copies of cephalometric radiographs
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>all the above</choice><choice>a, b, c, d</choice><choice>a, b, c</choice><choice>only what I have asked for</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct. Let's look at the specifics of what to expect from the referral.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's incorrect. Let's look at the specifics of what to expect from the referral.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Feedback from the Orthodontist (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>You should expect a letter acknowledging the referral, with a summary of the 
patient’s problems and the orthodontist’s recommendations 
for treatment. A copy of that letter, or one in simpler language providing 
the same information, goes to the parents. If the orthodontist took panoramic, 
bitewing, or periapical radiographs, you also should expect to receive 
copies of those.</p>

<p>You may or may not get copies of photographs, depending on whether you 
have told the orthodontist you want them. Unless you specifically request 
them, you won’t get copies of the cephalometric radiographs, simply 
because they are of minimal use in family practice—but you can have 
them if you want them.</p>

<p>A typical feedback letter is shown in the attached images (with the parts 
separated for greater enlargement on the computer screen).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="413" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/34.jpg" thumbnailWidth="116" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/34_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, feedback letter</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="315" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/35.jpg" thumbnailWidth="153" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/35_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, feedback letter (cont'd.)</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Melissa’s Recall Schedule</title><pageText><p>While Melissa is in orthodontic treatment, on what schedule will you recall her 
for evaluation in your office?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>No need to see her during orthodontic treatment</choice><choice>When the orthodontist indicates it</choice><choice>Every 10-12 weeks</choice><choice>Normal 6- or 12-month recall schedule as with any other young patient</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct. Melissa needs to be seen in a normal recall schedule like any of 
your other regular patients, to check for the development of caries or other 
problems, and to reinforce the importance of oral hygiene during orthodontic 
appliance wear (image).</p>

<p>If hygiene becomes a particular problem, the orthodontist may ask for your 
help, and then Melissa might need to be seen in your office more often. 
Other special problems—which Melissa does not have at this point—also 
could be the reason for a modified recall schedule when one of your patients 
is in orthodontic treatment.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That is incorrect. Melissa needs to be seen in a normal recall schedule like 
any of your other regular patients, to check for the development of caries 
or other problems, and to reinforce the importance of oral hygiene during 
orthodontic appliance wear (image).</p>

<p>If hygiene becomes a particular problem, the orthodontist may ask for your 
help, and then Melissa might need to be seen in your office more often. 
Other special problems—which Melissa does not have at this point—also 
could be the reason for a modified recall schedule when one of your patients 
is in orthodontic treatment.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="572" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="youngpatient/images/31.jpg" thumbnailWidth="102" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="youngpatient/images/31_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Poor oral hygiene during orthodontic treatment can cause problems like decalcified 
areas or caries.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Summary</title><pageText><p>Yes indeed. It will happen: In the near future you’ll be asked to look at 
a friend’s child or patient’s child to offer an opinion as to whether 
orthodontics is needed.</p>

<p>To answer such questions, you need to</p>

<ul><li>analyze the patient’s problems,</li>
<li>decide whether orthodontic treatment is needed, and</li>
<li>apply the triage method based on problem severity to make the decision 
as to whether a child has a problem that warrants consultation with 
an orthodontist.</li>
</ul><p>Specifically, you need to</p>

<ul><li>interview the parent and patient, asking about their concerns, 
the medical/dental history, and growth status;</li>
<li>perform a clinical exam with emphasis on facial symmetry/proportions 
and jaw relationships, then the dental alignment and occlusion; and</li>
<li>obtain a panoramic radiograph in most circumstances, so that you 
can evaluate pathology, anomalies in eruption dental development, 
missing teeth, and supernumerary teeth.</li>
</ul><p>Good communication in both directions is the key to good patient management 
when a patient from your practice goes to an orthodontist. It is important for 
the patient to have regular appointments with the primary dental health provider 
while undergoing orthodontics, to monitor oral health.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>