<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<presentation><title>Space Management in Preadolescent Children</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>Lorne D. Koroluk<br/>Dept. of Orthodontics, UNC School of Dentistry<br/>Suggested reading:<i>Contemporary Orthodontics, 3rd edition</i>p.165-170, 418-429, and 452-462</additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="spacemgt/images/titlepage.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Mixed Dentition Analysis Review</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Mixed Dentition Analysis Review</title><pageText><p>The most readily identifiable orthodontic problem in the early mixed dentition is 
dental crowding. Parents initially become concerned when the larger permanent incisors 
replace nicely aligned and spaced primary incisors in the early mixed 
dentition and crowding/malalignment is obvious. Parents want to know 
how this will impact the long-term alignment of the permanent teeth 
and usually seek advice from their family dentist initially. Family 
dentists should be able to</p>

<ul>
<li>Provide an answer based on their knowledge of dental development,</li>
<li>Perform a mixed dentition space analysis,</li>
<li>Interpret the results of the analysis, and</li>
<li>Suggest appropriate interventions.</li>
</ul>

<p>The normal condition in the primary dentition is interdental spacing of the 
primary incisors (image 1). The primate spaces between the lateral incisors and 
canines in the maxillary arch, and between the canines and first molars in the 
mandibular arch of the primary dentition, provide space that is important in 
allowing alignment of the larger permanent incisors (image 2). As a general rule, 
children who present with crowded primary incisors will have major crowding 
problems in the permanent dentition (image 3). <b>Spacing in the primary 
dentition is the norm. Perfectly aligned teeth with no spacing or crowded 
teeth are not normal.</b></p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/01.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="348" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/01_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="138" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Spacing of the primary incisors</label><caption><p>Interdental spacing of the primary incisors, as in this child, is normal.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/02.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="357" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/02_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Primate spaces in the primary dentition</label><caption><p>The crowns of the developing permanent incisors lie lingual to crowns of the 
primary incisors.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/03.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="348" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/03_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="138" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Crowding of the primary incisors</label><caption><p>This child has significant crowding of the primary dentition, which is indicative 
of significant future crowding in the permanent dentition.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>MDA Review (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>During the early mixed dentition the larger permanent incisors replace the 
smaller primary incisors, and the majority of children develop some degree of 
incisor crowding.</p>

<p>Graphs from Moorrees and Chandha (<i>Angle Orthodontist</i> 35, 1965) 
illustrate the amount of average crowding or spacing present in the 
incisor segments for males and females during the transition from the 
primary dentition to the early mixed dentition (Images 1-5). In each 
of these graphs, M represents the eruption of the permanent molar; I1 
and I2 represent the eruption of the central and lateral incisor, and 
C the eruption of the permanent canine.</p>

<p>Prior to the eruption of the first permanent molars there is an average of 
about 2 mm of spacing in the maxillary incisor segment (images 1 and 2) and 
about 1 mm of spacing in the mandibular incisor segment (images 3 and 4). As 
the first permanent molars erupt, they drift forward, closing some of the 
interdental spacing found in the primary dentition. This is called the early mesial 
shift. As the larger permanent incisors erupt and replace the primary 
incisors additional crowding occurs. In the maxillary arch, males (image 
1) tend to have no incisor crowding, while females iImage 2) develop 
minor incisor crowding (&lt;1 mm) when the permanent incisors erupt. 
In the mandibular arch both males (image 3) and females (image 4) appear 
to develop 2 mm of incisor crowding with the eruption of the lateral 
incisors. In all four cases, once the primary canines exfoliate this 
initial incisor crowding resolves.</p>

<p>Some parents may become quite concerned when the nicely aligned and spaced 
primary incisors are replaced by crowded and irregular permanent incisor in the 
early mixed dentition. This information can be used to reassure parents that 
some degree of initial crowding is quite normal in the early mixed dentition 
(image 5).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/04.jpg" resourceWidth="582" resourceHeight="384" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/04_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Maxillary Arch Crowding &#8211; Males</label><caption><p>Maxillary crowding in males in the early mixed dentition.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/05.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="392" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/05_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="122" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Maxillary Arch Crowding &#8211; Females</label><caption><p>Maxillary crowding in females in the early mixed dentition.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/06.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="364" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/06_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="132" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Mandibular Arch Crowding &#8211; Males</label><caption><p>Mandibular crowding in males in the early mixed dentition.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/07.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="384" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/07_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="125" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4, Mandibular Arch Crowding &#8211; Females</label><caption><p>Mandibular crowding in females in the early mixed dentition.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/08.jpg" resourceWidth="588" resourceHeight="374" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/08_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="126" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 5, Crowding by Gender and Arch</label><caption><p>Crowding in males and females in both arches in the early mixed dentition.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>MDA Review (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>Dental crowding is a function of two things: (1) the size of the teeth, 
and (2) the size of the dental arch supporting the teeth. Many parents 
are mystified when orthodontists or dentists suggest that extraction of 
teeth is required in young children who have not started their pubertal 
growth spurt and have a lot of growth potential remaining. Dentists must 
have a basic understanding of the growth and development of the dental 
arches to answer these concerns.</p>

<p>One can graphically summarize the dimensional changes in the maxillary 
and mandibular dental arches from ages 6-18 years. In the maxillary arch 
(image 1) there is a slight decrease in arch length and a slight increase 
in arch circumference (+1 mm). The maxillary incisors erupt into a more 
facial position, which increases arch length, but the loss of leeway space 
also reduces arch length. In the mandibular arch (image 2) there is a 
reduction in both arch length (-1 mm) and arch circumference (-4 mm) with 
a slight increase in canine and molar width. The mandibular incisors tend 
to upright over this period of time, which supplements effects due to 
the loss of leeway space.</p>

<p>In patients with moderate and more severe crowding, these average growth 
changes in the dental arches are insufficient to accommodate the larger 
teeth in both arches (image 3).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/09.jpg" resourceWidth="462" resourceHeight="447" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/09_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="83" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Growth changes in the maxillary arch.</label><caption><p>Growth changes in the maxillary arch between 6-18 years of age.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/10.jpg" resourceWidth="408" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/10_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="72" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Growth changes in the mandibular arch.</label><caption><p>Growth changes in the mandibular arch between 6-18 years of age.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/11.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="308" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/11_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="156" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Comparison of maxillary &amp; mandibular arch changes</label><caption><p>Comparison of growth changes in the dental arches between 6-18 years of age.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>MDA Review (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>In the early mixed dentition, we know that incisor crowding is very common, 
especially in the lower arch, and that future growth of the dental arches will 
most likely not accommodate a significant amount of dental crowding. The Mixed 
Dentition Space Analysis gives dentists some ability to predict future dental 
crowding (image 1).</p>

<p>As you recall from earlier courses, mixed dentition space analysis has a 
number of underlying assumptions:</p>

<ol>
<li>There is a correlation between the size of the erupted mandibular 
incisors and the remaining succedaneous teeth.</li>
<li>Prediction tables are valid for your patient&#8217;s sex and ethnicity.</li>
<li>All succedaneous teeth are present and developing normally.</li>
<li>Arch dimensions do not change appreciably during growth.</li>
<li>Molar position is stable.</li>
</ol></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/12.jpg" resourceWidth="331" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/12_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="59" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, UNC Space Analysis Form</label><caption><p>University of North Carolina Space Analysis Form.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>MDA Review (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>The UNC Space Analysis Form uses the Tanaka and Johnston space analysis 
procedure to predict the size of the unerupted permanent teeth. No radiographs 
or prediction tables are required to perform the analysis, as in other analyses. 
Upper and lower dental casts with erupted permanent incisors and a 
measuring device (i.e., Boley gauge) are all that are needed.</p>

<p>The first step in the Tanaka and Johnston space analysis is the measurement 
of the erupted lower incisors using a Boley gauge or dividers (image 
1). The mixed dentition analysis (MDA) assumes that there is a correlation 
between the size of the lower incisors and unerupted canines and premolars 
in both arches.</p>

<p>The size of the unerupted permanent canine and premolars in each buccal 
segment is determined by the following simple calculation:</p>

<blockquote>
<p class="noSpaceAfter">Mandible: half the sum of the widths of the mandibular incisors + 10.5 mm</p>
<p class="noSpaceBefore">Maxilla: half the sum of the widths of the mandibular incisors + 11.0 mm</p>
</blockquote></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/13.jpg" resourceWidth="455" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/13_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="81" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Measurement of mandibular incisors</label><caption><p>Width of the mandibular incisors measured with dividers and recorded in the MDA form.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>MDA Review (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>The <b>space available</b> in the dental arch is determined by measuring 
the arch segments between the mesial surfaces of both first permanent molars 
(image 1). One must estimate an ideal dental arch where the teeth are arranged 
in a stable position in the alveolar bone. Using a Boley gauge or dividers, the 
arch segments are as follows:</p>

<ol type="a">
<li>Mesial of first permanent molar to mesial of primary canine</li>
<li>Mesial of primary canine to the mesial of the permanent central</li>
<li>Mesial of permanent central to mesial of primary canine</li>
<li>Mesial of primary canine to mesial of first permanent molar.</li>
</ol>

<p>The <b>space required</b> to accommodate the permanent teeth is determined in 
each arch by adding together:</p>

<ol type="a">
<li>The sum of the incisor widths (image 2)</li>
<li>The predicted widths of the unerupted left canine and premolars</li>
<li>The predicted widths of the unerupted right canine and premolars</li>
</ol>

<p>Space discrepancy (crowding or spacing) is calculated in the mandibular arch 
(image 3) and the maxillary arch (image 4) by:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><b>Discrepancy = Total Space Available &#8211; Total Space Required</b></p>
</blockquote></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/14.jpg" resourceWidth="427" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/14_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="76" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Space Available in the maxillary and mandibular arch</label><caption><p>The space available in the dental arch is determined.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/15.jpg" resourceWidth="466" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/15_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="83" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Incisor width in the maxillary and mandibular arch</label><caption><p>The width of the four incisors in the maxillary and mandibular arches 
is recorded.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/16.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="273" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/16_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="75"><label>Image 3, Mandibular Space Analysis</label><caption><p>The discrepancy (crowding or spacing) in the mandibular arch is calculated.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/17.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="283" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/17_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="78"><label>Image 4, Maxillary Space Analysis</label><caption><p>The discrepancy (crowding or spacing) in the maxillary arch is calculated.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>MDA Review (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>The endpoint of the analysis is a number for each arch that may be either 
positive (spacing) or negative (crowding). As you learned previously, these 
numbers have very limited significance when viewed alone. The practitioner 
must now refocus on other relationships to interpret the results for each 
individual patient. These relationships are included in sections 7-10 of 
the UNC Space Analysis Form (image 1) and include</p>

<ul>
<li>Lip posture</li>
<li>Lip competence</li>
<li>Incisor position</li>
<li>Skeletal jaw relationship</li>
<li>Future molar shift (leeway space)</li>
<li>Occlusal relationship of the 1st permanent molars</li>
</ul>

<p>The facial profile analysis (image 2) is used to assess skeletal jaw 
relationship and lip posture. These relationships are used in sections 
7 to 10 of the space analysis to interpret the results of the space 
analysis.</p>

<p>The results of the profile analysis are crucial in assessing crowding 
and incisor position. Protrusive lips, significant lip incompetence 
(&gt;4 mm) and proclined incisors indicate dental crowding even if the 
teeth are aligned on the dental arches. These patients usually require 
extraction of permanent teeth to position the lips in acceptable positions, 
reduce lip incompetence, and upright the incisors in the alveolar bone. 
The profile view on the right shows lip and mentalis strain, while the 
view on the left shows lip incompetence (image 3). These relationships 
must be considered alongside the space analysis numbers.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/18.jpg" resourceWidth="484" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/18_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="86" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Interpretation of Numerical Results</label><caption><p>Sections 7-10 of the UNC Space Analysis.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/19.jpg" resourceWidth="340" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/19_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="60" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, UNC Facial Profile Analysis</label><caption><p>The UNC Facial Profile Analysis assesses skeletal jaw relationship and 
lip posture.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/20.jpg" resourceWidth="397" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/20_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="71" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Lip incompetence and incisor protrusion</label><caption><p>Lip protrusion and incompetence due to protrusive incisors.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Interpretation of Results</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Interpretation of Results</title><pageText><p>Now that you have completed a mixed dentition analysis and determined the 
amount of predicted crowding or spacing for a patient, how do you interpret 
the numbers and use the information in planning treatment?</p>

<p>When classifying generalized crowding the following clinical descriptions 
can be used:</p>

<p>
0-2 mm/arch: mild crowding<br/>
2-4 mm/arch: moderate crowding<br/>
&gt;4 mm/arch: severe crowding<br/>
&gt;10 mm/arch: very severe crowding
</p>

<p>The type of intervention depends on:</p>

<ul>
<li>Amount of crowding (mild, moderate, or severe)</li>
<li>Location of crowding (localized or generalized)</li>
</ul>

<p>Important questions should be considered:</p>

<ul>
<li>Was there initially sufficient space, and loss of a primary tooth 
resulted in localized crowding?</li>
<li>Will a primary tooth have to be extracted, and will intervention 
to prevent space loss be required?</li>
<li>In mild cases of crowding, can the leeway space be used to align 
the teeth?</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Interpretation of Results (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>To effectively diagnose and treat spacing problems in the mixed dentition, 
dentists must be familiar with four terms:</p>
		  
<ol> 
<li>Space maintenance</li>
<li>Space regaining</li>
<li>Space management</li>
<li>Serial extraction</li>
</ol>
		
<p>The definition of each of these terms is based on the results of the 
mixed dentition analysis. The degree and location of crowding will determine 
which of the above strategies is employed in the mixed dentition.</p>

<p>The first three techniques are suggested for children in the mixed dentition 
with mild crowding, and serial extraction is suggested for children with severe 
crowding who will receive later treatment with a fixed orthodontic appliance. 
Using these techniques during the mixed dentition may simplify future 
comprehensive orthodontic treatment in the permanent dentition. Each 
one of these terms will be explained in separate sections of this module 
to help clarify the differences.</p>

<p>Children with more severe generalized crowding in the mixed dentition will 
need comprehensive fixed orthodontic treatment, involving arch expansion or 
extraction of permanent teeth, and may be best treated by an orthodontist.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Space Maintenance</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Space Maintenance</title><pageText><p>In a patient with adequate space for the permanent teeth, space maintenance 
is the intervention used to prevent loss of space after extraction of a primary 
first or second molar. Once a primary molar is extracted, mesial drift and distal 
tipping of adjacent teeth will occur, reducing the space available for 
eruption of the underlying permanent premolars.</p>

<p>A number of factors must be evaluated prior to the initiation of space 
maintenance:</p>

<ol class="spaced">
<li> Space analysis should confirm that there is adequate space available.</li>

<li>When was the primary molar extracted? Space loss almost always starts 
immediately after the loss of a primary molar. If the tooth was lost 
more than 3 months prior, space loss has occurred, and space regaining 
will be required rather than space maintenance.</li>

<li>When will the underlying permanent tooth erupt? If the permanent 
tooth will require more than 6 months to erupt, space maintenance 
will be required. Eruption charts give average values for the general 
population; one must remember that individual variation exists (image 
1). Dental age as determined by assessing the general eruption schedule 
and root development (image 2) is more informative than chronological 
age. A permanent tooth normally erupts when 2/3 to 3/4 of root development 
is complete, and in general, a permanent tooth takes about 1 month 
to erupt through 1 mm of overlying bone. Extraction of primary teeth 
can also either accelerate or slow the eruption of underlying permanent 
teeth depending on root development.</li>

<li> Is there a permanent successor tooth present (image 3)? If not, 
long-term maintenance of the space for eventual prosthetic replacement 
may or may not be the best plan. This must be weighed against the 
possibility of closing the space orthodontically or forgoing space 
maintenance and allowing the permanent teeth to drift into the extraction 
site to close the space.</li>
</ol></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/21.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="360" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/21_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Tooth eruption and development chart.</label><caption><p>Tooth eruption and development chart.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/22.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="420" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/22_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="114" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Incomplete root development</label><caption><p>Incomplete root development in a maxillary incisor.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/23.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="372" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/23_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="129" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Congenitally missing second premolar</label><caption><p>Congenitally missing second premolar.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Space Maintenance (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>A number of different types of space maintainers can be used after the loss 
of primary teeth. Generally the appliances can be classified as:</p>

<ul>
<li>Fixed (cannot normally be removed) (image 1)</li>
<li>Removable (can be removed by the practitioner for minor adjustments 
or can be removed by the patient to allow easier access for oral hygiene)(image 
2)</li>
</ul>

<p>With any type of appliance, adequate follow-up is crucial. Space maintainers 
are not an &#8220;insert it and forget it&#8221; type of treatment. All patients 
must be on a regular recall schedule and have adequate oral hygiene to ensure 
success.</p>

<p>Patients with space maintainers are instructed to avoid hard, sticky, 
and chewy foods to decrease the chance of damage and loosening of appliances. 
Fixed appliances reduce the chance of failure, but some children do 
not follow these suggestions very well and damage even the best-designed 
fixed space maintainers.</p>

<p>The adaptation of orthodontic bands on primary teeth, especially first 
primary molars, can be difficult. This reduces the effectiveness of 
fixed banded appliances on these teeth. But this is even more of a problem 
with removable appliances, since primary teeth do not have a pronounced 
height of contour that can be used to engage retentive elements such 
as wire clasps. </p>

<p>In general, fixed space maintainers are more effective in children than 
removable space maintainers (image 3).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/24.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="398" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/24_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Fixed space maintainers</label><caption><p>Examples of a fixed space maintainers.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/25.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/25_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Removable space maintainers</label><caption><p>Example of a removable space maintainer.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/26.jpg" resourceWidth="347" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/26_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="62" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Fixed and removable space maintainers</label><caption><p>Fixed and a removable space maintainers.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Space Maintenance (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p><b>Fixed Space Maintainers</b></p>

<p><i>1. Loss of a single tooth</i>.<br/>
Band and loop space maintainers are most commonly used after the extraction 
of a single primary first molar in the primary or mixed dentition (image 
1). Bilateral band and loop space maintainers are indicated if both first 
primary molars are lost in an arch prior to the eruption of the permanent 
incisors. A variation of this appliance is the crown and loop space maintainer 
(image 2).</p>

<p><i>2. Loss of multiple teeth</i>.<br/>
If multiple primary teeth are lost and both the permanent incisors and 
first permanent molars have erupted, a lingual arch (mandible) (image 
3) or a Nance appliance (maxilla) can be used to prevent posterior space 
loss. Both appliances require the use of cemented orthodontic bands to 
attach the appliance to the 1st permanent molars. Variations of both appliances 
can be made to be removable by the use of special lingual attachments 
on the molars. The appliances can also include adjustment loops that can 
be activated to procline the incisors and tip the molars distally.</p>

<p>Lower lingual arches are contraindicated prior to the eruption of the 
permanent mandibular incisors. Remember, the permanent lower incisors 
tend to erupt lingual to the primary incisors. A lingual arch that is 
contoured to the lingual surfaces of the primary teeth can impede the 
eruption of the permanent teeth (image 4).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/27.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="426" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/27_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="113" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Band and loop space maintainer</label><caption><p>Band and loop space maintainers replacing a first primary molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/28.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="427" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/28_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Crown and loop space maintainer</label><caption><p>Crown and loop space maintainer replacing a primary molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/29.jpg" resourceWidth="564" resourceHeight="390" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/29_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="116" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Lower lingual arch space maintainer</label><caption><p>A lower lingual arch cemented to the first permanent molars.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/30.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="345" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/30_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="139" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4, Lower lingual arch impeding eruption of incisors</label><caption><p>A lower lingual arch impeding the eruption of lower incisors.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Space Maintenance (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p><b>Early Loss of Primary Second Molar</b></p>

<p>A distal shoe space maintainer is used in the primary dentition or early 
permanent dentition after the extraction of a 2nd primary molar in patients 
whose 1st permanent molar has not erupted (image 1). If at all possible, 
the 2nd primary molar should be maintained through endodontic intervention 
(i.e., pulpectomy) even if the prognosis is guarded, because the intact 
tooth is a much better space maintainer than a distal shoe appliance.</p>

<p>Radiographs are used to construct the appliance, which uses a blade to 
engage the mesial surface of the 1st permanent molar to guide its eruption 
(Image 2). As the erupting permanent molar engages the blade, it is guided 
into the correct position in the arch. Distal shoe space maintainers can 
fail to guide the eruption of the first permanent molar. In this radiograph 
(image 3) the molar has drifted forward underneath the blade of the space 
maintainer and become positioned underneath the wire loop. The space maintainer 
must be removed and the tooth allowed to erupt into the mouth. Space regaining 
may then be used to reposition the tooth distally into a normal position.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/31.jpg" resourceWidth="552" resourceHeight="354" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/31_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="125" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Distal shoe space maintainer</label><caption><p>A distal shoe space maintainer designed to guide the eruption of the 
first permanent molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/32.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="350" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/32_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="137" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Radiograph of a distal shoe space maintainer</label><caption><p>Radiograph of a successful distal shoe space maintainer.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/33.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="251" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/33_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="69"><label>Image 3, Failure of distal shoe space maintainer</label><caption><p>Failure of a distal shoe space maintainer. The appliance must be removed to 
allow the molar to erupt.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Space Maintenance (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p><b>Removable Space Maintainers</b></p>

<p>Removable acrylic partial denture space maintainers can be used when multiple 
posterior teeth have been lost (image 1). In these cases, long spans of 
wire make the use of band and loop space maintainers impractical, and 
unerupted permanent incisors make the use of a lingual arch problematic. 
Clasps are used to retain the appliances, and acrylic can be placed into 
the extraction sites to prevent tooth movement. The appliances allow ready 
access for oral hygiene in patients with a high caries rate. Compliance 
with wearing the appliance can then become an issue. If the appliance 
is not worn all the time, space loss will occur.</p>

<p>A flow chart has been developed to help in the decision-making process 
when planning space maintenance in the primary and mixed dentitions (image 
2). Part of the flow chart deals with treatment options for loss of a 
single primary posterior tooth (image 3). This next part of the flow chart 
shows the treatment options when there is loss of multiple posterior primary 
teeth, the first permanent molars are erupted, and the permanent incisors 
are not erupted (image 4). The last section of the flow chart illustrates 
treatment options when there is loss of multiple posterior permanent teeth 
and the first permanent molars and incisors are erupted (image 5).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/34.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/34_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Removable space maintainers</label><caption><p>Removable space maintainers used when multiple teeeth are extracted.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/35.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/35_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Flow chart showing space maintenance decisions.</label><caption><p>Flow chart for posterior space maintenance.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/36.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="323" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/36_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="148" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Flow chart showing cont&#8217;d.</label><caption><p>Flow chart continued.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/37.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="304" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/37_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="158" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4, Flow chart showing cont&#8217;d.</label><caption><p>Flow chart continued.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/38.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="279" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/38_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="77"><label>Image 5, Flow chart showing cont&#8217;d.</label><caption><p>Flow chart continued.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Space Regaining</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Space Regaining</title><pageText><p>If space maintenance is not instituted after extraction of a primary tooth, 
space loss will occur in a number of months. Repositioning the teeth to 
regain space, not just space maintenance, is required to stabilize the 
situation. Up to 3 mm of space can be reestablished in a localized area 
with relatively simple appliances. Localized space loss greater than 3 
mm constitutes a severe problem and is more difficult to manage.</p>

<p>In this case (image 1) localized space loss has occurred in the maxillary 
arch after the premature loss of the upper left second primary molar. 
The first permanent molar has drifted forward into the extraction space 
as it erupted. A removable acrylic appliance was used to regain the space 
by distalizing the permanent molar using a wire spring. The space for 
the second primary molar was regained, and space maintenance was used 
to maintain the regained space after the space maintainer was discontinued.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/39.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="444" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/39_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="108" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Maxillary space regaining appliance</label><caption><p>Space regaining for a maxillary second primary molar.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Space Regaining (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>Image 1 illustrates an example of a simple single-tooth space regaining appliance 
that resembles a band and loop space maintainer. There are two coil springs 
on the wire loop, which is free to slide through the tubes attached to 
the orthodontic band. The springs are compressed when the appliances is 
cemented and apply a force to push the teeth apart.</p>

<p>Space regaining is easier in the maxillary than the mandibular arch, and 
removable appliances can be designed to utilize springs (image 2) or expansion 
screws (image 3) to reposition the teeth. At the same time these forces 
tend to dislodge the appliance, stressing the retention elements, which 
limits the amount of force that can be applied to the teeth. Removable 
appliances generally are designed to apply forces to a single point on 
a tooth surface resulting in tipping of the tooth. As a majority of space 
loss manifests itself as tipping, these types of forces can be used with 
removable appliances to reposition teeth to their normal position.</p>

<p>If an expansion screw is used to regain space, the screw should be activated 
slowly (1/4 turn 2-3 times per week). When the screw is activated too 
quickly, the teeth will not move at the same rate as the screw is activated 
and the appliance may not seat correctly.</p>

<p>Extraoral forces can be applied to maxillary molars through the use of 
headgear. Unilateral space loss in the maxillary arch can be treated using 
an asymmetric headgear (image 4) in which the outer bow of the headgear 
on the side with space loss is longer than the unaffected side. A cervical 
pull neck strap is used along with the asymmetric outer bow to distalize 
the first permanent molar and upright the molar at the same time if mesial 
tipping is present.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/40.jpg" resourceWidth="504" resourceHeight="374" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/40_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="108" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Simple space regaining appliance</label><caption><p>Simple single tooth space regaining appliance.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/41.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="441" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/41_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="109" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Space regaining appliances with wire springs</label><caption><p>Space regaining appliances with various wire spring designs.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/42.jpg" resourceWidth="297" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/42_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Space regaining appliances with expansion screws</label><caption><p>Space regaining appliances with expansions screws.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/43.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="427" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/43_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4, Asymmetric cervical headgear</label><caption><p>An asymmetric cervical pull headgear to regain maxillary space unilaterally.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Space Regaining (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>In the mandibular arch, removable space regaining appliances are less 
efficient due to problems with irritation of the lingual tissues, breakage, 
and lack of retention (image 1).</p>

<p>More effective appliances in the mandibular arch are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Active lingual arch</li>
<li>Lip bumper</li>
</ul>

<p>A passive lingual arch can be used for space maintenance in the mandibular 
arch when multiple posterior teeth have been lost. Lingual arches can also be 
designed to actively apply a distal force to the molars and procline the incisors, 
thus regaining space bilaterally in the mandibular arch. Adjustable loops of wire, 
fabricated into the posterior sections of the lingual arch, can be opened 
to expand the length of the lingual arch (image 2). Since lingual arches 
are usually constructed of heavy round steel wire, large single activations 
generate excessive large forces. The loops must be opened only a little 
at the time.</p>

<p>A lip bumper (image 3) is attached to the lower first molars and has 
a heavy labial wire joining the orthodontic bands. The anterior portion 
of this heavy wire is coated with acrylic and is positioned off the 
labial surface of the teeth so it actively stretches the lower lip away 
from the teeth. The lip in turn puts force on the wire and the wire 
transfers the force to the molar teeth.</p>

<p>Both the active lower lingual arch and the lip bumper regain space by 
tipping the mandibular molars distally while proclining the incisors. With a lip 
bumper, even though the device does not touch the incisors, tongue forces procline 
the incisors when it eliminates lip pressure against them.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/44.jpg" resourceWidth="522" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/44_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="93" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Removable mandibular space regaining appliance</label><caption><p>Removable mandibular space regaining appliance.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/45.jpg" resourceWidth="492" resourceHeight="387" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/45_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="102" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Adjustable lingual arch</label><caption><p>An adjustable lingual arch can be used for mandibular space regaining.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/46.jpg" resourceWidth="352" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/46_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="63" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3, Lip bumper appliance</label><caption><p>A lip bumper with an anterior acrylic shield.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Space Management</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Space Management</title><pageText><p>In patients with generalized rather than localized crowding predicted to be less 
than 4 mm, space management uses leeway space to align the teeth. The mixed dentition 
space analysis shows the amount of crowding that could be alleviated 
if mesial shifting of the permanent molars were prevented.</p>

<p>Leeway space (image 1) is the difference in the mesial-distal widths 
of the teeth in the primary buccal segments (canine, first molar, and 
second molar) and the permanent buccal segments (canine, first premolar, 
and second premolar). The late mesial shift occurs with the exfoliation 
of the primary second molars around 11-12 years of age. Since the primary 
molars are larger than the premolars that replace them, the permanent 
first molars can move mesially with the loss of the primary second molars. 
In the majority of cases the leeway space is larger in the lower arch 
than the upper arch, which allows the lower molar to shift further anteriorly 
than the upper molar and establish a Class I occlusal relationship.</p>

<p>On average the leeway space per arch is:</p>

<ul class="spaced">
<li>Maxillary arch = 0.9 mm/quadrant</li>
<li> Mandibular arch = 1.8 mm/quadrant</li>
</ul>

<p>These are average values, and there may be significant variations among 
individual patients. If leeway space is maintained, however, the average patient 
has nearly 4 mm of space in the mandibular arch that can be used for the relief 
of incisor crowding.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/47.jpg" resourceWidth="441" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/47_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="78" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Leeway Space in the mixed dentition</label><caption><p>Leeway space in the buccal segments of the primary and the permanent dentition.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Space Management (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>In space management, prior to loss of the primary buccal segments, a lingual 
arch is placed to prevent the late mesial shift, the mesial drifting of 
the permanent molars following exfoliation of the primary teeth. The lingual 
arch can also be activated slightly to tip the molars distally and the 
incisors facially, slightly expanding the arches to gain additional space. 
Image 1 shows a series of slides depicting space management in the late 
mixed dentition. Initially there is a mild amount of incisor crowding. 
A lingual arch is placed and the second primary molars are disked, allowing 
the anterior teeth to align. Once the premolars have erupted, the lingual 
arch can be removed and the incisors are relatively well aligned.</p>

<p>Disking primary canines and molars can also be used to provide space for 
alignment of the permanent teeth. A one-sided end-cutting diamond disk 
can be used to reduce the width of the primary canines and create sufficient 
space to allow the permanent incisors to realign in the early mixed dentition 
when a mild amount of crowding is present (image 2).</p>

<p>The mandibular leeway space allows the lower first permanent molars to 
shift mesially into a Class I molar relationship. If a lower lingual arch 
is placed to utilize the leeway space to align the permanent mandibular 
teeth, a Class I molar relationship may not result. In cases where a lower 
lingual arch is used for space management, headgear may be required to 
distalize the maxillary molars to establish a Class I molar relationship.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/48.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="435" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/48_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="110" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Space management in the late mixed dentition</label><caption><p>Lingual arch used for space management in the late mixed dentition.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/49.jpg" resourceWidth="462" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/49_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="82" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Disking of primary teeth</label><caption><p>A one-sided diamond disk can be used to reduce the width of the primary teeth.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Space Management (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>A common sign of severe crowding in the early mixed dentition is early unilateral 
loss of a primary canine, which results in a shift of the mandibular dental 
midline (image 1). Initially there is inadequate space for the eruption 
of the permanent mandibular lateral incisor. As the incisor erupts it 
causes extensive resportion of the mesial surface of the primary mandibular 
canine, which causes increased mobility and early loss of the tooth. After 
the canine is lost unilaterally, the incisors are free to shift toward 
the side where the canine was lost.</p>

<p>In these cases it is best to extract the contralateral primary canine 
and place a lingual arch. This prevents the incisors from moving lingually 
and allows self-correction of the midline shift, which can occur if the 
incisors have not drifted too far laterally. A partial fixed appliance 
may be used to actively create space and correct the midline shift. A 
lower lingual arch can be used to maintain the leeway space in the mandibular 
arch while a fixed orthodontic appliance (first molar bands, bonded brackets 
on incisors--often called a 2x4 appliance) is used to align the mandibular 
incisors and correct the midline shift. The 2x4 appliance along with the 
LLA can be activated to create arch length by advancing the incisors and 
distally tipping the lower molars (image 2).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/50.jpg" resourceWidth="322" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/50_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Early unilateral loss of a mandibular primary canine</label><caption><p>Early unilateral loss of a mandibular primary canine with a shift of the midline.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/51.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="373" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/51_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="129" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Lingual arch and 2x4 appliance</label><caption><p>A lower lingual arch and fixed 2x4 appliance used to align mandibular incisors.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Space Management (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>Patients with &gt;4 mm of crowding/arch will require more extensive treatment and 
may best be referred to an orthodontist.</p>

<p>The critical treatment decision in these patients is whether to expand 
the dental arches to create space to align the teeth or to extract permanent 
teeth in each quadrant (usually, first premolars) to make room for the 
others. This subject is covered in detail in the Level IV teaching program 
To Extract Or Not To Extract, Part 1. Expansion of the dental arches to 
create space must not cause excessive incisor protrusion, compromise alveolar 
bone support or periodontal attachment, or exceed the tolerance of the 
soft tissues (i.e., produce lip incompetence and protrusion).</p>

<p>Nonextraction treatment may require dental and/or skeletal expansion, 
distalization of posterior teeth, alteration of incisor position or angulation, 
and stripping of teeth to reduce their mesiodistal widths. A complete 
fixed appliance and 18-24 months of treatment time usually are necessary.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Serial Extraction</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Serial Extraction</title><pageText><p>In some children, the mixed dentition analysis will predict a very significant 
amount of crowding (image 1). If the space discrepancy is large enough, 
intervention to gain sufficient space to align all the permanent teeth 
in a stable position will be futile. Extraction of primary and permanent 
teeth will be required during the mixed dentition to reduce crowding and 
irregularity and allow the permanent teeth to erupt through keratinized 
tissue into more normal positions in the alveolus. Serial extraction can 
be defined as the orderly removal of selected primary and permanent teeth 
in a predetermined sequence to alleviate crowding.</p>

<p>Historically, serial extraction was developed in the hope of providing 
a way to treat severe crowding while eliminating the need for future appliance 
therapy. Time has shown that it does not result in ideal tooth positions 
or eliminate the need for future orthodontic treatment. The main advantage 
of serial extraction is that it potentially makes future orthodontic treatment 
less complicated.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/52.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="432" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/52_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="111" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Serial extraction candidate</label><caption><p>Intraoral photos and panorex radiograph of a serial extraction candidate 
ready for extraction of the first premolars.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Serial Extraction (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>The ideal patient for serial extraction should have:</p>
		
<ol class="spaced">
<li>Early mixed dentition with a large amounted of predicted crowding, 
10 mm or discrepancy per arch. If the amount of crowding is less than 
10 mm, serial extraction is not recommended because residual spacing 
will result and more uncontrolled tipping of the teeth will occur 
(image 1).</li>

<li>No skeletal disproportions.</li>

<li>Class I molar relationship.</li>

<li>Normal overbite. Serial extractions will deepen the bite.</li>

<li> No congenitally missing permanent teeth.</li>
</ol>
		
<p>Even in the ideal situation, a later phase of comprehensive orthodontic 
treatment is usually required to correct the sequelae of serial extraction.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/53.jpg" resourceWidth="596" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/53_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="106" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Residual effects of serial extraction</label><caption><p>Drifting and tipping of permanent teeth after serial extraction.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Serial Extraction (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>The sequence followed during serial extractions is designed to allow the 
first premolars to erupt ahead of the canines so that the first premolars can be 
extracted early to allow eruption of the canines and second premolars. If severe 
crowding exists, the result is that in each quadrant, the canine and second premolar 
share the space vacated by the first premolar.</p>

<p>Normally, in the maxillary arch the first premolar erupts before the 
permanent canine, which is ideal for serial extractions. However in 
the lower arch, the first premolar erupts along with or after the permanent 
canine. This makes serial extractions in the lower arch trickier. If 
the primary 1st molar is extracted when the root of the underlying first 
premolar is approximately 1/2 to 2/3 developed, the eruption of the 
first premolar can be accelerated.</p>

<p><i>Step 1 of serial extraction sequence</i><br/>
Primary canines are extracted first to allow the permanent incisors to 
align (image 1). A lower lingual arch may be placed to prevent the lower 
incisors from retroclining and deepening the bite prior to the eruption 
of the permanent canines.</p>

<p><i>Step 2 of serial extraction sequence</i><br/>
The first primary molars are extracted when the roots of the lower first 
premolars are about 2/3 formed (image 2). This will accelerate the eruption 
of the first premolars so they erupt before the canines.</p>

<p><i>Step 3 of serial extraction sequence</i><br/>
The first premolars are then extracted soon after they erupt. This allows the 
canine and second premolars to erupt into position.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/54.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="404" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/54_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="119" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Extraction of primary canines</label><caption><p>The first step in the serial extraction process is extraction of the primary.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/55.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="159" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/55_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="44"><label>Image 2, Extraction of 1st primary molars</label><caption><p>The second step in the serial extraction process is extraction of the first 
primary molars.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Serial Extraction (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>Serial extraction is not a panacea for the treatment of severe crowding. In the 
vast majority of patients, future comprehensive orthodontic treatment 
is required to treat the tipping, residual spacing, and increased overbite 
that usually occurs after serial extraction (image 1). The advantage of 
serial extraction is that the comprehensive treatment usually is shorter 
and less complicated than if serial extractions had not been done.</p>

<p>In cases with very severe crowding, the amount of residual tipping and 
drifting may be minimal after serial extractions, as shown in this panoramic 
radiograph of a patient who had serial extractions but no orthodontic 
treatment (image 2).</p>

<p>Once the sequence of serial extraction has been initiated, a prudent dentist 
might repeat the mixed dentition analysis space analysis and/or refer 
the patient for an orthodontic consult prior to extracting the first premolars. 
As a general rule, extraction of the permanent teeth should not be done 
before arrangements for future fixed appliance treatment are in place.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/56.jpg" resourceWidth="591" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/56_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="105" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1, Tipping and drifting of the teeth after serial extraction</label><caption><p>Tipping of teeth is common after serial extraction.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/57.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="332" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/57_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="145" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2, Panorex of reasonable result after serial extractions</label><caption><p>Reasonable results after serial extraction without orthodontic treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Self-Test Referral</title><pageText><p>The self-test section of this program is designed to help you be sure you 
have understood the material. Take it now, and use it as a guide for further 
study and review.</p>

<p>Copyright 2003, UNC Dept. of Orthodontics</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Instructions</title><pageText><ol>
<li>View the teaching program.</li>
<li>Use the mouse to mark the correct answer(s) to each question.</li>
<li>Review the feedback from the program&#8212;it will tell you if you&#8217;re 
right or wrong, and why.</li>
</ol>

<p>Reading: <i>Contemporary Orthodontics,</i> 3rd edition, pages 165-170, 
418-429, and 452-462.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is <b>not</b> an underlying assumption of a complete mixed 
dentition space analysis (like the UNC analysis)?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>All succedaneous teeth are present and developing normally.</choice><choice>Males have larger teeth than females.</choice><choice>Molar position is predictable.</choice><choice>The size of the erupted mandibular incisors is well correlated with the unerupted buccal segments.</choice><choice>Prediction tables are valid for all patients.</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right; even though males do have larger teeth than females, that is not 
one of the assumptions of the UNC mixed dentition space analysis. Mesial 
drift of the 1st permanent molars is assumed to occur when 2nd primary molars 
are lost, and calculating the amount of drift to correct the molar relationship 
is an important part of the space analysis procedure. It is assumed that 
all teeth are present and will erupt, that the size of the incisors can 
be used to predict the size of the unerupted canine, premolars can be used 
to predict the size of the unerupted teeth, and that prediction tables for 
this purpose will be valid.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. Even though males do have larger teeth than females, 
that is not one of the assumptions of the UNC mixed dentition space analysis. 
Mesial drift of the 1st permanent molars is assumed to occur when 2nd primary 
molars are lost, and calculating the amount of drift to correct the molar 
relationship is an important part of the space analysis procedure. It is 
assumed that all teeth are present and will erupt, that the size of the 
incisors can be used to predict the size of the unerupted canine, premolars 
can be used to predict the size of the unerupted teeth, and that prediction 
tables for this purpose will be valid.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/12.jpg" resourceWidth="331" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/12_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="59" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>UNC Space Analysis Form.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>Which of the following additional factors are evaluated during interpretation 
of the numerical results in sections 7-10 of the UNC Space Analysis Form?</p>

<p>
a. Lip posture<br/>
b. Molar shift<br/>
c. Facial profile analysis results<br/>
d. Depth of the curve of Spee
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>a and c</choice><choice>b and d</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right; all of these factors are evaluated in sections 7 through 10 
of the UNC Space Analysis Form except the depth of the curve of Spee. The facial 
profile analysis is used to analyze lip posture, mandibular incisor position, 
and skeletal jaw relationship, which all have a direct relationship on space 
analysis in the dental arches. The depth of the curve of Spee, although 
it does have implications to the space required to align the teeth in the 
mandibular arch, is not part of the UNC Space Analysis Form.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. All of these factors are evaluated in sections 7 through 
10 of the UNC Space Analysis Form except the depth of the curve of Spee. 
The facial profile analysis is used to analyze lip posture, mandibular incisor 
position, and skeletal jaw relationship, which all have a direct relationship 
on space analysis in the dental arches. The depth of the curve of Spee, 
although it does have implications to the space required to align the teeth 
in the mandibular arch, is not part of the UNC Space Analysis Form.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/18.jpg" resourceWidth="484" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/18_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="86" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Sections 7-10 of the UNC Space Analysis.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>(A) A lower lingual arch is recommended for bilateral space maintenance in the 
mixed dentition prior to the eruption of the mandibular permanent incisors, 
because (B) The mandibular permanent incisors erupt lingually to the primary 
incisors.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, the first statement is false, but the second one is true. A lower 
lingual arch is contraindicated for use in the primary or early mixed dentition 
prior to the eruption of the mandibular permanent incisors. Bilateral band 
and loop space maintainers are indicated in these situations. The second 
statement is true as the mandibular incisors usually erupt lingual to the 
primary incisors. A lower lingual arch would impede the eruption of the 
mandibular permanent incisors.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. The first statement is false, but the second one is 
true. A lower lingual arch is contraindicated for use in the primary or 
early mixed dentition prior to the eruption of the mandibular permanent 
incisors. Bilateral band and loop space maintainers are indicated in these 
situations. The second statement is true as the mandibular incisors usually 
erupt lingual to the primary incisors. A lower lingual arch would impede 
the eruption of the mandibular permanent incisors.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/30.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="345" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/30_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="139" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>A lower lingual arch impeding the eruption of lower incisors.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>Which of the following can be used as space regaining appliances?</p>

<p>
a. Distal shoe<br/>
b. Lower lingual arch<br/>
c. Transpalatal arch<br/>
d. Band and loop
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>a and c</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. Lower lingual arches and transpalatal arches can be used as passive 
space maintenance appliances, but they can also be used as active appliances 
to regain space in the maxillary or mandibular arches. Omega loops in the 
lingual arch can be opened that will distally tip the molars and procline 
the lower incisors. Transpalatal arches can be adjusted to derotate and 
distalize a maxillary molar. The band and loop and distal shoe appliances 
are passive space maintainers and cannot be adjusted to regain space.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. The correct answer is b and c. Lower lingual arches 
and transpalatal arches can be used as passive space maintenance appliances, 
but they can also be used as active appliances to regain space in the maxillary 
or mandibular arches. Omega loops in the lingual arch can be opened that 
will distally tip the molars and procline the lower incisors. Transpalatal 
arches can be adjusted to derotate and distalize a maxillary molar. The 
band and loop and distal shoe appliances are passive space maintainers and 
cannot be adjusted to regain space.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/45.jpg" resourceWidth="492" resourceHeight="387" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/45_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="102" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>An adjustable lingual arch can be used for mandibular space regaining.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>Space regaining should be limited to cases with</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>0-3 mm of generalized space loss.</choice><choice>3-5 mm of generalized space loss.</choice><choice>0-3 mm of localized space loss.</choice><choice>3-5 mm of localized space loss.</choice><choice>bilateral space loss.</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s correct. If space maintenance is not instituted after extraction of a primary 
tooth, space loss will occur in a number of months. Repositioning the teeth 
to regain space is then required. Up to 3 mm of space can be reestablished 
in a localized area with relatively simple appliances. Localized space loss 
greater than 3 mm constitutes a severe problem and is more difficult to 
manage.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. If space maintenance is not instituted after extraction 
of a primary tooth, space loss will occur in a number of months. Repositioning 
the teeth to regain space is then required. Up to 3 mm of space can be reestablished 
in a localized area with relatively simple appliances. Localized space loss 
greater than 3 mm or generalized space loss constitute severe problems and 
are more difficult to manage.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/39.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="444" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/39_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="108" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Localized space regaining in the maxillary arch.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>(A) Space management can be used to accommodate up to 4 mm of crowding in the 
transition from the mixed dentition to the permanent dentition, because 
(B) This much space typically is lost as the permanent first molars shift 
mesially after exfoliation of the primary second molars.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right; both statements are true and related. Space management uses a lingual 
arch to prevent loss of the leeway space during the late mixed dentition. 
The leeway space, which can be up to 4 mm in the mandibular arch, can then 
be used to accommodate mild crowding in the permanent dentition. Loss of 
the leeway space occurs when the primary second molars are exfoliated and 
the permanent molars shift mesially.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong, both statements are true and related. Space management 
uses a lingual arch to prevent loss of the Leeway space during the late 
mixed dentition. The Leeway space, which can be up to 4 mm in the mandibular 
arch, can then be used to accommodate mild crowding in the permanent dentition. 
Loss of the leeway space occurs when the primary second molars are exfoliated 
and the permanent molars shift mesially.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/48.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="435" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/48_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="110" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Lingual arch used for space management in the late mixed dentition.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>A lower lingual arch that utilizes the mandibular leeway space to align the 
mandibular teeth may</p>

<p>
a. interfere with the early mesial shift.<br/>
b. require that the maxillary molars be distalized to obtain a Class I molar 
relationship.<br/>
c. be indicated for use in cases with a mild amount of crowding.<br/>
d. be indicated for use in cases with a moderate amount of crowding.
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>a and c</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>a, b, and d</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s correct. During space management the late mesial shift of the mandibular 
molars is prevented. The late mesial shift and loss of the mandibular leeway 
space usually allows the lower first permanent molars to shift mesially 
into a Class I molar relationship. If a lower lingual arch is placed to 
utilize the leeway space to align the permanent mandibular teeth, a Class 
I molar relationship may not result. In cases where a lower lingual arch 
is used for space management, headgear may then be required to distalize 
the maxillary molars to establish a Class I molar relationship. Space management 
is indicated for use in cases with mild crowding. The leeway space is not 
sufficient to accommodate moderate crowding.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. During space management the late mesial shift of the 
mandibular molars is prevented. The late mesial shift and loss of the mandibular 
leeway space usually allows the lower first permanent molars to shift mesially 
into a Class I molar relationship. If a lower lingual arch is placed to 
utilize the leeway space to align the permanent mandibular teeth, a Class 
I molar relationship may not result. In cases where a lower lingual arch 
is used for space management, headgear may then be required to distalize 
the maxillary molars to establish a Class I molar relationship. Space management 
is indicated for use in cases with mild crowding. The leeway space is not 
sufficient to accommodate moderate crowding. The early mesial shift occurs 
with the eruption of the first permanent molars (approximately age 6 years) 
and the closure of the primate spaces in the early mixed dentition.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>In the early mixed dentition, premature unilateral loss of a primary mandibular 
canine</p>

<p>
a. indicates significant incisor crowding.<br/>
b. results in a shift of the dental midline to the affected side.<br/>
c. occurs during the eruption of the adjacent permanent lateral incisor.<br/>
d. requires no intervention.
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>a and c</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. Premature unilateral loss of a primary mandibular canine usually 
indicates significant incisor crowding. There is insufficient space for 
the eruption of the adjacent permanent lateral incisor. As the lateral incisor 
erupts, it prematurely resorbs the mesial surface of the primary canine, 
which causes it to be lost early. The unilateral loss of the primary canine 
then results in a shifting of the dental midline to the affected side. Intervention 
is usually recommended in these cases. The contralateral primary is extracted 
and a lingual arch is placed to encourage self-correction of the midline. 
Active correction of the midline can also be done.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That&#8217;s wrong. Intervention is usually recommended in these cases. The contralateral 
primary is extracted and a lingual arch is placed to encourage self-correction 
of the midline. Active correction of the midline can also be done. Premature 
unilateral loss of a primary mandibular canine usually indicates significant 
incisor crowding. There is insufficient space for the eruption of the adjacent 
permanent lateral incisor. As the lateral incisor erupts, it prematurely 
resorbs the mesial surface of the primary canine, which causes it to be 
lost early. The unilateral loss of the primary canine then results in a 
shifting of the dental midline to the effected side.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/50.jpg" resourceWidth="322" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/50_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Early unilateral loss of a mandibular primary canine with a shift of the midline.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>(A) The normal eruption sequence in the maxillary arch makes serial extractions 
more challenging in the maxillary arch because (B) The eruption of a maxillary 
permanent tooth can be accelerated if the extraction of the overlying primary 
tooth is timed correctly.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. The first statement is false while the second statement is true. 
A major objective of serial extraction is to extract the first premolars 
before the permanent canines erupt. In the maxillary arch the first premolars 
usually erupt before the canines, which is favorable. The mandibular arch 
is more challenging because the canines often erupt before the first premolars. 
It's true that the eruption of a permanent tooth can be accelerated if the 
overlying primary tooth is extracted when this uncovers the underlying permanent 
tooth, so timely removal of first primary molars can accelerate the eruption 
of first premolars, allowing their extraction before canines erupt.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. The first statement is false while the second statement 
is true. A major objective of serial extraction is to extract the first 
premolars before the permanent canines erupt. In the maxillary arch the 
first premolars usually erupt before the canines, which is favorable. The 
mandibular arch is more challenging because the canines often erupt before 
the first premolars. It's true that the eruption of a permanent tooth can 
be accelerated if the overlying primary tooth is extracted when this uncovers 
the underlying permanent tooth, so timely removal of first primary molars 
can accelerate the eruption of first premolars, allowing their extraction 
before canines erupt.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/52.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="432" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/52_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="111" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Intraoral photos and panorex radiograph of a serial extraction candidate ready 
for extraction of the first premolars.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>Serial extractions are done to</p>

<p>
a. accelerate the eruption of the first premolars.<br/>
b. prevent loss of the leeway space.<br/>
c. eliminate the need for future orthodontic treatment.<br/>
d. allow early alignment of the permanent incisors.
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>a and c</choice><choice>a and d</choice><choice>a, c, and d</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. One of the objectives of serial extractions is the early resolution 
of permanent incisor crowding. The extraction of the primary canines creates 
space for the permanent incisors to erupt into normal positions and align 
early. Another objective is to accelerate the eruption of the first premolars, 
so they can be removed early. Serial extractions do not eliminate the need 
for future orthodontic treatment. First premolars are removed during serial 
extractions, and leeway space is not relevant since these teeth have been 
removed.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. One of the objectives of serial extractions is the early 
resolution of permanent incisor crowding. The extraction of the primary 
canines creates space for the permanent incisors to erupt into normal positions 
and align early. Another objective is to accelerate the eruption of the 
first premolars, so they can be removed early. Serial extractions do not 
eliminate the need for future orthodontic treatment. First premolars are 
removed during serial extractions, and leeway space is not relevant since 
these teeth have been removed.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="spacemgt/images/52.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="432" thumbnailLocation="spacemgt/images/52_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="111" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Intraoral photos and panorex radiograph of a serial extraction candidate ready 
for extraction of the first premolars.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>