<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<presentation><title>The Nature of Craniofacial Growth</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>- need info-<br/></additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/titlepage.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Introduction</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Intro, Learning Objectives</title><pageText><p>Before viewing this program, you should have looked at “The Study of Physical Growth”, the first module in the series. In this module, we will go into craniofacial growth in more detail. As with this and all the computer teaching programs, it's important to read the assigned material in <i>Contemporary Orthodontics</i> (5th edition, pages 33-40; 6th ed., 30-37;) as well as view the program, and then take the self-test at the end.</p>
<p>The general learning objectives for this module are to:</p>
<ul class="spaced">
<li>Distinguish the various types of growth in the skeletal system, and understand important related concepts</li>
<li>Describe the pattern of growth of the craniofacial skeleton in detail</li>
</ul>
<p>To meet these educational objectives, be sure that you are able to:</p>
<ul>
<li>describe the cellular processes involved in physical growth and the differences in soft tissue and hard tissue growth</li>
<li>describe the growth of the calvarium and cranial base in 3 planes of space, identifying the sites and mode of growth</li>
<li>similarly describe the growth of the maxilla, identifying the chief sites of growth, the role of surface remodeling and the effect of secondary displacement</li>
<li>describe the basic processes involved in growth of the mandible and the changes that occur in each area</li>
<li>describe the growth of the dental arches and identify the chief sites of growth.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Learning Objectives</title><pageText><p>The general learning objectives for this module are to:</p>
<ul class="spaced"><li>Distinguish the various types of growth in the skeletal system, and understand important related concepts </li>
<li>Describe the pattern of growth of the craniofacial skeleton in detail</li>
</ul><p>To meet these educational objectives, be sure that you are able to:</p>
<ul><li>describe the cellular processes involved in physical growth and the differences in soft tissue and hard tissue growth</li>
<li>describe the growth of the calvarium and cranial base in 3 planes of space, identifying the sites and mode of growth</li>
<li>similarly describe the growth of the maxilla, identifying the chief sites of growth, the role of surface remodeling and the effect of secondary displacement</li>
<li>describe the basic processes involved in growth of the mandible and the changes that occur in each area</li>
<li>describe the growth of the dental arches and identify the chief sites of growth.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Types of Skeletal Growth</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Bone Growth: Cellular Level</title><pageText><p>At the cellular level, there are only three possibilities for growth:</p>
<ul class="spaced">
<li>Hyperplasia - an increase in the number of cells</li>
<li>Hypertrophy - an increase in size of the cells</li>
<li>Secretion of extracellular material, which contributes to an increase in size independent of the number or size of the cells themselves.</li>
</ul>
<p>All three of these phenomena are important in craniofacial growth, including the production of extracellular material that later calcifies into bone. This creates an important distinction between soft tissue growth, in which interstitial growth (growth that occurs at all points within the tissue) is seen routinely, and hard tissue growth, in which interstitial growth is impossible after tissue mineralization occurs. From this perspective, uncalcified cartilage behaves like a soft tissue, with interstitial growth occurring, until it calcifies--and then behaves like a hard tissue.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Skeletal Growth: Soft Tissues vs. Hard Tissues</title><pageText><p>Growth of soft tissues occurs mostly by a combination of hyperplasia and hypertrophy. These processes go on within the tissues at all points, and the result is interstitial growth, which simply means growth inside the tissues. Secretion of extracellular material also can accompany interstitial growth, but hyperplasia primarily and hypertrophy secondarily are its characteristics. Hard tissues are bones, teeth, and sometimes cartilages. Soft tissues are everything else.</p>
<p>Because interstitial growth is impossible in hard tissues, hyperplasia, hypertrophy and secretion of extracellular material are possible only, but only on the surface. Interstitial growth still is an important part of overall skeletal because a major portion of the skeletal system is originally modeled in cartilage. This includes the base of the skull as well as the trunk and limbs. Direct addition of new bone to the surface can and does occur through the activity of cells in the periosteum that covers the surface: extracellular material created by the periosteal cells mineralizes after secretion. This process is called <i>﻿direct </i>﻿or <i>﻿surface apposition</i>﻿ of bone.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p02_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p02_01s.jpg"><label>Soft tissue growth</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Hard tissue growth</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Endochondral Ossification: Interstitial Growth</title><pageText><p>Interstitial growth is shown well in this view of a growing area at the top of the mandibular condyle. This is endochondral ossification, in which cartilage is doing the growing and then is replaced by bone (a process we will review in detail later in this program).</p>
<p>The cartilage is growing by all three of the methods we have described. Hyperplasia, formation of new cells, is occurring in the area below the fibrocartilage that covers the surface of the bone. Below that, note the enormous increase in the size of the maturing cartilage cells. This, of course, is hypertrophy. In addition, the cartilage cells are producing an extracellular material that lies between the cells and separates them. The hypertrophic changes are in preparation for the formation of new bone as it replaces the mature cartilage. Interstitial growth is a characteristic of uncalcified cartilage and other soft tissues.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="431" resourceHeight="448" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p03_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="77" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p03_01s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Endochondral ossification of the mandibular condyle.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Bone Growth: Growth of Hard Tissues</title><pageText><p>In contrast, when calcification takes place so that hard tissue is formed, interstitial growth in the calcified area becomes impossible. Significant growth occurs only at surfaces, not within the calcified mass. The interior of the calcified material can and does remodel, but it can’t grow larger because it’s too hard and rigid to expand internally.</p>
<p>Growth of hard tissue, therefore, occurs in two ways. The first is direct addition to the calcified tissue on its free surfaces. This occurs through the activity of cells in the periosteum, the soft tissue membrane covering the bone. Formation of new cells occurs in the periosteum, and extracellular material is secreted that then calcifies into bone. The second way is by replacement of soft tissue that grew before calcification occurred.</p>
<p>Many bones are modeled in cartilage originally, and the cartilage model is replaced by bone, thus the term “endochondral ossification.” In this situation, the cartilage does the growing while the bone merely replaces it. Cartilage can and does grow interstitally; bone can’t. It’s an attractive intuitive notion that bones expand more or less like a balloon being inflated. In fact, they can’t and don’t grow like that.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p04_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p04_01s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Endochondral ossification in the neuro-cranium</title><pageText><p>By 8 weeks in intrauterine life, a continuous thin plate of cartilage called the chondrocranium underlies the brain and extends from the nasal capsule to the foramen magnum (Fig. 1). During the third month, this cartilage grows rapidly (interstitial growth), keeping pace with the rapid growth of the brain.</p>
<p>By the beginning of the fourth month (Fig. 2), there is an ingrowth of blood vessels into multiple areas of the chondocranium, and these areas become centers of ossification in which cartilage is transformed into bone by <i>﻿endochondral ossification</i>﻿, and islands of bone develop in the sea of cartilage.</p>
<p>At the same time, <i>direct ossification, </i>in which there is formation of bone within an area of mesenchymal cells, begins. This occurs as some cells differentiate into osteoblasts rather than fibroblasts. These areas near the neurocranium are shown in lighter blue. They also develop above and around the brain. Both the cranium and the mandible are formed from direct ossification, not from endochondral ossification.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>A. Condocranium at 8 weeks in utero. (Fig 2-19A)</label><caption><p>This plate of cartilage has to be thin because cartilage is avascular and its interal cells depend on diffusion inward from the surface.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>B. Chondocranium at 12 weeks in utero (Fig 2-19B)</label><caption><p>By this time endochondral ossification has created an early version of the face, with cartilage remaining along the cranial base beneath the brain, and direct ossification of mesenchymal tissue also occurring in the cranium and future mandible.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth of Long Bones: Endochondral Ossification</title><pageText><p>Endochondral ossification of a typical long bone with a cartilaginous precursor begins with bone formation on the surface of the cartilage at about the same time bone formation begins in the neurocranium. This is followed by invasion of blood vessels that produce a hollowed-out center with bone formation in that area (A in the figure).</p>
<p>Ingrowth of blood vessels leads to an ossification center in the cartilaginous caps on either end (B), but a band of cartilage remains between what we can now call the diaphysis (the central part) and epiphyses. These cartilage bands are the epiphyseal plates.</p>
<p>The bone grows longer as the cartilage of the epiphyseal plates grows, matures, and is replaced by bone (C). Eventually, the rate of replacement of the cartilage with bone exceeds the rate of cartilage growth, all the cartilage is replaced—and the bone then is as long as it can get (D).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="284" resourceHeight="265" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_05nr.jpg" thumbnailWidth="86" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_05nr_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Endochondral ossification of a long bone.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Bone Growth: Endochondral Ossification (cont.)</title><pageText><p>A histologic view of endochondral ossification at an epiphyseal plate shows the areas of proliferating and maturing cartilage, then replacement of degenerating mature cartilage by spicules of bone.</p>
<p>It is important to keep in mind that in addition to the endochondral replacement, periosteum is actively forming bone on the outer surfaces. The bone grows longer by endochondral ossification. It grows wider by direct formation of new bone on the surface.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="476" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-19a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="85" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-19a_s.jpg"><label>Endochondral at an epiphyseal plate</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Bone Growth: Endochondral vs. Surface Ossification</title><pageText><p>The combination of surface apposition of bone and endochondral replacement can be 
seen in this drawing of a growing bone. Periosteal bone formation on the surface is 
different from the endochondral bone formation occurring beneath it.</p>

<p>For endochondral bone formation, a complex maturational pattern of the cartilage 
is required. In direct bone formation by the periosteum, osteoblasts secrete their 
matrix directly in connective tissue, and it calcifies there without any 
intermediate formation of cartilage.</p>

<p>The details of this process are a review of what you learned in histology and will 
not be emphasized further here, but you must understand it.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="386" resourceHeight="256" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_07nr.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_07nr_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Bone Growth: Endochondral vs. Surface Ossification (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Growth at an epiphyseal plate requires corresponding changes in the surface of the bone. Not all the surface changes can be met by adding new bone. Because the contour of the long bones calls for a knob on the end, a continuous remodeling of the surface is required as endochondral growth occurs, meaning that bone must be added to the surface in some areas and removed in others.</p>
<p>The periosteum, therefore, must and does contain cells whose purpose is to remove bone as well as cells to make it, and there is a balance between apposition of bone in some areas and resorption in others. Addition of bone in some areas while old bone is removed in others is an essential component of the growth process.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="341" resourceHeight="223" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_08nr.jpg" thumbnailWidth="122" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_08nr_s.jpg"><label>Remodeling around an epiphyseal plate</label><caption><p>Surface remodeling of bone requires resorption (green areas) as well as deposition (yellow areas).</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Bone Growth: Internal Remodeling</title><pageText><p>We have said that growth within a calcified mass is impossible, but that doesn’t mean that metabolic change is impossible. In fact, osteocytes embedded in the bone are alive, and quite capable of producing internal remodeling of the bone. Calcified tissue in bones is turned over through a constant process of remodeling.</p>
<p>In this vital-stained section, you can see the live osteocyte with its processes extending out into the calcified bone around it. This makes it obvious how activity by a cell like this can affect calcified tissue at a distance from the cell body of the osteocyte.</p>
<p>Remodeling of the internal structure of bone has two major functions: it serves as a means of adapting the bone to mechanical stresses, and it also makes calcium and phosphate ions available for exchange with blood. Exchange of calcium and phosphate occurs near periosteal surfaces and around Haversian systems.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/scrn15.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/scrn15_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Vital-stained osteocyte, showing its processes that extend into the bone. Osteocyle activity is the basis for internal remodeling of bone.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Bone Growth: Internal Remodeling (cont.)</title><pageText><p>In this decalcifed section from a bone, the larger holes are where a blood vessel was, the smaller lacunae are where the cells were. Osteocytes cluster around vascular channels, as you can see. Ingrowth of blood vessels into an area of cartilage or connective tissue is essential for ossification. It also is essential for maintenance of the calcified tissue.</p>
<p>A complex like the one shown here, with osteocytes surrounding a blood vessel, is called a Haversian system, and it’s constantly remodeled during life. This internal remodeling, however, does not significantly contribute to growth or change the shape of the bone. The bone can’t get bigger through internal remodeling.</p>
<p>In this section of bone, you can see remnants of an old Haversian system (dotted yellow lines) being replaced by smaller new ones (HC) as the bone remodels. Bone is a dynamic tissue, constantly being rebuilt. It’s a mistake to think of it as just an inert scaffold on which the other tissues are suspended.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="296" resourceHeight="366" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p10_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="65" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p10_01s.jpg"><label>Remodeling of Haversian systems</label><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Cranial and Maxillary Skeletal Growth</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Regions of the Cranium and Face</title><pageText><p>With the general principles of bone growth established, let’s look in more detail at growth of the cranium and face. For this discussion, it will be convenient to divide the cranium and face into two areas each:</p>
<p>For the cranium (labeled 1 in this image):<br/> The <b><i>cranial vault</i></b> and <b><i>cranial base</i></b>.</p>
<p>For the face: The <b><i>naso-maxillary complex</i></b> (2) and<br/> the <b><i>mandible </i></b>(3).</p>
<p>The special features of growth of the dentoalveolar processes (4, 5) and eruption of the teeth will be considered later.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="417" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/6-41.jpg" thumbnailWidth="74" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/6-41_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Skeletal Growth: Cranial Vault</title><pageText><p>Let’s begin by examining the cranial vault. It is made up of a number of flat bones that are formed directly by periosteum. As Fig. 1 shows, ossification of the bone plates that are forming around the brain is not as advanced as in the areas of endochondral ossification. Endochondral bone formation has no role in cranial vault formation, and there’s never any cartilage in the vicinity. Instead, growth occurs entirely by periosteal activity at the surfaces of the bones, both at the flat inner and outer surfaces and the periosteum-lined spaces between them.</p>
<p>At birth, the bones are rather widely separated by connective tissues (Fig. 2), and these open spaces are called fontanelles. The presence of the fontanelles allows considerable deformation at birth, which is important in getting the relatively large head through the birth canal.</p>
<p>Apposition of bone along the edges of the fontanelles eliminates these open spaces fairly quickly after birth, but the bones remain separated by remnants of the fontanelles in the form of thin periosteum-lined sutures for years.</p>
<p>Despite their small size, apposition of bone at the sutures is the major mechanism for growth of the cranial vault. In addition, there is a tendency for bone to be removed from the inner surface of each bone and added to the outer surface, especially in some areas where contours change. The magnitude of these changes, however, is much less than the growth at sutures.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig 1. Head and face ossification at 3 months in utero (Fig 2-21)</label><caption><p>Note the early, almost porous, ossification of the cranial bone plates, compared to the much more solid ossification of the areas in the face.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="363" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-23.jpg" thumbnailWidth="132" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-23_s.jpg"><label>B, Fontanelles of the newborn skull</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Skeletal Growth: Cranial Base</title><pageText><p>You have seen previously how the initial stage of ossification in the head is the plate of cartilage beneath the brain. As growth continues, this cartilage is reduced in size as endochondral ossification occurs, but islands of the cartilage are still present at birth between the bony units that have formed there, and endochondral ossification continues as the brain grows above them. These units of cartilage, called synchondroses because of their location between bones, are important growth sites.</p>
<p>Although lengthening of the cranial base definitely has a component of endochondral growth at the synchondroses, as one moves laterally beneath the brain, growth at the sutures that connect the cranial base to the facial skeleton also is necessary.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="399" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-24_s.jpg"><label>Synchondroses of the cranial base</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Synchondrosis vs. Suture</title><pageText><p>Be sure you understand the difference between a suture and a synchondrosis. Both are thin soft tissue areas between adjacent bones, but the synchondrosis is filled with cartilage. A band of proliferating cartilage cells is located in the center of the synchondrosis, and a band of maturing cartilage extends in both directions away from the center. Endochondral ossification occurs at both margins.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="329" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-25ab.jpg" thumbnailWidth="146" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-25ab_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>A: distant view of the spheno-occipital synchondrosis, where growth pushes the sphenoid bone away from the occipital bone. B: close-up view of a synchondrosis, showing the proliferating cartilage in the center.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Synchondrosis vs. Suture (cont.)</title><pageText><p>In contrast, a suture has only periosteum and connective tissue. At the synchondrosis, bone formation proceeds by cartilage replacement, while for sutures, there is no intermediate cartilage stage.</p>
<p>As you will see when we review growth control, the difference is significant: the cartilage at synchondroses is capable of active, independent growth while the connective tissue at sutures only reacts to what happens in its surroundings.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s03_p06_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s03_p06_01s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Skeletal Growth: Maxilla</title><pageText><p>Now let’s consider the maxilla and the associated smaller nasal and palatine bones. Postnatally, the face grows downward and forward from the cranium, and the maxilla must move a considerable distance. How this occurs, and what changes accompany the growth, are what we must focus on now. In the case of the maxilla, there is no pre-existing cartilage, so maxillary growth is a matter of sutures and surface changes. </p>
<p>As Fig. 1 shows, the naso-maxillary complex is pushed forward by foward growth of the cranial base behind it. How long would this mechanism of growth be effective? Only as long as the cranial base is growing--and that ends at about the time brain growth ends, at about age 6.</p>
<p>After that (Fig. 2), growth of the maxilla occurs at the sutures, where bone formation occurs in response to tension across them as the surrounding soft tissues slowly pulls the maxilla downward and forward.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="378" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-7.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-7_s.jpg"><label>Forward push of the maxilla</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Downward-forward pull of the maxilla  (Fig. 2-27)</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Skeletal Growth: Maxilla (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Let’s look in more detail at the right half of the maxilla in this figure. You can see that it forms the floor of the orbit, the lateral wall of the nose, the roof of the mouth and the lateral aspects of the facial skeleton. Note the network of sutures posteriorly along the maxillary tuberosity, superiorly at the end of the frontal process, and superiorly-laterally along the zygomatic process.</p>
<p>There’s also a suture in the midline down the middle of the palate, providing a mechanism for the midface and upper dental arch to become wider. Growth occurs by apposition at the sutures and by modeling or remodeling of the surfaces.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="404" resourceHeight="349" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_10nr.jpg" thumbnailWidth="93" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_10nr_s.jpg"><label>Right half of the maxilla</label><caption><p>Note the location of sutures above and behind the maxilla.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth at Sutures and Surfaces of the Maxilla</title><pageText><p>It is apparent that the posterior and superior sutures of the maxilla are ideally situated to allow downward and forward repositioning. As the maxilla moves in that direction, new bone is added at the sutures to maintain its connection to the cranium.</p>
<p>The space that would otherwise open up at the sutures is filled in by proliferation of bone, so the sutures remain the same width but the various processes of the maxilla become longer. As the drawing illustrates, this requires moving the maxilla away from the structures above and behind it.</p>
<p>Part of the posterior border of the maxilla, in the tuberosity area, is a free surface. Bone is added to this area, creating additional space into which the molar teeth can erupt.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="543" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-26.jpg" thumbnailWidth="97" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-26_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Apposition of bone at the sutures surrounding the maxilla as it grows down and forward.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Surface Resorption in Growth of Maxilla</title><pageText><p>As the maxilla grows down and forward, its front surfaces are remodeled, and bone is actually removed from most of the anterior surface.</p>
<p>In this three-quarter view (Fig.1), areas of resorption are more darkly shaded. Note that almost the whole anterior surface is a resorptive area–which seems backward to what you might think it should be. If you look at it in profile (Fig. 2), there's a little apposition at the anterior nasal spine and just below it, but all the other surfaces are resorptive.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="493" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-27.jpg" thumbnailWidth="88" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-27_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Resorptive areas on the front surface of the maxilla (shaded).</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="365" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-8.jpg" thumbnailWidth="65" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-8_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Areas of surface bone apposition (+) and resorption (-) during growth of the maxilla.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Translation and Remodeling</title><pageText><p>What takes place as the maxilla grows down and forward is represented by this cartoon. The whole bone is moving downward and forward relative to the cranium, being translated in space. This is exemplified in the cartoon by the platform on wheels.</p>
<p>At the same time, the front surface, represented in the cartoon by the wall, is being reduced on its anterior side and built up posteriorly, so that it moves in space opposite to the direction of overall growth.</p>
<p>How do we know this modeling (apposition behind) and remodeling (resorption on the front) occurs? Vital staining shows this quite nicely, as you saw with the zygomatic arch in Module 1. How do we know that translation occurs? Superimposed tracings of cephalometric x-rays are a good way to show that.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="324" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-28.jpg" thumbnailWidth="148" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-28_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Translation and Remodeling (cont.)</title><pageText><p>It’s not always true that surface remodeling opposes the direction of translation of the maxilla. Depending on location, translation may be augmented by addition to bone. Look in more detail at what happens to surfaces in the palatal area during growth.</p>
<p>The maxilla is being translated downward and forward. At the same time the floor of the nose is resorbing and bone is being added to the roof of the mouth, and this adds to the downward movement of the palate. But it's not totally that way: note that the front surface below the anterior nasal spine is resorbing, so the surface change there opposes the direction of translation.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="537" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-29c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="95" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-29c_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Translation and Remodeling: An Overall View</title><pageText><p>In this overall view of the movement of the dental portions of the maxilla during growth (using cephalometric tracings superimposed on the cranial base), you can see that the maxilla seems to be moving as much downward as forward, and the maxillary teeth have erupted downward relative to the skeletal bone above them.</p>
<p>It looks like that in part because the direction of surface remodeling opposes forward translation of the maxilla but adds to the downward component.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="313" resourceHeight="445" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s03_p13_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s03_p13_01s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Cephalometric superimposition on the cranial base shows the normal downward-forward growth direction of the maxilla, which isn't as simple as it appears because resorption on the anterior surfaces of the maxilla keeps the maxilla from moving forward while downward growth is fully expressed.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary: Overall Pattern of Maxillary Growth</title><pageText><p>The overall pattern of maxillary growth as seem in cephalometric superimposition on the cranial base can be summarized as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>As the bone moves downward and forward, new bone is added at the sutures and the tuberosity.</li>
<li>Anterior surfaces resorb, while the roof of the mouth moves further down by remodeling.</li>
<li>The remodeling of the roof of the mouth means, among other things, that you can’t judge how much a tooth has erupted by measuring how far it is from the height of the palatal vault.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you understand that, you have grasped the concept of remodeling in relation to maxillary growth. If you don’t, go back and review this section and make some drawings.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="337" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-9a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="60" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-9a_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Cranial base superimposition, normal growth pattern.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Mandibular and Dentoalveolar Skeletal Growth</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Skeletal Growth: Mandible</title><pageText><p>Growth of the mandible is different in many ways from growth of the maxilla. The difference begins with its relationship to the chondrocranium. The mandible has a cartilage model, of sorts (Meckel's cartilage, a cartilaginous bar in the mandibular arch whose proximal ends eventually ossify to form the malleus of the middle ear). But the mandible develops more in association with that cartilage than by replacing it.</p>
<p>Bone formation begins just lateral to Meckel’s cartilage and spreads posteriorly along it without any direct replacement of the cartilage by the newly forming bone.The two halves fuse very early, so for all practical purposes, a growing mandible, even in fetal life, is a single bone extending across the midline.</p>
<p>In contrast, the maxilla has a midline suture that makes it possible to expand it transversely in a way that the mandible cannot.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="263" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-21.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="73" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-21_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Mandibular bone forming in relation to Meckel’s cartilage but not replacing it.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Origin and Growth of the Condylar Cartilage</title><pageText><p>There is some cartilage that covers the surface of the condyle at the temporomandibular (TM) joint, but it appears relatively late in embryonic life and is not derived from Meckel’s cartilage. It begins formation separately from the body of the mandible and fuses with the bone at about 4 months in utero, as shown in the figure.</p>
<p>This cartilage is not like the cartilage at an epiphyseal plate or synchondrosis, but hyperplasia, hypertrophy, and endochondral replacement do occur there in late fetal and post-natal growth. All other areas of the mandible are formed and grow by direct surface apposition and remodeling.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="213" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-22.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="59" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-22_s.jpg"><label>The developing bony and cartilaginous components of the mandible</label><caption><p>The cartilage that will eventually cover the head of the mandibular condyle forms separately from the mandible (A) and fuses with the mandibular body around 4 months in utero (B). The remnants of this cartilage end up on the top of the condylar process (C).</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Pattern of Mandibular Growth</title><pageText><p>The overall pattern of growth of the mandible can be represented in two ways. Depending on your frame of reference, both are correct.</p>
<p>If you hold the cranium constant and look at mandibular growth relative to it (A), the chin moves downward and forward a long way relative to the cranium, so you might think that new bone was added anteriorly. But, if you look specifically at the sites of growth on the bone as revealed by vital staining and similar techniques, very little change occurs at the chin and most of the growth is posteriorly (B). Superimposing on the chin correctly shows that the body of the mandible grows longer by apposition of bone on the posterior surface, and the ramus grows higher by endochondral replacement at the condyle and by surface remodeling.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="176" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-30ab.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="49" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-30ab_s.jpg"><label>The pattern of mandibular growth from two viewpoints</label><caption><p>The mandible appears to grown downward and forward, away from the cranial base (A). In reality, bone is added to the posterior border of the mandible and vertically to the ramus at the condyle (B).</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Pattern of Mandibular Growth (cont.)</title><pageText><p>From cephalometric tracings superimposed on the cranial base, the overall growth pattern of the mandible looks like this: the bone moves downward and forward, taking the teeth with it (Fig. 1).</p>
<p>The position of the TM joint can change because of changes in the posterior cranial base, but usually it remains about in the same place on the skull.</p>
<p>If the x-ray tracings are superimposed at the chin so that the anterior mandible is held constant, then it appears that the mandible grows upward and backward (Fig. 2). In fact, this is where new bone is added, by a combination of endochondral replacement at the head of the condyle and surface apposition.</p>
<p>Can you visualize the correctness of the statement that the mandible grows upward and backward, but the effect of this growth is a downward and forward translation of the chin? If that’s clear, you understand an important concept.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="337" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-9a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="60" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-9a_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 1, superimposition of a growing patient, registered on the cranial base</label><caption><p>Superimposed on the cranial base, the maxilla, mandible, and teeth all appear to have moved downward and forward with growth. </p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="176" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-30ab.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="49" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-30ab_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 2, superimposition registered on the cranial base (left) compared to superimposition on the chin</label><caption><p>Superimposition on the chin shows the correct pattern of mandibular growth: growth is upward and backward at the condyle and ramus.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Backward Drift of the Ramus</title><pageText><p>Nowhere is there a better example of drift of bone in response to forces on it than in the backward movement of the ramus of the mandible. During growth, new bone is added on the posterior surface of the ramus. At the same time, bone is removed—large quantities of bone—from the anterior surface of the ramus. Bone from the tip of the condylar process early in life can be found at the anterior surface of the ramus some years later. The body of the mandible grows longer as the ramus moves away from the chin.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="311" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-31.jpg" thumbnailWidth="55" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-31_s.jpg"><label>Backward drift of the mandibular ramus</label><caption><p>Bone is removed (-) from the anterior surface of the ramus and added (+) to the posterior surface.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth by Drift of the Ramus</title><pageText><p>How is this possible? Remember the previous cartoon: this movement occurs the same way as a wall could be moved by removing stones from the front side and adding them to the back.</p>
<p>Looking at mandibles at different ages, you might think there had to be a growth center somewhere under the teeth, so the chin could grow forward away from the ramus. But that is not possible, since interstitial bone growth is impossible. Instead, the ramus remodels. What was the posterior surface at one time becomes the center at a later date, and eventually may become the anterior surface and then disappear.</p>
<p>Removing bone from the posterior surface of the ramus also makes space available for the molar teeth to erupt. In infancy the ramus is located about where the first primary molar will erupt. Progressive modeling and remodeling create space for the second primary molar and then for the permanent first and second molars. It often doesn't go far enough to make room for the third molar, which ends up impacted below the ramus.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="311" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-31.jpg" thumbnailWidth="55" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-31_s.jpg"><label>Remodeling resorption of the mandible</label><caption><p>Remodeling of the ramus allows growth to occur by addition of bone at the posterior surface despite the fact that the chin appears to grow forward.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth by Modeling and Remodeling of the Mandible (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Looking down on top of the mandible, the effect of these surface changes can be seen clearly. This is the type of superimposition that metallic implants make possible. Note that surface modeling also has made the bone wider.</p>
<p>There’s no midline suture like the one for the maxilla, so the ramus also is widened by surface modeling. The old condyles are totally resorbed after a while, as the ramus widens by removing bone from the inside and adding it outside.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="461" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/scrn39a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="82" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/scrn39a_s.jpg"><label>Axial view of remodeling of the mandible</label><caption><p>Surface resorption and apposition also allow for the mandible to increase in width.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary: Growth of the Mandible</title><pageText><p>Mandibular growth can be summarized like this:</p>
<ul class="spaced">
<li>a large amount of bone is added on the posterior and superior surfaces of the ramus</li>
<li>nearly as much bone is removed from the anterior surface of the ramus</li>
<li>there are smaller changes in surfaces elsewhere</li>
<li>bone is added to some outer surfaces and removed from some inner surfaces, especially in the extensive modeling and remodeling of the ramus.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Skeletal Growth: Alveolar Processes of Maxilla and Mandible</title><pageText><p>In talking about craniofacial bone growth, we have made little mention of the alveolar processes of the maxilla and mandible.  In both jaws, growth of the bone that supports the teeth is an important aspect of the overall growth process.</p>
<p>One way to think about it is that the mandible grows downward away from the maxilla, creating more space between the jaws. As the jaws grow, the teeth are actively erupting (they have to in order to maintain contact), and as they erupt they bring alveolar bone with them, so that the alveolar processes become taller. Note in this cranial base superimposition of normal growth (the same one you've seen previously) how the teeth erupted to compensate for greater downward movement of the mandible than the maxilla. If new alveolar bone didn’t form, the teeth would just grow right out of the bone. We’ll be looking more at what happens to the teeth during growth in the later part of this course.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="337" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-9a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="60" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-9a_s.jpg"><label>Superimposition of a normally growing patient, registered on the cranial base</label><caption><p>As the maxilla and mandible move downward in relation to the cranial base, the teeth erupt and bring alveolar bone with them.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Facial Soft Tissue Growth</title><pageText><p>Dentists used to just focus on the teeth; now they focus on how the teeth fit into the face and try to optimize their appearance--which means that how the facial soft tissues grow is now an important topic.</p>
<p>For now, there is one major message with two important examples. The major message: the growth of the facial soft tissues does not perfectly parallel the growth of the hard tissues and eruption of the teeth. The two important examples:</p>
<p>1) the lips trail behind the growth of the jaws until adolescence, then undergo a growth spurt to catch up, and move downward across the teeth with increasing aging. This means that separation of the lips at rest (<i>lip incompetence)</i> is maximal during childhood and decreases during adolescence. Young people display their upper teeth both at rest and during smile; older people have increasing display of their lower teeth and less of their upper teeth.</p>
<p>2) Growth of the nasal bone is complete at about age 10. Growth thereafter is only of the soft tissue (including the nasal cartilage), which undergo a marked adolescent growth spurt, especially in males, in whom the nose keeps growing even late in life.</p>
<p>You will be hearing a lot more about that as we get into orthodontic treatment planning.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary</title><pageText><p>To summarize the important points:</p>
<p>First, you certainly should understand that bone cannot grow interstitially, and the growth of the facial skeleton cannot be explained in that way. Where interstitial growth is important for the skeleton, a layer of cartilage in that area does the growing, and then bone replaces it.</p>
<p>Second, with regard to the sites and types of growth in the cranium and cranial base:</p>
<ul class="spaced">
<li>Growth of the cranium occurs largely at the sutures, with a little surface remodeling;</li>
<li>The cranial base grows largely by endochondral replacement at the mid-line synchondroses, but also by apposition at sutures laterally;</li>
</ul>
<p>Additionally, with regard to the sites and types of growth in the jaws and face:</p>
<ul class="spaced">
<li>Growth of the maxilla and associated structures is a combination of growth at sutures and surface remodeling. As the maxilla is translated downward and forward during growth, bone fills in at the superior and posterior sutures and is added at the tuberosity;</li>
<li>The mandible grows largely by apposition of bone on the back of the ramus and resorption on the front, and by endochondral replacement at the condyles;</li>
<li>The alveolar processes of both jaws grow as the teeth erupt, bringing bone with them.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Self-Test Referral</title><pageText><p>Now take the self-test in the following section of this module to ensure that you understand what you have learned.  Before you do, be sure you have read  the assigned material in <i>Contemporary Orthodontics</i> (5th edition: pages 33-40; 6th edition: pages 30-37).</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>In growth of the craniofacial skeleton, which of the following cellular activities is most important?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>Hyperplasia</choice><choice>Hypertrophy</choice><choice>Secretion of extracellular material</choice><choice>All are equally important</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct. Although all the cellular processes are important, secretion of 
extracullar material is particularly important in growth of the skeletal system, in 
which the extracellular material later calcifies into bone. Cartilage cells mature and 
secrete extracellular matrix that becomes calcified; osteoblasts also later form new 
bone by secreting extracellular matrix that calcifies.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. Although all the cellular processes are vital for growth, 
secretion of extracellular material is particularly important in growth of the skeletal 
system, in which the extracellular material later calcifies into bone. Cartilage cells 
mature and secrete extracellular matrix that becomes calcified; osteoblasts also later 
form new bone by secreting extracellular matrix that calcifies.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="269" resourceHeight="229" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/scrn45a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="94" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/scrn45a_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>In growth of the cranial and facial soft tissues, which of the following cellular 
activities is the least important?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>Hyperplasia</choice><choice>Hypertrophy</choice><choice>Secretion of extracellular material</choice><choice>All are equally important</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right. Secretion of extracellular material can occur as soft tissues are 
formed, but this is not an important characteristic of growth of the craniofacial soft tissues.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. Secretion of extracellular material can occur as soft tissues are 
formed, but is not an important characteristic of growth of the craniofacial soft 
tissues. Hyperplasia primarily and hypertrophy secondarily are the major characteristics 
of soft tissue growth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p02_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/s02_p02_01s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>(A) Interstitial growth does not occur in the growth of calcified tissues because 
(B) the rigid calcified tissue mass cannot expand internally.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A True, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right. Calcified tissues don’t grow by interstitial growth that leads 
to external expansion, because it’s physically impossible. So these statements 
are both true and they're related.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, you’re wrong. Both statements are true and related. Calcified tissues don’t 
grow by interstitial growth that leads to external expansion, because it’s 
physically impossible.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>Which of the following statements best describes the growth of a long bone of the limbs?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>The bone is formed in cartilage and replaced by endochondral ossification</choice><choice>Cartilage does all the growing, then is replaced by bone</choice><choice>A little cartilage is present originally, but most of the growth is bone apposition</choice><choice>Both replacement of cartilage and direct apposition of bone are major contributors to the growth</choice><choice>None of the above, there’s no role for cartilage except in facial growth</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right. Replacement of cartilage that grows at the epiphyseal plates is very 
important, but so is direct apposition of bone at the periosteum.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The correct answer is (4). Both replacement of cartilage 
and direct apposition of bone are major contributors to the growth. Replacement 
of cartilage that grows at the epiphyseal plates is very important, but 
so is direct apposition of bone at the periosteum. As important as the cartilage 
growth is, you mustn’t overlook the equal importance of the apposition 
(and remodeling) at the periosteal surface.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="255" resourceHeight="228" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/scrn51.jpg" thumbnailWidth="89" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/scrn51_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>(A) Significant interstitial remodeling of long bones occurs around Haversian 
systems because (B) the final increments of bone growth are obtained in 
this manner.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>A true, B true, A And B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct. It’s true that long bones remodel internally around their 
Haversian systems, but this has almost nothing to do with growth, so the first statement 
is true but the second is false.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. It’s true that long bones remodel internally around 
their Haversian systems, but this has almost nothing to do with growth, so the first 
statement is true and the second statement is false.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>(A) Formation of bone always requires the intermediate step of cartilage formation because 
(B) osteoblasts must secrete their matrix on a framework of calcified cartilage.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>A true, B true, A And B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct, both statements are false. Bone can be (and often is) formed without an 
intermediate cartilage step, because osteoclasts can secrete their matrix directly in 
connective tissue.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s incorrect, both statements are false. Bone can be (and often is) formed without 
an intermediate cartilage stop, because osteoclasts can secrete their matrix directly in 
connective tissue.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="386" resourceHeight="256" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_07nr.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_07nr_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>Growth of the cranial vault involves which of the following processes?<br/><br/>
(1) endochondral ossification at multiple growth centers<br/>
(2) apposition of new bone at sutures <br/>
(3) apposition of new bone on external surfaces<br/>
(4) apposition of new bone on internal surfaces</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>1 and 2</choice><choice>2 and 3</choice><choice>2, 4 and 4</choice><choice>All of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the cranial vault grows primarily by apposition of new bone at the 
sutures, and to a smaller extent by adding new bone on the outer surfaces, so the second 
and third statements are correct. There aren’t any growth centers in the cranium 
and no endochondral ossification, and bone is removed rather than added on the internal 
surfaces, so the first and last statements are incorrect.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The cranial vault grows primarily by apposition of new bone 
at the sutures, and to a smaller extent by adding new bone on the outer surfaces, so the 
second and third statements are correct. There aren’t any growth centers in the 
cranium and no endochondral ossification, and bone is removed rather than added on the 
internal surfaces, so the first and last statements are incorrect.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="363" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-23.jpg" thumbnailWidth="132" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-23_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>Which of the following types of growth is most important in the cranial base?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>endochondral ossification at multiple growth centers</choice><choice>apposition of new bone along suture lines</choice><choice>apposition of new bone on external surfaces</choice><choice>removal of bone from internal surfaces</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, all of these processes are involved to some extent in growth of the 
cranial base—but cartilage growth and endochondral replacement of bone at the midline 
synchondroses are particularly important in lengthening the cranial base and projecting 
the midface forward.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. All of these processes are involved to some extent in growth of 
the cranial base–but cartilage growth and endochondral replacement of bone at the 
midline synchondroses are particularly important in lengthening the cranial base.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="399" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-24_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>Growth of the maxilla involves which of the following processes?<br/><br/>
(1) endochondral ossification at multiple growth centers <br/>
(2) apposition of new bone along suture lines <br/>
(3) apposition of new bone on external surfaces <br/>
(4) removal of bone from external or internal surfaces</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>1 and 2</choice><choice>2 and 3</choice><choice>3 and 4</choice><choice>2, 3 and 4</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, there’s no direct endochondral ossification and no cartilaginous 
growth centers in maxillary growth, and both growth at sutures and surface remodeling are 
important. Compared to the cranium, the maxilla has less sutural growth and more remodeling 
partly because it’s pushed forward by growth of the cranial base behind it and 
remodeling occurs in response to that.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. There’s no direct endochondral ossification and no 
cartilaginous growth centers in maxillary growth, so the first statement is incorrect. 
Both growth at sutures and surface remodeling (in the form of internal and external 
apposition and resorption) are important, so the other three statements are correct. 
Compared to the cranium, the maxilla has less sutural growth and more remodeling, 
partly because it’s pushed forward by growth of the cranial base behind it and 
remodeling occurs in response to that.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="378" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-7.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-7_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>What is the major area for addition of new bone to the surface of the 
maxilla during growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>tuberosity</choice><choice>upper anterior surface</choice><choice>lower anterior surface</choice><choice>paranasal areas</choice><choice>all of the above, bone is added to all surfaces about equally</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the main area of the maxilla where bone is added during growth is the 
tuberosity. Formation of new bone here allows the dental arch to become longer during growth 
and provides space of the molar teeth as they erupt. Most of the anterior surfaces, in contrast, 
are resorbed rather than added to during growth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The main area of the maxilla where bone is added during growth is 
the tuberosity. Formation of new bone here allows the dental arch to become longer during growth 
and provides space of the molar teeth as they erupt. Most of the anterior surfaces, in contrast, 
are resorbed rather than added to during growth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="404" resourceHeight="349" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_10nr.jpg" thumbnailWidth="93" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/jmemod2_10nr_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 11</title><pageText><p>Which of the following mechanisms move the roof of the mouth downward during growth?<br/><br/>
(1) endochondral ossification at the back of the maxilla <br/>
(2) displacement of the maxillary core from the cranium and cranial base <br/>
(3) apposition of bone on the inferior surface of the palatal bone<br/>
(4) resorption of bone on the nasal surface of the palatal bone</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>1 only</choice><choice>2 only</choice><choice>2 and 3</choice><choice>2, 3 and 4</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right. No endochondral ossification is involved in downward movement of the roof of 
the mouth, but displacement of the core of the maxilla and remodeling of the bony surfaces are 
important. In some instances, with the roof of the mouth being an excellent example, the direction 
of remodeling is the same as the direction of displacement.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. No endochondral ossification is involved in downward movement of the roof 
of the mouth, but displacement of the core of the maxilla and remodeling of the bony surfaces are 
important. The first statement is incorrect, the other three are correct. In some instances, with 
the roof of the mouth being an excellent example, the direction of remodeling is the same as 
the direction of displacement.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="537" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-29c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="95" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-29c_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 12</title><pageText><p>(A) Most aspects of mandibular growth can be explained by endochondral ossification 
because (B) a cartilaginous model of the mandible forms early in embryonic life and 
then resorbs.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct. The first statement (A) is false, but the second statement 
(B) is true. Mandibular growth is mostly a surface phenomenon, and endochondral 
ossification at the condyle plays a smaller role, so the first statement is false. 
It’s true that a cartilaginous model of the mandible forms early in life and 
then resorbs, although the new, primarily membranous mandible forms alongside 
it without really replacing it in the classic form of endochondral bone growth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. Mandibular growth is mostly a surface phenomenon, and 
endochondral ossification at the condyle plays a smaller role, so the first statement 
is false. It’s true that a cartilaginous model of the mandible forms early 
in life and then resorbs, so the second statement is true, although the cartilage 
resorbs and the new, primarily membranous mandible forms alongside it without really
 replacing it in the classic form of endochondral bone growth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="263" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-21.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="73" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-21_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 13</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is the best illustration of remodeling resorption?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>backward movement of the mandibular ramus</choice><choice>forward movement of the chin</choice><choice>lateral movement of the mandibular alveolar process</choice><choice>backward movement of the maxillary tuberosity</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct. The ramus moves backward as bone is removed from its front surface 
and added to the back. There’s so much remodeling that in a young child, what at one 
time was the back surface eventually becomes the front surface and then is resorbed away.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. The best illustration of remodeling resorption in the face by 
far is the backward movement of the mandibular ramus. It moves backward as bone is removed 
from its front surface and added to the back. There’s so much remodeling that in a 
young child, what at one time was the back surface eventually becomes the front surface and 
then is resorbed away. There’s a little remodeling at the chin and the alveolar
 process, next to none at the tubererosity.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="311" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-31.jpg" thumbnailWidth="55" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-31_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 14</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is not an area of significant bone apposition during mandibular growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>posterior border of ramus</choice><choice>superior border of ramus</choice><choice>alveolar process</choice><choice>chin</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right. Little or no bone is added at the chin during mandibular growth, and 
the area immediately above the chin prominence usually is resorptive. In contrast, there 
is major apposition of bone in the other areas.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. Little or no bone is added at the chin during mandibular 
growth, and the area immediately above the chin prominence usually is resorptive. Bone is 
added all along the posterior and superior (but not the anterior) surfaces of the ramus and 
at the alveolar process. The correct answer is (4) chin.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="311" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-31.jpg" thumbnailWidth="55" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-31_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 15</title><pageText><p>After it first comes into occlusal contact with its antagonists at about age 6, 
how much further does a typical permanent first molar erupt?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>stops after coming into occlusion</choice><choice>1-2 mm</choice><choice>3-5 mm</choice><choice>10 mm or more</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct, after it comes into occlusion a typical first molar has to erupt 
a centimeter or more. The mandible grows away from the maxilla, creating a space into 
which the teeth have to erupt to stay in occlusion, and there’s a lot of vertical 
growth after age 6.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. After it comes into occlusion a typical first molar has to erupt 
a centimeter or more. The mandible grows away from the maxilla, creating a space into which 
the teeth have to erupt to stay in occlusion, and there’s a lot of vertical growth 
after age 6. If the teeth don’t erupt, an open bite develops.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="337" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-9a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="60" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/4-9a_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 16</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is a site of interstitial growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>synchondrosis of cranial base</choice><choice>roof of the mouth</choice><choice>ramus of the mandible</choice><choice>maxillary tuberosity</choice><choice>none of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the synchondrosis contains cartilage that can and does grow interstitially, but 
the other bony areas can’t grow interstitially.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. The synchrondoses of the cranial base contain cartilage that 
can and does grow interstitially, but the other bony areas can’t do that.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="399" resourceLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-24.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="naturecfgrowth/images/2-24_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>
