<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<presentation><title>Biology of Orthodontic Treatment</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>William R. Proffit<br/>Dept. of Orthodontics, UNC School of Dentistry</additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="biologyorthotx/images/titlepage.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Periodontal and Bone Response to Normal Function</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Learning Objectives</title><pageText><p>It is easy to think about moving teeth as a mechanical problem that requires an 
engineering solution, and in fact an orthodontic appliance can be analyzed like 
any mechanical device&#8212;but the engineering solution doesn&#8217;t predict 
what will happen when the orthodontic appliance is used.</p>

<p>Why not? Because tooth movement requires remodeling of the bone that supports 
the teeth, and the objective of the appliance is not to move the teeth, but to 
use gentle force to produce the biologic response that allows tooth movement 
and/or affects growth of the jaws and face. That concept can be a bit difficult 
to really accept, but it is the key to understanding clinical orthodontic 
treatment.</p>

<p>In this module, the goal is to explore the principles that underlie the biology 
of treatment, looking at both the local (dentoalveolar) and distant (jaw / face) 
responses to orthodontic force.</p>

<p>In addition to viewing this module, read Chapter 9, pages 331-358 in the 4th 
edition of <i>Contemporary Orthodontics</i>.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Biting Force and Tooth Movement</title><pageText><p>You certainly have already noticed, perhaps without thinking much about it, that 
your teeth are repeatedly subjected to heavy loads during mastication but are 
stable in their position. How can we explain that a tooth stays in position 
quite nicely despite the forces of occlusion, which normally range up to 50 kg 
and can be much higher at maximum effort&#8212;and yet the same tooth can be 
made to move with light force from an orthodontic appliance?</p>

<p>The first thing to remember is that the periodontal ligament space (image 1) 
functions very nicely as a shock absorber. In between the tooth and the alveolar 
bone is the periodontal ligament (PDL), which of course consists of cellular 
elements in a fluid-filled chamber. For the shock absorber effect, the cellular 
elements are irrelevant&#8212;it&#8217;s the fluid that&#8217;s important. When 
you bite down, the fluid is incompressible, and the first thing that happens is 
that the alveolar bone bends. The tooth (or teeth) moves relative to the jaw, 
but not relative to the alveolar bone. After one second or so, the fluid 
begins to be squeezed out, and at that point the cellular elements begin to 
feel pressure. If you bite down on what you thought was a peanut and it 
doesn&#8217;t break apart, you probably maintain the force and bite a little 
harder. If it still doesn&#8217;t shatter, you begin to feel pain because the 
cellular elements are being loaded more as the fluid continues to be squeezed 
out&#8212;and you stop biting. Maybe they put one of the finest little 
Virginia rocks in the bag of Virginia peanuts!</p>

<p>Note in the attached chart (image 2) the time course of heavy pressure against 
a tooth. Over the time of a very few seconds, the physiologic response is bone 
bending, then pain if the heavy pressure is maintained.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-1a.jpg" resourceWidth="202" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-1a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="36" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-1b.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-1b_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Bone Bending as a Stimulus to Bone Maintenance</title><pageText><p>Bone bending turns out to be important for more than just allowing us to 
withstand heavy forces during mastication. Have you thought about why the 
alveolar bone resorbs and all but disappears over time after a tooth is 
extracted? We know now that bone bending is necessary to maintain normal 
calcification and remodeling. Somewhere in orbit at this moment an astronaut 
is pedaling away on an exercise bike, trying to prevent decalcification of his 
skeleton by causing the bending of arm, leg and other bones that happens as 
you function against the pull of gravity. It&#8217;s not just alveolar bone 
that bends under normal function. The mandible bends every time you open wide, 
and some bending occurs in all bones that are subjected to external forces.</p>

<p>Bone bending produces an interesting electrical effect, the generation of a 
piezo-electric current (image 1). Force against a crystalline structure (many 
nonbiologic crystals, but also bone and collagen) mechanically distorts the 
crystals. This produces a current flow as electrons move to a different 
location within the crystal lattice. When the force that produced bending is 
removed, the electrons move back to their original position, and a reverse 
current flow is observed. As you walk down the street, there is a rhythmic 
current flow with each step. When you chew, the same rhythmic current flow 
occurs in your alveolar bone and throughout your jaws.</p>

<p>So why is alveolar bone lost when a tooth is extracted? After the tooth is 
gone, it doesn&#8217;t get the rhythmic loading necessary to generate the 
piezo-electric currents, and the result is decalcification and resorption.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-2.gif" resourceWidth="497" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-2_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="88" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Force application to a crystalline structure generates a current flow as 
electrons move to a new location, and when the force is removed, a reverse 
current flow is observed.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Piezo-electricity and Orthodontic Tooth Movement</title><pageText><p>When biologic piezo-electricity was discovered in the 1960s, it was 
immediately thought that perhaps orthodontic tooth movement would be more 
effective if pulsed rather than continuous forces were used. Fortunately 
for the complexity of orthodontic appliances, experiments showed that this 
was not the case.</p>

<p>The bottom line: piezo-electric currents are important for maintenance of 
calcification of bones that are loaded during function, which very much 
includes alveolar bone, but are irrelevant for orthodontic tooth movement.</p>

<p>Does that mean electrical signals have no role in the bone remodeling that 
makes orthodontic tooth movement possible? No, because it has been demonstrated 
that electrical fields can alter cell membrane potentials and the ability of 
molecules to enter cells. Will the time come that a patient is to plug in 
their braces rather than connect the rubber bands? Perhaps, but it seems 
quite unlikely. The classic theory of how cells are affected by orthodontic 
force, the pressure-tension theory, remains the basis of our understanding 
of orthodontic tooth movement. Let&#8217;s take a look at that theory now.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/bioelectricity_and_movement.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/bioelectricity_and_movement_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Response to Sustained Orthodontic Force</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Sustained versus Short-Duration Force</title><pageText><p>What happens when force against a tooth, which creates pressure in the PDL, 
is maintained? If the force is heavy, as with the multi-kilogram force 
generated during chewing or clenching the teeth tightly, severe pain is 
felt immediately. If the force is lighter, perhaps 50 or 100 grams, 
immediate pain does not occur.</p>

<p>Suppose you activate a spring that presses against a tooth with a force of 
100 grams? What&#8217;s the first thing that happens? That&#8217;s right, 
the tooth is displaced and the alveolar bone bends. But this time the force 
is not released. Within a few seconds the bone begins to spring back, creating 
pressure in the PDL on the pressure, fluid begins to be expressed from the 
pressure side, and although the tooth stays in the same position relative to 
the head or other external references, now it is displaced relative to the 
alveolar bone. This creates pressure in the PDL on one side and tension on 
the other.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-2a.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-2a_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Pressure-Tension Effects</title><pageText><p>The pressure-tension explanation for orthodontic tooth movement relies on 
chemical rather than electrical signals as the stimulus for cell 
differentiation and ultimately tooth movement. There is no doubt that 
chemical messengers are important in the cascade of events that lead to 
remodeling of alveolar bone. Because this theory explains the course of 
events reasonably well, it is the basis of our current understanding.</p>

<p>From the perspective of pressure-tension and release of chemical messengers, 
application of a light but sustained force to a tooth has 
two effects:</p>

<ol class="spaced">
<li>mechanical distortion of cells in the periodontal ligament, which causes 
release of the contents of some cells, and</li>

<li>a decrease in blood flow in the PDL on the side opposite the direction 
of force application, where the PDL is compressed, and an increase in blood 
flow on the other side, where the PDL is under tension. This leads to a 
change in oxygen and carbon dioxide levels in the PDL. Both effects lead 
to the release of chemical messengers from affected cells.</li>
</ol>

<p>Classic animal experiments by David Khouw in Goldhaber&#8217;s lab at 
Harvard in the 1960s allow visualization of the blood flow change. He 
infused India ink into experimental animals while the animal was being 
sacrificed, so that blood vessels in the periodontal ligament could be 
seen easily. Note in images 1,2 and 3 the effect on blood flow of 
compressing the PDL, while image 4 shows the effect on the tension side.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-4a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="310" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-4a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="155" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-4b.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="449" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-4b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-4c.jpg" resourceWidth="579" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-4c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="103" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-5.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="442" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-5_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="109" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Pressure-Tension Effects (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The same effects on vessels in the PDL are shown diagrammatically in the 
attached drawings. As pressure increases, the PDL is increasingly compressed, 
and if the pressure is high enough, blood flow is totally cut off.</p>

<p>What is the result of totally cutting off blood flow? Necrosis of the tissue 
in that area, of course. In early studies of the effects of sustained force, 
someone thought that the PDL tissue where blood flow was cut off resembled 
hyaline cartilage, and still sometimes these areas are called hyalinized. 
Perhaps that&#8217;s an acceptable euphemism&#8212;it sounds better than 
necrotic, but a better description is sterile necrosis.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-6a.jpg" resourceWidth="452" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-6a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>no pressure</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-6b.jpg" resourceWidth="448" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-6b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>light pressure, mild compression of vessels</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-6c.jpg" resourceWidth="448" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-6c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>heavier pressure, moderate compression</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-6d.jpg" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-6d_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>heavy pressure, vessels totally occluded</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cascade of Events Leading to Tooth Movement</title><pageText><p>Within minutes after sustained light force is placed against a tooth, pressure 
and tension are created within the PDL, oxygen / carbon dioxide levels are 
altered, and prostaglandins and cytokines are released.</p>

<p>These chemical messengers affect cellular activity, and enzyme levels change.
Within a few hours, metabolic changes can be detected. In experiments with 
cats, Davidovitch detected increased cyclic AMP levels at about 4 hours, which 
suggests that cell differentiation is beginning.</p>

<p>With ideally light pressure, early remodeling of the tooth socket by 
osteoclasts and osteoblasts can be observed at about 2 days, and tooth 
movement by frontal resorption (resorption of alveolar bone alongside the 
PDL) begins.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-2c.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-2c_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cascade of Events with Heavier Sustained Pressure</title><pageText><p>Now let&#8217;s look at the sequence and timing of events leading to tooth 
movement if heavier force is used, so that there is enough pressure in the 
PDL to totally occlude blood vessels in some areas on the compression side.</p>

<p>What&#8217;s the first thing that happens? The same thing that happens with 
any application of force to a tooth: bone bending. With sustained force the 
alveolar bone springs back and the PDL is placed under compression in some 
areas and tension in others.</p>

<p>Let&#8217;s look at the sequence after that. In 3-5 seconds blood vessels 
are totally occluded in some compressed areas and mechanically-distorted 
cells are leaking cytokines and prostaglandins. Within a few minutes, blood 
flow ceases in those areas, and cell death begins. After some hours, there are 
no cells in the PDL to differentiate into the osteoclasts and osteoblasts needed 
for remodeling of the socket. Where are the cells going to come from?</p>

<p>There are two answers to that question: (1) from adjacent PDL areas that are 
not necrotic, and (2) from bone marrow spaces outside the lamina dura. If the 
necrotic area is tiny, cells from adjacent areas would be the major source. If 
it&#8217;s larger, the bone marrow is the more likely source via a process 
called undermining resorption. Take a careful look at the sequence of events 
in this chart, and then we&#8217;ll examine undermining resorption more 
closely.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-2b.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-2b_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Undermining Resorption</title><pageText><p>Undermining resorption has that name because it is necessary for osteoclasts 
to resorb the lamina dura from its underside. A necrotic area in the PDL sends 
a chemical signal to stimulate the formation of  osteoclasts, but it takes a 
few days for this to penetrate through the lamina dura into the bone marrow. So 
instead of 2 days for remodeling to begin, it&#8217;s 3-5 days before an 
osteoclastic attack on the underside of the lamina dura begins. Note the 
typical Howship&#8217;s lacunae on the underside of the lamina dura in this 
image from Dr. Khouw&#8217;s research (image 1).</p>

<p>It takes 7-14 days for the lamina dura to be removed, and at that point tooth 
movement begins with a sudden jump in the direction of the force. If heavy 
force still is present, there&#8217;s another delay while further undermining 
resorption occurs, so light force actually produces more tooth movement early 
in treatment than heavy force (image 2). One indicator that force is too 
heavy is that the tooth gets quite loose. The periodontal ligament space 
enlarges during orthodontic tooth movement, so there&#8217;s always some 
increase in mobility while tooth movement is occuring, but a really loose 
tooth reflects loss of a lot of the lamina dura.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-07.jpg" resourceWidth="579" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-07_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="103" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-8.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="403" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-8_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="119" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Diagrammatic representation of the time course of tooth movement with frontal 
vs undermining resorption</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Force Distribution and Types of Tooth Movement</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Tipping: the Simplest Form of Tooth Movement</title><pageText><p>Tipping of a tooth occurs when a single force is applied to the crown of a 
tooth. Because the resistance to movement is created almost entirely by the 
root, this produces rotation around a point about halfway down the root, which 
is called the &#8220;center of resistance&#8221;. Heavy pressure / tension 
in the periodontal ligament is felt at the apex of the root and at the crest 
of the alveolar bone, which decreases progressively toward the center of 
resistance.</p>

<p>In tipping, only one-half the PDL area that could be compressed actually is. 
This loading diagram is represented as a pair of triangles covering half the 
PDL. With a single force against the crown of the tooth, the crown goes one 
way and the root apex goes the other. Maximum pressure occurs at the crest 
of the alveolar bone and at the root apex, with no pressure at a point 
halfway along the root (which is the center of resistance, and in this 
instance also the center of rotation). We&#8217;ll be talking more about 
those terms later.</p>

<p>Both human and animal experiments indicate that tipping forces should not 
exceed approximately 50 grams, and for small teeth it should be less 
than that.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-9.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="419" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-9_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="115" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Bodily Movement</title><pageText><p>If you want to move a tooth bodily (create as much root as crown movement in 
the same direction), it is necessary to apply two forces simultaneously to 
the crown of the tooth, so that there is both a force to move the crown and 
a moment (force applied at a distance) to move the root. This loads the 
entire PDL area, so that there is equal compression all along one side of 
the root.</p>

<p>If twice as much of the PDL is loaded in bodily movement as in tipping, you 
would think that twice as much force would be needed. That&#8217;s correct, 
about 100 grams is needed to produce bodily movement.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-10.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="439" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-10_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="109" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Rotation, Extrusion and Torque</title><pageText><p>Other types of tooth movement are rotation, extrusion, torque and intrusion. 
Intrusion is a special case we will discuss in the next screen.</p>

<p>You would think that rotation of a tooth around its long axis would 
potentially load the entire volume of the PDL, not just an area on one side 
of the tooth. Extrusion, pulling the tooth gently out of the socket (gently, 
we don&#8217;t want to extract it!) also could load the entire PDL volume. 
Would that mean that much higher force would be needed for either of these 
movements? The answer is no. In fact, it is impossible to rotate or extrude 
a tooth without compressing areas similar to those that are loaded in tipping. 
Why? Because the roots are irregularly shaped, not conical, so that as soon 
as a tooth responds to either of these directions of force, it tips as well 
as rotating or extruding. For that reason, the ideal force for rotation and 
extrusion is the same as for tipping, ~50 grams.</p>

<p>Torque is the type of tooth movement in which the root apex is moved further 
than the crown of the tooth in the desired direction. To accomplish this, a 
relatively larger moment is needed to move the root is needed in addition to 
the force to move the crown. This produces a loading diagram intermediate 
between what is needed for bodily movement and tipping, and therefore an 
intermediate force of ~75 grams is needed.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Intrusion: A Special Case</title><pageText><p>Until recently, orthodontic intrusion was so difficult that many orthodontists 
considered it impossible. Now we know that successful intrusion is possible 
only if exceptionally light force is applied down the long axis of the tooth, 
so that the PDL is compressed just at the apex of the root.</p>

<p>That makes sense, of course, when you remember that force against the 
crown becomes pressure in the PDL. Intrusion compresses only a small 
area at the root apex, and so a small force produces the same pressure 
as a larger force would if it were distributed over a larger area of the 
PDL. The optimum force for intrusion is ~10 grams, less for smaller teeth, 
perhaps a bit more for larger ones like canines, definitely more (but still 
small) for multi-rooted teeth.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-11.jpg" resourceWidth="382" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-11_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="68" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Force Magnitudes for Tooth Movement</title><pageText><p>This table summarizes the amount of force needed to produce different types 
of tooth movement. The way to think about it is to realize that there is 
only one optimum pressure in the PDL, and different forces are needed to 
obtain that optimum pressure depending on the type of tooth movement that 
is desired.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-3_optimum_forces.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-3_optimum_forces_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Force Duration</title><pageText><p>Does the force to move a tooth have to be there every minute in order to get 
the tooth to move? If so, that would require a major effort in cooperation 
by the patient. Wearing a removable appliance all the time is impossible. 
You have to take it out to clean it and brush your teeth, and it&#8217;s so 
difficult to eat while wearing most appliances that you have to take it out 
for meals. With a fixed appliance, if you&#8217;re wearing rubber bands, 
you&#8217;d have to remove them at least briefly to brush your teeth and 
put on new ones, even if you wore them during eating.</p>

<p>Orthodontists have run many inadvertent experiments on how many hours an 
appliance has to be worn, simply by using removable appliances and observing 
the results. Anything that can be removed by a patient will be&#8212;the 
only question is how many hours it will be in the mouth instead of out.</p>

<p>With removable appliances there is a threshold somewhere between 4 and 8 
hours per day, below which no tooth movement happens. Above the threshold, 
the amount of tooth movement increases with increasing hours per day, with 
decreasing returns toward the top of the curve. A theoretic plot of tooth 
movement efficiency versus duration of force is shown in the attached 
image. The concept it illustrates is correct, but the details simply 
aren&#8217;t known.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-12.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="438" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-12_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="110" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Force Decay: Continuous vs. Interrupted Force</title><pageText><p>Ideally one would use a perfect spring to apply orthodontic force&#8212;but 
of course this isn&#8217;t a perfect world, and for all practical purposes 
there aren&#8217;t any perfect springs. A perfect spring is one whose force 
would not change when a tooth began to move away from it. Real springs show 
a decline in force, perhaps all the way to zero, as a tooth moves.</p>

<p>We already have said that a light continuous force is the best way to 
move teeth. From a real world perspective, continuous force doesn&#8217;t 
mean that the force doesn&#8217;t change. It means that force is maintained 
all the time between adjustment appointments even though some force decay 
occurs, as this image shows.</p>

<p>If the force is light enough to avoid undermining resorption, a relatively 
slow progression of tooth movement will result from frontal resorption, 
which is resorption on the PDL side of the lamina dura that lines the tooth 
socket. If the continuous force is heavy, tooth movement will be delayed 
until undermining resorption (from the underside of the lamina dura) occurs. 
Then the tooth will adjust its position rapidly, and if the heavy force is 
still present so that another area of the PDL loses its blood supply, there 
will be no opportunity for tissue repair and another round of undermining 
resorption will be generated. This can be quite destructive.</p>

<p>The bottom line: light continuous force is good, heavy continuous force 
is not.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-13a.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="398" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-13a_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Continuous vs Interrupted Force</title><pageText><p>In contrast, a spring with poorer force decay characteristics might produce a 
force that dropped to zero before the patient returned for reactivation. 
This is defined as interrupted force. If the initial force level is light 
enough, the tooth will move a small amount by frontal resorption and then 
stop until the spring is activated again. If the initial force level is 
heavy but decays to zero after the first movement of the tooth, the tooth 
will move only when undermining resorption has occurred&#8212;and stop there, 
since the force has now dropped to zero. This provides an opportunity for 
regeneration and repair of the PDL before force is applied again.</p>

<p>It is difficult to keep orthodontic force low enough totally avoid necrotic 
PDL areas, so some areas of undermining resorption probably are generated in 
almost every patient. The heavier forces that produce this response are 
physiologically acceptable only if the force declines to zero before the 
next reactivation appointment.</p>

<p>That leads to an interesting paradox: the more perfect the spring (the slower 
its force decays), the more careful the clinician must be to apply only light 
force. Springs with poor force decay characteristics produce only interrupted 
force. They are not capable of causing the biologic damage that can occur with 
heavy continuous force. Heavy continuous force must be avoided; heavy 
interrupted force can be clinically acceptable even though this is less 
efficient and more likely to produce pain.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-13b.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="390" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-13b_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Intermittent Force</title><pageText><p>Continuous force is impossible with a removable appliance, since the force 
falls to zero as soon as it is removed and is reestablished when the appliance 
is inserted again. The result is intermittent force, which also shows force 
decay as tooth movement occurs. Intermittent force would also become 
interrupted force if after some tooth movement, there was no reestablishment 
of force when the removable appliance was reinserted.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-13c.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="395" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-13c_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="122" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Reactivation Intervals</title><pageText><p>A clinical rule is that orthodontic appliances should not be reactivated 
more frequently than every 3 weeks, and a 4- to 6-week interval between 
appointments is more typical. Undermining resorption takes 7 to 14 days. 
When this is the mode of tooth movement and when force levels decay rapidly, 
tooth movement is essentially completed in that amount of time. Another 2 
weeks or so is needed for repair before the appliance is reactivated.</p>

<p>So with a springy appliance that produces light force, there is no need for 
frequent reactivation at short intervals, while with a less springy appliance 
that produces heavy force initially, a repair period is needed. You might 
think that if patients were seen every week to reactivate the orthodontic 
appliance, faster tooth movement would have to result. Bad idea&#8212;the 
result might be heavy continuous force and significant tissue damage.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Deleterious Effects of Orthodontic Force</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Pain</title><pageText><p>If heavy sustained pressure is applied to a tooth, pain develops immediately 
as the PDL is literally crushed. If you activate an orthodontic appliance and 
there is immediate pain, it&#8217;s obvious that too much force is being 
used, and action to reduce the force is required. There is no immediate pain 
with appropriate force magnitudes.</p>

<p>Several hours later, however, the patient usually feels a mild aching 
sensation, and the teeth are sensitive to pressure so that biting something 
hard hurts. The pain typically lasts 2-4 days, then disappears until the next 
activation of the appliance. At that point the same cycle may recur, but 
almost always the greatest pain follows the first activation. There is a 
great deal of variation: some patients report no pain, others have considerable 
pain with even very light force.</p>

<p>The pain is related to the development of ischemic areas in the PDL that are 
on the way to sterile necrosis. During the first 24 hours, having the patient 
bite repeatedly on a plastic wafer or chew gum decreases pain&#8212;probably 
because this displaces the tooth temporarily and allows spurts of blood flow 
through compressed areas.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Effects on the Dental Pulp</title><pageText><p>You would expect a light sustained force against the crown of a tooth to 
produce a PDL response, but not an effect on the pulp. The increased 
sensitivity to biting force after initial activation of an orthodontic 
appliance, however, suggests inflammation at the root apex, and this 
probably is related to mild pulpitis that occurs during the first few days.</p>

<p>The mild pulpitis has no long term significance. Loss of tooth vitality 
during orthodontic treatment almost never occurs. When this does happen, 
usually there is a history of previous trauma to that tooth, but poor 
control of heavy orthodontic force also can be the culprit. If heavy 
continuous force is used, a large abrupt movement of the tooth after 
undermining resorption can result in severance of the blood vessels 
entering the pulp. It also is possible to sever these vessels by moving 
the root apex through the labial cortical plate. Fortunately, this is 
hard to do,  but it has occurred.</p>

<p>Because tooth movement is a PDL phenomenon, not a pulpal one, moving 
endodontically-treated teeth should be possible, and this is correct. 
There is no contraindication to orthodontic repositioning of a non-vital 
but endodontically treated tooth. This is most likely to be needed in an 
adult before definitive restorative or prosthodontic treatment is done.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/endo_pan.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="344" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/endo_pan_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="140" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>For this patient, the endo-treated tooth will respond to orthodontic force 
like the other teeth</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Effects on Root Structure</title><pageText><p>The goal of orthodontic force is to generate remodeling of alveolar bone so 
a tooth can move. For many years it was thought that osteoclasts did not 
attack tooth roots. Now we know that roots often are attacked by clast cells, 
but that repair of the root also occurs.</p>

<p>In the absence of necrotic (hyalinized) PDL areas, uncalcified cementum on 
the root surface protects against osteoclastic attack, but cementum adjacent 
to a necrotic area is &#8220;marked&#8221; or stained by adjacent necrotic 
tissue in the PDL, and clast cells attack this area when the PDL is repaired. 
Cementum (and dentin if the attack penetrates all the way through the 
cementum) is removed, and then new cementum is formed to fill in the 
defect in the tooth root.</p>

<p>In this figure, which is a coronal section of a premolar being moved to the 
left before it was extracted for study (which is ethical if premolar 
extraction was required anyway), note the area of compression of the PDL on 
the left side and the tension area on the right side. Osteoblasts and bone 
formation can be seen in the tension area; osteoclastic activity is apparent 
on the compression side; and areas of root resorption with penetration into 
the dentin also can be seen on that side. These areas would be filled in with 
new cementum under normal conditions. So root remodeling is a feature of 
orthodontic tooth movement&#8212;but there would be a loss of root structure 
only if repair did not replace the resorbed cementum.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-22.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-22_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Resorption penetrating into the dentin (courtesy Dr. Birte Melsen).</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Apical Root Resorption</title><pageText><p>Repair of the damaged root does restore its original contours along the side 
of the root and at the apex&#8212;unless the attack on the root surface at 
the apex leads to coalescence of craters. This can create islands of root 
structure that are separated from the root surface. Once that happens, the 
island resorbs and is lost, as image 1 shows diagrammatically. This is why 
permanent loss of root structure related to orthodontic treatment occurs 
primarily at the apex.</p>

<p>Several studies have shown that in general, root length for most teeth 
decreases about 1 mm for each year of complete fixed appliance treatment, 
but of course there is considerable individual variation. The data presented 
in image 2 come from a study comparing treatment changes in patients treated 
for Class I crowding at the Univ. of Washington. One group, who had had 
serial extraction earlier, had an average of 15 months in a fixed 
appliance. The other group, who had extractions just before their fixed 
appliance started, had an average of 24 months. Note that some loss of root 
length occurred in the 15 months group, but a bit more occurred for most 
teeth as the treatment time increased. All other things being equal, the 
longer the treatment time, the greater the root resorption.</p>

<p>Resorption of this magnitude, 1 or 2 mm (usually referred to as moderate 
generalized resorption) is a finding, not a problem (images 3 and 4). It is 
best considered as an inevitable part of comprehensive orthodontic treatment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-23.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="206" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-23_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="57"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>diagrammatic representation of apical resorption</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-4_avg_root_change.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/table_9-4_avg_root_change_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-24a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="401" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-24a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>mild blunting of root apices</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-24b.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="405" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-24b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>moderate apical root resorption (loss of less than 1/4 of root length)</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Severe Generalized Resorption</title><pageText><p>There are three types of apical root resorption that can be seen after 
orthodontic treatment: (1) mild to moderate generalized resorption, which 
we have already discussed; (2) severe generalized resorption, and (3) severe 
localized resorption. Now let&#8217;s look at the severe varieties.</p>

<p>Severe generalized resorption describes the loss of most of the roots of most 
of the teeth. It is quite rare&#8212;the average dentist is likely to 
encounter only one or two such cases in a career. But if you see one, you 
won&#8217;t forget it.</p>

<p>Why a few individuals have resorption of this type remains unknown. We know a 
lot of things that don&#8217;t cause it. Among those is orthodontic treatment. 
Severe generalized resorption is as likely to occur in people who never had 
orthodontic treatment as in those who did.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/severe_gen_resorption_pan.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="309" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/severe_gen_resorption_pan_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="155" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Severe generalized resorption--which fortunately is quite rare</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Severe Localized Resorption</title><pageText><p>Severe localized resorption, as seen in this image, is defined as loss of 
more than &#188; of the root of some teeth. It also is uncommon but occurs 
in 2-3% of orthodontic patients, and is related to the treatment. The 
maxillary incisors are by far the most likely teeth to be affected. Other 
teeth can be affected, but this is uncommon.</p>

<p>Why does this happen to some patients but not to the great majority? There 
seem to be two major factors: 
(1) some individuals clearly are more susceptible to root resorption than 
others, and (2) one aspect of tooth movement, bringing the root apices into 
contact with cortical bone, is a definite risk factor.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-24c.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="406" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-24c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Severe Localized Resorption</title><pageText><p>At this point it is not known why some individuals are susceptible, but we 
do know that in them resorption starts earlier and advances more rapidly. 
As a result, as part of informed consent, orthodontic patients and parents 
should be told that significant root resorption is unlikely but possible.</p>

<p>Root contact with cortical bone is most likely to occur when the root apices 
of maxillary incisors are moved lingually, either as the crown is tipped 
facially (which leads to root apices moving lingually) or as the roots of 
the incisors are torqued lingually. A study at North Carolina reported that 
the chance of severe resorption was increased 20-fold when the incisor roots 
contacted the lingual cortical plate. This becomes a limitation on how much 
maxillary incisors can be moved during treatment.</p>

<p>The bottom line: It is good practice to take a panoramic radiograph 6-9 
months after orthodontic treatment begins to check the status of roots. If 
obvious resorption is occurring at that point, keeping treatment as short as 
possible and compromising treatment goals may be necessary.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-24c.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="406" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-24c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Distant Effects of Orthodontic Force: Growth Modification</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Modification?</title><pageText><p>Because orthodontic force applied to the teeth also is felt by the facial 
skeleton, it has the potential to modify growth of the jaws. If this were 
successful, it would provide a way to treat skeletal problems. It seems 
reasonable that pressures resisting the normal downward and forward growth of 
either jaw could diminish the amount of growth, while adding to the pressures 
that pull the jaws downward and forward could increase the growth. The 
clinical effectiveness of some treatment procedures aimed at modifying growth 
has been demonstrated in recent years, but it is important to understand 
that some things are more possible than others and that the amount of skeletal 
change is relatively small.</p>

<p>The goal of this section is to help you understand how growth modification 
works, and to put its effectiveness for various possible changes into 
perspective.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Principles in Growth Modification</title><pageText><p>When growth modification is considered, at least three principles should be 
kept in mind:</p>

<ol class="spaced">
<li>You can&#8217;t modify growth that isn&#8217;t happening. That means 
treatment at a period of rapid growth usually is the best plan, and for 
practical purposes, it means that the adolescent growth spurt is the 
preferred time for most growth modification treatment (but not all, as we 
will discuss below).</li>

<li>When growth modification is desired, tooth movement almost always is 
undesirable. Correction of a malocclusion is not a primary goal of growth 
modification treatment, correction of an improper jaw relationship is. The 
less a malocclusion is corrected by tooth movement, and the more it is 
corrected by favorable jaw growth, the more successful the growth modification 
treatment is.</li>

<li>The hours of the day are not created equal relative to growth. In fact, 
almost all skeletal growth (and tooth eruption) occurs in a critical time 
period between early evening and midnight. Whatever the growth modification 
device is, it&#8217;s important for it to be worn during these hours&#8212;but 
wearing it all the time may be neither necessary nor desirable.</li>
</ol></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Restraint of Maxillary Growth</title><pageText><p>Excessive maxillary growth contributes to both Class II and long face 
problems. Since formation of new bone as the sutures above and behind the 
maxilla are pulled apart by soft tissue growth is a major mechanism of 
growth, a force to restrain growth at the sutures ought to be effective.</p>

<p>Extra-oral force to restrain maxillary growth that is produced by a headgear 
device (image 1) has been used in orthodontics for many years. Because of the 
large area of the sutures, a heavier force than is recommended for tooth 
movement is generally considered necessary for effective restraint. A force 
of about 250 grams per side (500 gm total) is thought to be about the minimum. 
Because this force often is applied just to the maxillary first molars, 
its effect on the teeth is a matter of concern. As we have discussed, heavy 
continuous force against the teeth is undesirable. Intermittent force is 
less effective for tooth movement, and it makes sense to suggest that the 
headgear should be worn during the early evening (don&#8217;t wait until you 
go to bed!) and night, but perhaps not during the day. The force duration 
should be at least 12 hours per day. Whether this really limits tooth 
movement without compromising the skeletal effect has not been clearly 
demonstrated.</p>

<p>A change in the direction of maxillary growth often is observed with headgear 
treatment (image 2). Note that the maxilla actually moved slightly back in 
this individual as he grew while wearing his headgear consistently. Not all 
treatment results are so favorable, however. Clinical 
trials indicate that there is about a 75% chance of an improvement in a 
skeletal Class II jaw relationship with headgear treatment during adolescence. 
Although this surely is affected by the degree of the patient&#8217;s 
cooperation, it appears that cooperation is not the whole story. For whatever 
reason, some children respond better than others.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-26.jpg" resourceWidth="448" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-26_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-27.gif" resourceWidth="358" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-27_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="64" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Augmentation of Maxillary Growth</title><pageText><p>Increasing the amount of forward growth of the maxilla by pulling forward 
with a face mask (reverse headgear) (image 1) has not been as successful 
as restraint of maxillary growth, especially when the treatment is done during 
adolescence. Part of the problem is getting enough force at the maxillary 
sutures to pull them apart, but a bigger problem is the anatomy of the 
sutures.</p>

<p>Human autopsy material has shown the morphology of the mid-palatal suture at 
different ages, and the other maxillary sutures are similar. In the images 
with this screen, the two halves of the maxilla are shown below, with the 
nasal septum above. Note in image 2 that the mid-palatal suture is an open 
straight-line structure in infants and young children. It shows some 
convolutions in childhood (early mixed dentition) (image 3), and by late 
childhood / early adolescence the suture is so interdigitated (image 4) that 
opening it requires micro-fractures of the bone spicules along the suture 
line. After the adolescent growth spurt opening the suture is possible only 
with surgical assistance.</p>

<p>If you want to move the maxilla forward you have to do so at an early age, 
before the sutures become so locked up. So maxillary advancement to augment 
growth is an exception to the rule about treatment during adolescence. It 
has to be done before adolescence, during the elementary school years.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_13-10b.jpg" resourceWidth="296" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_13-10b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-25a.jpg" resourceWidth="513" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-25a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="91" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Mid-palatal suture in the early preschool years</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-25b.jpg" resourceWidth="488" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-25b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="87" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>Mid-palatal suture in the mixed dentition</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-25c.jpg" resourceWidth="418" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-25c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="74" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>Mid-palatal suture in late childhood</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Restraint of Mandibular Growth</title><pageText><p>You have learned already that the mandible grows downward and forward as it 
is pulled in that direction by the growth of the soft tissues in which it 
is embedded&#8212;so a force to prevent that movement should effectively 
restrain growth. Unfortunately this just doesn&#8217;t work. A chin cup or 
other restraining device attached to the chin (image 1) may rotate the 
mandible down and back, so that growth is more down and less forward, but 
it&#8217;s remarkably ineffective in preventing the mandible from growing.</p>

<p>There are several explanations for this ineffectiveness, none totally 
satisfying: it&#8217;s difficult to load the whole TM joint area instead of 
just a part of it (image 2); a force large enough to be effective may be 
painful; a chin cup is uncomfortable to wear even if it isn&#8217;t painful; 
and so on.</p>

<p>For patients with excessive mandibular growth, the only really successful 
treatment is surgery to reduce the size of the mandible after adolescent 
growth has stopped.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_8-31b.jpg" resourceWidth="349" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_8-31b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="62" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-28.gif" resourceWidth="593" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-28_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="105" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Augmentation of Mandibular Growth</title><pageText><p>The soft tissues pull the mandible forward, and the condylar process grows 
upward and backward in response, so a device to further move the mandible 
forward ought to make it grow larger. Mandibular deficiency is the major 
cause of skeletal Class II problems. Not surprisingly, appliances to try 
to make the mandible grow have played a prominent role in growth modification 
treatment.</p>

<p>There are dozens if not hundreds of devices to hold the mandible forward and 
encourage it to grow (images 1 and 2). They&#8217;re referred to generically 
as &#8220;functional appliances&#8221;, but function has little to do with 
their effect. The name of the game is holding the mandible forward so that 
the condyle is down and forward from the glenoid fossa.</p>

<p>The typical outcome of functional appliance treatment is encouraging on one 
hand, and discouraging on the other. It often happens that in the short term, 
an acceleration of mandibular growth is observed, but in a longer term the 
growth rate tends to decline so that the mandible no longer is growing as 
much as might have been expected without the appliance (image 3). Does the 
mandible end up larger than it would have been without treatment? Perhaps 
a little bit, only a millimeter or two.</p>

<p>The interesting result is that although the theory behind their use is totally 
different, the outcome of headgear and functional appliance treatment is 
remarkably similar. How much skeletal change can you get? Perhaps 4-5 mm, 
rarely more, and both jaws seem to be affected by both appliance types.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig13-27b.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig13-27b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Bionator appliance: a block of plastic between the teeth guides the patient 
into advancement of the mandible</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig13-29a.jpg" resourceWidth="414" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig13-29a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="74" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>The Frankel appliance: shields hold the lower lip and cheeks away from the 
teeth while the mandible is held forward by a wire framework and lingual pad</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_8-19.gif" resourceWidth="581" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_8-19_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="103" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>The usual response to a functional appliance is short-term acceleration of 
mandibular growth, followed by slow growth later so that there is little or no 
long-term increase in size</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Retention</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Why Is Retention Necessary?</title><pageText><p>If you have had orthodontic treatment, you know that when the braces come 
off, some type of retainer follows, and the orthodontist tells you quite 
severely that you&#8217;d better wear it or your teeth won&#8217;t stay 
straight. Perhaps you didn&#8217;t believe that, didn&#8217;t wear the 
retainer, and found out for yourself that the teeth really will move 
spontaneously for a while after treatment. Why is that?</p>

<p>There are three major reasons for retention:</p>

<ol class="spaced">
<li>the gingival and periodontal tissues require time for reorganization 
after the orthodontic appliances are removed;</li>

<li>the teeth may be in an inherently unstable position, so that soft 
tissue pressures constantly produce a relapse tendency; and</li>

<li>changes produced by growth may alter the treatment result.</li>
</ol>

<p>Let&#8217;s consider these reasons one at the time.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>PDL / Gingival Reorganization</title><pageText><p>Disruption of the collagen fiber bundles in the PDL and widening of the PDL 
space are necessary to allow tooth movement to occur. Even if active tooth 
movement stops, reorganization of the PDL does not occur as long as each 
tooth is tightly splinted to the one next to it by a heavy archwire. After 
the braces are removed, reorganization of the PDL takes 3-4 months, and only 
at that point does the slight mobility that is normal after treatment 
disappear. During this time the teeth will be unstable against occlusal 
and soft tissue pressures that can be resisted later. For this reason, 
every patient needs retainers for at least a few months.</p>

<p>Gingival fibers are stretched when a tooth is moved a considerable distance 
or is rotated significantly. These fibers remodel quite slowly, and are 
still capable of moving a tooth back towards its original position even a 
year after treatment. This becomes a reason for more prolonged retention 
after correction of severe crowding. For a tooth or teeth that had correction 
of severe rotations, like the maxillary central incisors shown in these images, 
it is wise to sever the gingival fiber network around them (which must be done 
carefully to maintain the interdental papillae) before the braces are removed. 
Without this it can be almost impossible to maintain the rotation correction.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_16-16a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_16-16a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Sectioning the supra-crestal gingival elastic fibers is important if 
correction of rotation is to be maintained</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_16-16b.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_16-16b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Completion of fiber section surgery--an important adjunctive procedure 
in orthodontic treatment</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Unstable Tooth Positions</title><pageText><p>How far can you move teeth before the pressures of the lips/cheeks or tongue 
change enough to be a long-term factor in their stability? The question is 
asked correctly if you put it that way, because it&#8217;s how far the 
teeth were moved, not how their position after treatment compares to 
&#8220;standards&#8221; derived from population averages, that determines 
long-term stability. As a general 
rule (to which there are exceptions), the lower arch can be considered a 
foundation on which the upper arch rests, so how far the lower teeth were 
moved is important.</p>

<p>For a typical patient, the magnitude of change that is likely to be stable is 
shown in the attached figure. Note that the incisors can be advanced a little 
but not a lot, that stable expansion across the canines is extremely limited, 
and that the amount of stable transverse expansion is greater as you go 
posteriorly.</p>

<p>If the teeth are in an unstable position (for instance, after major arch 
expansion), the only possibilities are permanent retention or accepting 
relapse after retainers are discontinued.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_8-11.gif" resourceWidth="491" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_8-11_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="87" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Limits of movement for good stability</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Effects</title><pageText><p>Continued growth after treatment creates a problem in two circumstances:</p>

<ol class="spaced">
<li>patients who received growth modification treatment for a skeletal 
problem. You&#8217;ve already learned that the pattern of growth tends to 
be constant. If treatment changed it, growth after treatment still will be 
in the same pattern as it was originally. So the more a Class II, 
Class III, long face or asymmetric patient grows after treatment, the more 
likely it is that some of the correction will be lost. In these patients, 
the retainer may need to be a modification of a functional appliance, and 
it will need to be worn at night until the patient&#8217;s late teens or 
early twenties.</li>

<li>patients without a skeletal problem whose incisors were aligned with 
some expansion (image 1) or who hadspace closure in 
the maxillary incisor area (image 2). You will remember that there&#8217;s 
normally a little late mandibular growth in the late teens that occurs after 
maxillary growth has essentially ceased. This has the potential to create 
lower incisor crowding, even in an individual who never had orthodontic 
treatment. The late mandibular growth tends to increase pressure from the lip 
against the lower incisors, and also creates pressure against the upper 
incisors that can re-open space in that area. For that reason it is a good 
idea to bond a retainer in the lower incisor segment, or to continue 
night-time wear of a removable retainer, and also to maintain a maxillary 
retainer, at least until the late growth has occurred. If significant forward 
movement of the lower incisors occurred during treatment, a retainer will be 
needed indefinitely.</li>
</ol>

<p>Do you still have a retainer even though you&#8217;re now in dental school? 
If you&#8217;re in the approximately 50% of dental students who had orthodontic 
treatment, maybe you should.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_17-11a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_17-11a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Bonded lower retainer to maintain alignment as late growth occurs.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_17-11b.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_17-11b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Bonded maxillary incisor retainer to prevent space re-opening related 
to late mandibular growth.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary</title><pageText><p>To summarize this discussion of the biology of orthodontics:</p>

<ul class="spaced">
<li>Orthodontic tooth movement requires sustained light force.</li>

<li>The optimal force depends on the type of tooth movement. Force against a 
tooth creates pressure in the PDL. There is only one optimal pressure, but 
varying forces are needed to obtain it, depending on how much of the PDL is 
loaded.</li>

<li>Light continuous force (which may decline as teeth move, but not to zero) is 
the most effective and biologically benign way to move teeth. Heavy 
intermittent force, which declines to zero so that there is a repair 
period before the force is resumed, can be acceptable. Heavy continuous 
force must be avoided.</li>

<li>Moderate pain for 2-4 days is to be expected when orthodontic treatment is 
initiated. The magnitude of the pain is related to the magnitude of the force 
being used, because heavier force creates larger ischemic (and eventually 
necrotic) areas in the PDL.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary (cont.)</title><pageText><ul class="spaced">
<li>Modest apical root resorption (1-2 mm) accompanies almost all orthodontic 
tooth movement. More severe root resorption is seen in 2-3% of orthodontic 
patients.</li>

<li>Growth modification via forces to the teeth can produce a few millimeters of 
improvement in jaw relationships, with restraint of mandibular growth being 
the least effective.</li>

<li>
<p>Retention after orthodontic treatment is needed for three reasons:</p>
<ol class="spaced">
<li>it takes 3-4 months for PDL reorganization to occur</li>
<li>teeth may be in an unstable position, particularly after rotation 
correction or excessive expansion</li>
<li>growth after treatment can affect stability, especially in patients 
who had a skeletal problem, but also in those who exerience late mandibular 
growth that often causes crowding of lower incisors.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is not correct regarding piezo-electricity?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>important for maintaining calcification</choice><choice>affected by exercise level</choice><choice>important for orthodontic signaling</choice><choice>occurs in both biologic and non-biologic crystals</choice><choice>all are correct</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. Piezo-electricity is important for maintaining 
calcification, it&#8217;s affected by exercise level because it's generated by 
bone bending during function, and it occurs in both biologic and non-biologic 
crystalline materials&#8212;but it is not important for orthodontic signaling.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. Piezo-electricity is important for maintaining 
calcification, it&#8217;s affected by exercise level because it's generated by 
bone bending during function, and it occurs in both biologic and non-biologic 
crystalline materials&#8212;but it is not important for orthodontic signaling.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-2.gif" resourceWidth="497" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-2_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="88" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>Why is some shortening of tooth roots likely to occur after prolonged 
orthodontic treatment?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>it isn&#8217;t, osteoclasts don&#8217;t attack cementum</choice><choice>cementum repair only occurs along the sides of the tooth, not at the apex</choice><choice>craters in cementum fill in, but cementum islands are cut off and lost</choice><choice>unstained and therefore unprotected cementum is found mostly at the root apex</choice><choice>poor blood supply around the apex prevents cementum repair in that area</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, stained or marked cementum adjacent to necrotic areas is 
likely to be found around the apex of the tooth because it is easy to severely 
compress the PDL in that area. This leads to attack by clast cells during 
repair, and if the resulting craters coalesce, cementum islands that resorb 
during repair may be formed.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. Stained or marked cementum adjacent to necrotic areas 
is likely to be found around the apex of the tooth because it is easy to 
severely compress the PDL in that area.This leads to attack by clast cells 
during repair, and if the resulting craters coalesce, cementum islands that 
resorb during repair may be formed.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-23.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="206" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-23_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="57"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>Force against a tooth creates pressure in the periodontal ligament. If an 
equal force is used for the following types of tooth movement, which will 
have the lightest pressure?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>intrusion</choice><choice>tipping</choice><choice>rotation</choice><choice>torque</choice><choice>translation</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, with equal amounts of force against the crown, translation 
(bodily movement) would produce the lightest pressure because the force is 
distributed over the largest PDL area, and intrusion would have the highest 
pressure because the force is concentrated on a small area.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. With equal amounts of force against the crown, 
translation (bodily movement) would produce the lightest pressure because the 
force is distributed over the largest PDL area, and intrusion would have the 
highest pressure because the force is concentrated on a small area.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-10_9-11.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="270" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-10_9-11_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="75"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>What&#8217;s the first thing that happens when an orthodontic spring is 
applied against a tooth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>the tooth moves relative to the facial skeleton</choice><choice>the tooth moves within the periodontal ligament space</choice><choice>distorted cells release prostaglandins and cytokines</choice><choice>blood flow decreases in some areas and increases in others</choice><choice>it depends on how much force the spring exerts, could be 1 or 2 </choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s correct, the tooth moves relative to the facial skeleton as the 
alveolar bone bends, but it doesn&#8217;t move within the PDL space until 1-2 
seconds pass and the bone begins to spring back as fluid is squeezed out. 
Cell distortion and blood flow changes all start a minute or two after that.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. The tooth moves relative to the facial skeleton 
as the alveolar bone bends, but it doesn&#8217;t move within the PDL space 
until 1-2 seconds pass and the bone begins to spring back as fluid is squeezed 
out. Cell distortion and blood flow changes all start a minute or two after 
that.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>What&#8217;s the chance that severe shortening of the maxillary 
incisors (&gt;25% of the root length) will occur during typical 
orthodontic treatment?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>less than 0.5%</choice><choice>1%</choice><choice>2-3%</choice><choice>4-5%</choice><choice>10%</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct. The best data suggest that there is a 2-3% chance of severe 
resorption, with the maxillary incisors most likely to be affected, 
during typical treatment (which has about a 2-year duration). Fortunately, 
even when this occurs the chance of premature loss of the affected teeth 
remains very low.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. The best data suggest that there is a 2-3% 
chance of severe localized resorption, with the maxillary incisors most 
likely to be affected, during typical treatment (which has about a 2-year 
duration). Fortunately, even when this occurs the chance of premature loss 
of the affected teeth remains very low.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>What is the chance that severe generalized resorption (loss of much of the 
root of most of the teeth) will occur during typical orthodontic treatment?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>less than 0.5%</choice><choice>1%</choice><choice>2-3%</choice><choice>4-5%</choice><choice>10%</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, severe generalized resorption is quite rare, with a 
prevalence of much less than 0.5%. It is as likely to occur in patients 
who don&#8217;t have orthodontic treatment as in those who do, so 
orthodontics isn&#8217;t the cause&#8212;but the cause remains unknown.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That&#8217;s wrong. Severe generalized resorption is quite rare, with a 
prevalence of much less than 0.5%. It is as likely to occur in patients who 
don&#8217;t have orthodontic treatment as in those who do, so orthodontics 
isn&#8217;t the cause&#8212;but the cause remains unknown.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/severe_gen_resorption_pan.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="309" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/severe_gen_resorption_pan_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="155" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>What happens if orthodontic force is heavy enough to totally compress blood 
vessels in the PDL?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>hyaline cartilage forms in the compressed area</choice><choice>sterile necrotic areas develop in the compressed area</choice><choice>sterile necrotic areas develop in the pulp</choice><choice>persistent piezo-electric signals are observed</choice><choice>all the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. Sterile necrotic areas develop in the compressed area. 
These areas often are called hyalinized areas because some early observers 
thought they looked like hyaline cartilage, but cartilage doesn&#8217;t form 
there. Mild pulpitis can occur after activation of orthodontic appliances, 
but there are no necrotic areas in the pulp. Persistent piezo-electric signals 
are seen only during rhythmic function as bone bends, and have nothing to do 
with PDL compression.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. Sterile necrotic areas develop in the compressed 
area. These areas often are called hyalinized areas because some early 
observers thought they looked like hyaline cartilage, but cartilage 
doesn&#8217;t form there. Mild pulpitis can occur after activation of 
orthodontic appliances, but there are no necrotic areas in the pulp. 
Persistent piezo-electric signals are seen only during rhythmic function 
as bone bends, and have nothing to do with PDL compression.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-4c.jpg" resourceWidth="579" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-4c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="103" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>When orthodontic appliances are removed, why are retainers needed full-time 
for 3-4 months?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>PDL reorganization takes 3-4 months</choice><choice>most patients are still growing when treatment ends</choice><choice>sometimes teeth have been moved into unstable positions</choice><choice>teeth are particularly likely to move post-treatment as they erupt</choice><choice>all the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. All the response statements are reasons for retention, 
but only the first one is the reason for full-time retention for a few months 
after orthodontic treatment is completed. It takes 3-4 months for the PDL to 
reorganize, and for that length of time the teeth need to be held against soft 
tissue pressures that they may be able to withstand after the reorganization is 
comleted. Growing patients, or patients whose teeth are not in stable 
positions, need long-term retention but can wear retainers only part-time.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. All the response statements are reasons for 
retention, but only the first one is the reason for full-time retention 
for a few months after orthodontic treatment is completed. It takes 3-4 
months for the PDL to reorganize, and for that length of time the teeth 
need to be held against soft tissue pressures that they may be able to 
withstand after the reorganization is comleted. Growing patients, or patients 
whose teeth are not in stable positions, need long-term retention but can wear 
retainers only part-time.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>How many hours a day do you have to wear your removable orthodontic appliance 
in order to gain any treatment effect?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>no minimum, every little bit helps</choice><choice>at least 2 consecutive hours</choice><choice>at least 3-4 hours</choice><choice>at least 4-8 hours</choice><choice>at least 10-12 hours</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, there is a time threshold somewhere between 4-8 hours. 
If you wear your removable appliance that much, some treatment response will 
occur (although if you wore it more there would be a better response). Less 
than 4 hours is likely to produce no response.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. There is a time threshold somewhere between 4-8 hours. 
If you wear your removable appliance that much, some treatment response will 
occur (although if you wore it more there would be a better response). Less 
than 4 hours is likely to produce no response.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-12.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="438" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-12_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="110" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>What&#8217;s the optimal force in grams to intrude a tooth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>approximately 10</choice><choice>approximately 20</choice><choice>approximately 50</choice><choice>approximately 75</choice><choice>approximately 100</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, 10 grams (or even a bit less for a small tooth like a 
lower incisor) is the optimal force for intrusion. The reason, of course, 
is the small PDL area that&#8217;s compressed by an intrusive force.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. 10 grams (or even a bit less for a small tooth 
like a lower incisor) is the optimal force for intrusion. The reason, of 
course, is the small PDL area that&#8217;s compressed by an intrusive force.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-11.jpg" resourceWidth="382" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-11_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="68" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 11</title><pageText><p>How long does it take to generate chemical signals (for example, prostaglandin 
release) when steady orthodontic pressure is applied against a tooth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>a minute or so</choice><choice>5-10 minutes</choice><choice>an hour or so</choice><choice>about 4 hours</choice><choice>could be any of the first three, depending on force magnitude</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. Chemical signals begin to be generated almost immediately 
after fluid is squeezed out of the PDL space and the ligament is compressed, 
because mechanically distorted cells release some of their contents. Within 
one minute the process is well underway. It takes about 4 hours to begin to 
see evidence of secondary messengers that will lead to cell differentiation, 
but release of signals started long before that.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. Chemical signals begin to be generated almost 
immediately after fluid is squeezed out of the PDL space and the ligament 
is compressed, because mechanically distorted cells release some of their 
contents. Within one minute the process is well underway. It takes about 4 
hours to begin to see evidence of secondary messengers that will lead to cell 
differentiation, but release of signals started long before that.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 12</title><pageText><p>(A) Intermittent force from a fixed orthodontic appliance is inevitable 
because (B) there is no such thing as a perfect spring&#8212;they all have 
some decay of the force as teeth move.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, the first statement is false but the second one is true. 
Decay of the force is reflected in whether the force still can be considered 
continuous (doesn&#8217;t go to zero between appointments) or interrupted 
(decays to zero before reactivation). Intermittent force is seen with 
removable appliances, where the force goes to zero when the appliance 
is removed and resumes when it is reinserted.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That&#8217;s wrong. The first statement is false but the second one is 
true. With a fixed appliance, decay of the force is reflected in whether 
the force still can be considered continuous (doesn&#8217;t go to zero 
between appointments) or interrupted (decays to zero before reactivation). 
Intermittent force is seen with removable appliances, where the force goes 
to zero when the appliance is removed and resumes when it is reinserted.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-13c.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="395" thumbnailLocation="biologyorthotx/images/fig_9-13c_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="122" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>