<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<presentation><title>Adjunctive Orthodontic Treatment Procedures</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>William R. Proffit<br/>Dept. of Orthodontics, UNC School of Dentistry</additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/titlepage.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Molar Uprighting</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>One of the most frequently used adjunctive orthodontic procedures is the uprighting and distal movement of a mesially tipped permanent second molar to allow placement of a properly contoured restoration.</p>
<p>Early loss of permanent first molars is much less common now than previously, but fluoridation does not protect against pit and fissure caries, and deep occlusal decay in these teeth can occur before patients are even aware of it. If a first molar must be extracted, mesial drift of the permanent second molar can be expected. The younger the patient when the tooth was removed, the more drift is likely to occur, but even in adults, second molars drift mesially when first molars are lost.</p>
<p>In the mandibular arch, the second molar typically tips mesially, and often spaces develop between the premolars as these teeth drift distally into the extraction site (image 1). Periodontal inflammation and bone loss often occur on the mesial of the tipped second molar. In the maxillary arch, the second molar usually rotates mesiolingually and tips mesially, while spaces open between the premolars. This makes replacement of the missing tooth difficult, but periodontal problems are much less frequent than in the mandibular arch.</p>
<p>Periodontal problems on the mesial of a tipped mandibular second molar occur for two reasons: (1) the area beneath the tipped mesial portion of the crown is difficult to clean and inherently unhealthy, and (2) occlusal forces are not directed along the long axis of the tooth. If a bridge or implant is placed without correcting the position of the tooth, both factors increase the likelihood of periodontal breakdown that may cause the restoration to fail.</p>
<p>The advantages of uprighting the tipped molar and closing spaces between the premolars are better periodontal health and a better long-term prognosis for restorations placed in this area. It is possible to fabricate a bridge without uprighting a tipped abutment molar, but it is very difficult to make a good one (image 2), and the long-term success of an implant-supported crown adjacent to a tipped molar also can be compromised.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="392" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/03_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, loss of first molar</label><caption><p>Typical mesial tipping of mandibular second molar after loss of first molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="465" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/04.jpg" thumbnailWidth="124" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/04_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, bridge on tipped abutment</label><caption><p>Bridge on tipped abutment: periodontal health is compromised.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Molar Uprighting (cont.)</title><pageText><p>When a mandibular second molar has tipped mesially into an old first molar extraction space, the best treatment usually is to extract the third molar and upright the second molar by tipping it distally. This provides space for an appropriately contoured replacement tooth and places occlusal forces more along the long axis of the teeth.</p>
<p>If restorations (crowns/onlays) are needed in what would be the bridge abutment teeth (as they often are), replacing the missing first molar with a bridge pontic can be the best procedure (see images). If restorations are not needed, an implant is often preferred.</p>
<p>The bridge or implant stabilizes the dental occlusion and serves as a permanent retainer to maintain the tooth positions.</p>
<p>For this patient (image 1), the lower second molar was tipped distally after the third molar was extracted (image 2), creating an ideal arrangement for placing a bridge or implant. On the postuprighting radiograph, note the new bone that has filled in on the mesial of the second molar (image 3).</p>
<p>A view of implant-supported crowns to replace missing first molars (in a different patient) can be seen in image 4.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="261" resourceHeight="176" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/05a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="119" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/05a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, pretreatment occlusion</label><caption><p>Dental relationships prior to molar uprighting.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="271" resourceHeight="181" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/05b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/05b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, post-uprighting occlusion</label><caption><p>After molar uprighting, before restorations.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="342" resourceHeight="228" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/05c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/05c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, post-uprighting radiograph</label><caption><p>Radiograph after molar uprighting, showing new bone formation—note the 
old lamina dura at the tip of the arrow and the bone that has filled in as the 
molar was tipped distally.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="427" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/s01_p02_04.jpg" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/s01_p02_04s.jpg"><label>Image 4, implant-supported molar crowns</label><caption><p>Crowns on implants now replace missing first molars for this patient.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Considerations in Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>Three things must be kept in mind when this type of molar uprighting is the plan:</p>
<ul class="spaced"><li>Extraction of the third molar is necessary if significant distal movement of the second molar is to be obtained. If both the second and third molars are to be retained, the technique for uprighting is different (see below).</li>
<li>Adequate anchorage for the uprighting must be obtained. This means that fixed attachments on the molar, canine, and both premolars are necessary, and better control is obtained when a fixed lingual arch from canine to canine is placed (image 1). Typically, a band is placed on the molar to be uprighted (but a bonded tube can be used), bonded brackets are placed on the facial surface of the premolars and canine, and a bonded lingual wire is used to stabilize the position of the canines.</li>
<li>Reduction of the occlusal surface of the molar is necessary as it uprights, to control occlusal interferences (image 2). This also improves the crown-root ratio and decreases stress on the periodontium.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="410" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/s01_p03_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="117" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/s01_p03_01s.jpg"><label>Image 1, fixed appliance for uprighting</label><caption><p>Fixed appliance for molar uprighting: band on molar, bonded brackets on premolars and canines, and a bonded canine-to-canine lingual arch.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="599" resourceHeight="268" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/06b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="74" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/06b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, reduction of uprighted molar</label><caption><p>Reduction of the occlusal surface of the molar improves the crown-root ratio.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Fixed Appliance for Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>The first step in molar uprighting is to place a fixed appliance, either bands or bonded attachments, on the molar and the anchor teeth.</p>
<p>Bonded brackets on the premolars and canine are almost always preferred now. Exactly how they should be placed is determined by the extent to which movement of these anchor teeth is desired (see the Concepts of Adjunctive Treatment module). Marks on the teeth (which can be made intraorally after enamel etching in preparation for bonding) help in orienting the bracket as desired (image 1).</p>
<p>Either a bonded tube (image 2) or a band carrying a welded tube (image 3) can be used on the molar. A bonded tube can be broken off during treatment, so a band is more trouble-free, but the band margins should not extend into periodontally sensitive areas. The more severe the periodontal problems, the more likely a bonded tube would be preferred.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="266" resourceHeight="180" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/07a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/07a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, orientation marks</label><caption><p>Orientation marks help in bonding brackets in the correct location.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="266" resourceHeight="178" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/07b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/07b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, molar uprighting appliance</label><caption><p>Band on molar, with bonded attachments on anchor teeth—note the bonded lingual arch.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="256" resourceHeight="169" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/07c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/07c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, banded molar</label><caption><p>Bonded tube on molar, bonded brackets on canine and premolars.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Step 1 in Mandibular Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>The sequence of treatment requires three steps. The first step to upright the molar, correcting malalignment of the premolars and canines at the same time.</p>
<p>This can be done in three ways: with</p>
<ul class="spaced"><li>a flexible rectangular wire placed in both the premolar brackets and the molar tube (image 1).</li>
<li>a continuous wire that spans the old extraction site and an auxiliary spring (image 2). This requires two tubes on the molar, one used for the auxiliary spring and the other for the main arch wire. It is convenient to have two tubes available routinely on a molar to be uprighted, so that an auxiliary spring can be used if desired.</li>
<li>a wire in the brackets of the anchor teeth that does not span the old extraction site, and an auxiliary uprighting spring (image 3).</li>
</ul><p>The choice is determined by how much change is desired in the position of the anchor teeth, and how severely the molar is tipped. A continuous flexible wire implies that the molar is only mildly tipped. After initial alignment of the anchor teeth, an auxiliary spring often facilitates uprighting the molar, so the first two ways frequently are combined.</p>
<p>An auxiliary spring with a separate anchor segment of rigid wire is indicated when the molar is severely tipped, so that a continuous flexible wire cannot be fitted into both the attachments on the anchor teeth and the molar tube. With this approach, the anchor teeth should be stabilized with a rigid wire before the auxiliary spring is activated.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="241" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/08a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="67" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/08a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, continuous flexible wire</label><caption><p>Continuous flexible wire for alignment/uprighting.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="368" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/08b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="130" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/08b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, continuous wire plus auxiliary spring</label><caption><p>Auxiliary uprighting spring with continuous wire.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="365" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/08c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="131" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/08c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, anchor segment plus auxiliary spring</label><caption><p>Auxiliary spring with separate anchor segment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Step 2 in Mandibular Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>The second step in a typical molar uprighting case is to further open the space of the missing first molar, closing any space between the premolars and moving the second molar more distally. Often it is as important to move the second premolar mesially, closing spaces between the premolars, as it is to move the molar further distally.</p>
<p>This is accomplished with a compressed coil spring over a rigid wire (images 1 and 2). The wire must not fit too tightly in the brackets and molar tube, because it must be able to slide in the attachments. For sliding to occur, there must be at least 0.002 inch clearance between the wire and the attachments—so .020 wire would be the largest that should be used with a .022 edgewise appliance. Often .018 wire is rigid enough, and the additional clearance would facilitate sliding.</p>
<p>Reactivation of the spring can be accomplished by adding a split section of tubing over the arch wire to further compress the spring (image 3). It is not necessary to remove the spring to activate it in this way.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="176" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/09a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="49" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/09a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, compressed coil, diagram</label><caption><p>Compressed coil spring to open space for replacement of the missing molar 
and close spaces between premolars.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="269" resourceHeight="179" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/09b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/09b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, compressed coil, intraoral</label><caption><p>Compressed coil spring over continuous arch wire.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/10.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/10_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, re-activation of coil</label><caption><p>Adding a split spacer as shown in the diagram reactivates the spring without 
having to remove the wire.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Step 3 in Mandibular Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>The third and final step in a typical molar uprighting case is a fixed retainer to maintain the teeth in position until either a bridge or implant can be placed.</p>
<p>This can be done either with a wire for that purpose in the attachments (images 1, 2), or with a wire bonded into shallow intracoronal preparations after the orthodontic appliance has been removed (images 3, 4).</p>
<p>In either case, the bridge or implant will serve as a permanent retainer, and it should be placed as soon as possible. Long delays in placing the permanent retainer can lead to problems.</p>
<p>The two types of fixed retainer are shown diagrammatically in image 5. If retention is continued more than a few weeks, the bonded intracoronal retainer is preferred.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="276" resourceHeight="220" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/11a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="100" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/11a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1 pre-treatment</label><caption><p>Prior to uprighting, third molar already removed.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="288" resourceHeight="230" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/11b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="100" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/11b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2 wire in attachments as retainer</label><caption><p>Wire section in orthodontic appliance as a temporary retainer.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="270" resourceHeight="202" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/11c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/11c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3 pre-treatment</label><caption><p>Prior to treatment, third molar still present.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="306" resourceHeight="197" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/11d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="124" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/11d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4 bonded wire as retainer</label><caption><p>Bonded intracoronal retainer, after removal of appliance.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/12.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/12_s.jpg"><label>Image 5 two types of fixed retainers</label><caption><p>The two types of fixed retainers.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Mesial Root Movement in Mandibular Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>It is much more difficult to move the root of the second molar mesially than to tip the crown distally, but if the third molar is not extracted, some mesial root movement is needed.</p>
<p>This is typically accomplished with a loop in a rectangular arch wire segment. The wire is shaped initially as shown in image 1. When it is placed into the molar tube, a moment is created to tip the crown distally and bring the root mesially (image 2). If the wire is pulled through the distal of the tube and bent over (image 3), the effect is to create a force to prevent the crown from tipping distally. Then the effect is to close the space and bring the root of the second molar mesially--if the premolars are tied together to provide adequate anchorage.</p>
<p>If the molar to be uprighted is severely rotated and tipped, a modification of a loop wire, with the wire inserted into the distal of the molar tube as shown in image 4, can be helpful.</p>
<p>The major advantage of moving the roots of a lower second molar forward is to improve the periodontal condition between the 2nd and 3rd molars. As we have noted previously, this root movement is difficult because remodeling of cortical bone usually is required, and the advantage of retaining the 3rd molar versus removing it and tipping the 2nd molar distally must be evaluated carefully.  </p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="223" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/13a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="62" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/13a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, T-loop before activation</label><caption><p>T-loop spring (typically, 17 x 25 steel wire) before activation.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="207" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/13b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="57" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/13b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, T-loop, activated</label><caption><p>T-loop activated for uprighting by distal tipping of the molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="204" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/13c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="56" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/13c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, T-loop, activated for space closure</label><caption><p>T-loop activated for space closure, with mesial movement of the molar roots.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="237" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/13d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="66" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/13d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, modified loop for rotations</label><caption><p>Modified T-loop with distal insertion, for rotation.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Maxillary Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>A similar approach can be taken to uprighting a mesially tipped maxillary 
second molar. In the upper arch, the additional anchorage of a canine-to-canine 
lingual arch is not needed (and would be highly irritating to the tongue 
if used).</p>

<p>As they drift mesially, upper molars tend to tip less than lower molars 
but rotate more. The details of the uprighting appliance always must be 
modified to deal with the specific clinical situation. Loops in rectangular 
wire, or a superelastic continuous wire, can be used to tip an upper molar 
distal or activated to bring the root mesially.</p>

<p>This patient, who had lost both upper first molars and one second premolar, 
needed uprighting of both second molars in preparation for restorations. 
On the right side, moving the roots of the molar mesially would be desirable 
so as not to increase the already large space. On the left side, tipping 
the molar distally to increase the space and improve its inclination was 
the appropriate goal.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="423" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/15a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="113" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/15a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, occlusal view</label><caption><p>Occlusal view, missing maxillary molars.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="359" resourceHeight="267" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/15b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="108" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/15b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, radiograph, right side</label><caption><p>Radiograph, right side: missing first molar and 2nd premolar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="344" resourceHeight="253" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/15c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="109" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/15c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, radiograph, left side</label><caption><p>Radiograph, left side: missing first molar.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>T-Loops in Uprighting</title><pageText><p>For this patient, T-loops were used bilaterally.</p>
<p>On the left side, after the loop was activated by placing it into the tube on the molar, the end of the wire was bent over so that the crown could not move distally and the roots would move mesially. This is the same type of activation shown in the drawing below, of activating a lower molar uprighting appliance to bring the roots mesially.</p>
<p>On the right side, the end of the loop was not bent over, and then the activation was expressed by tipping the crown distally and opening the space. When a couple is placed against the crown of a tooth, the crown will move more than the root unless movement of the crown is restrained. Thus a T-loop can be used to move either the crown or the root, depending on how it is attached.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/16.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/16_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, uprighting right side</label><caption><p>Uprighting maxillary 2nd molar, mesial root movement: wire activated with 
end bent over at back of molar tube to restrain distal movement of the crown.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/17_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, uprighting left side</label><caption><p>Uprighting maxillary 2nd molar, distal crown tipping: wire activated with molar 
tube free to slide distally along the wire.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Fixed Retainers</title><pageText><p>At the completion of the molar uprighting, which required four months for this patient, fixed retainers in the form of bonded wires were placed (images 1-4).</p>
<p>Retainers of this type are tolerated by patients much better than a palate-covering maxillary removable retainer, and for that reason are much more effective in maintaining the position of the teeth until final restorations can be placed.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="404" resourceHeight="272" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/18a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="119" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/18a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, left side</label><caption><p>Fixed retainer bonded into small occlusal preparations, left side.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="404" resourceHeight="273" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/18b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/18b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right side</label><caption><p>Bonded fixed retainer, right side.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="590" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/18c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="105" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/18c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, occlusal view</label><caption><p>Occlusal view, bilateral fixed retainers.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="207" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/18d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="57" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/18d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, drawing of fixed retainer</label><caption><p>Diagram, intracoronal fixed retainer.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Evaluation of Maxillary Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>For this patient, bridges were placed bilaterally after the maxillary molar uprighting was continued. As part of the restorative phase of treatment, root canal therapy was performed for the right molar and second premolar abutment teeth. </p>
<p>Note that as planned, the space on the left side was opened as the crown of the molar tipped distally, while the inclination of the right molar was improved, but the space remained the same size as the roots moved mesially.</p>
<p>The benefit of the orthodontic treatment was to improve the periodontal prognosis of the abutment teeth, both by creating a better gingival environment and by placing masticatory stresses more along the long axis. Note particularly the improved bone contour on the mesial of the maxillary left 2nd molar.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/19.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/19_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Before/after maxillary molar uprighting: for each side, pretreatment below, 
posttreatment above.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Further Considerations in Molar Uprighting</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Root Paralleling in Molar Uprighting</title><pageText><p>Because research has shown that in the upper arch, healthy alveolar bone can exist even if the second molar and second premolar roots are not parallel, closing space in the upper arch also is more feasible than in the lower arch. The crowns can be brought together with having to move the roots further than the crowns, i.e., the space can be closed without the necessity of paralleling the roots. Almost always, not as much tooth movement is required either to open space in the upper arch (or close it) when a first molar was lost previously. </p>
<p>For this patient who had lost both the upper and lower left first molars years before, uprighting the mandibular second molar by tipping it distally after extraction of the third molar, but closing the molar extraction space in the upper arch, was the treatment plan. That was feasible because the upper molars could be left at a mesially tipped inclination that would not be compatible with periodontal health in the lower arch.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/20.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/20_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Closure of maxillary first molar extraction sites often is more feasible than 
closing mandibular extraction sites.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Molar Uprighting with Posterior Crossbite Correction</title><pageText><p>For this patient, who wanted replacement of a missing lower molar, the situation 
was complicated by a crossbite relationship of the molars in that quadrant. 
Note (image 1) that the lower second molar was rolled to the lingual, 
and the upper second molar was tipped facially, so there was a complete 
buccal crossbite of those teeth.</p>

<p>For this man (age 50), the anterior deep bite was not a problem esthetically, 
and since his periodontal condition was good (i.e., he was tolerating 
the anterior deep bite from the perspective of periodontal health), there 
was no necessity to totally correct the occlusion. His problems were the 
missing lower first molar, the mesially and lingually tipped lower second 
molar, and the molar crossbite. Adjunctive orthodontic treatment appropriately 
would focus on correcting the occlusion so that a satisfactory restoration 
for the missing tooth would be possible.</p>

<p>One approach to correction of a molar crossbite of this type is the use 
of a “through the bite” or cross-elastic, running from the 
mesial of the lower molar to the facial of the upper molar. A cross-elastic 
to correct the more common lingual crossbite is illustrated in image 2. 
Because elastics of this type tend to extrude the teeth as well as move 
them faciolingually, they must be used carefully, but they can be quite 
effective.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="389" resourceHeight="260" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/21a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/21a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, posterior crossbite / tipped molar</label><caption><p>Buccal crossbite of second molars, lower molar uprighting needed to allow 
replacement of missing lower first molar.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="209" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/21b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="37" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/21b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, cross elastics</label><caption><p>Drawing of cross-elastic to correct posterior crossbite.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Molar Uprighting with Posterior Crossbite Correction (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>Uprighting of the lower second molar was done in the usual way, tipping the crown 
distally with a flexible arch wire. In addition, a rubber band from a 
button on the lingual of the lower molar (image 1) to a hook on the facial 
of the upper molar (image 2) was used to tip the upper molar lingually 
and the lower molar facially.</p>

<p>An elastic of this type is called a cross-elastic because it crosses through 
the occlusion. The force was about 100 gm when the jaws were in their 
postural position. Reduction of the cusp height of both teeth was necessary 
to allow the crossbite correction. Normal occlusion on the lower second 
molar bridge abutment was achieved.</p>

<p>With the upper molar brought lingually and the lower molar moved facially 
as well as uprighted, it was possible to bring the posterior teeth into 
good occlusion (image 3), and a fixed bridge was placed with the abutment 
teeth out of crossbite (image 4). The amount of change created by the 
combination of uprighting the lower molar and lingual movement of the 
upper molar can be seen in the composite view (image 5).</p>

<p>This patient could tolerate some extrusion during crossbite correction 
that was compensated by reducing the cusp height of the teeth—but 
not every crossbite patient could, so cross-elastics cannot be used for 
all crossbite conditions.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="366" resourceHeight="210" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/22a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="139" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/22a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, lower band with lingual button</label><caption><p>Lower arch, uprighting with fixed appliance, lingual button on lower molar 
for attachment of cross-elastic.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="366" resourceHeight="244" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/22b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/22b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, upper band with facial hook</label><caption><p>Molar uprighting in lower arch, buccal hook on upper molar band for attachment 
of cross-elastic.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="341" resourceHeight="187" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/22c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="146" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/22c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, orthodontic treatment completed</label><caption><p>Crossbite corrected, upper molar band removed.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="375" resourceHeight="262" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/22d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="115" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/22d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, bridge in place</label><caption><p>Bridge in place, molar uprighted and crossbite eliminated. In this situation, retention of the crossbite correction is needed, and the bridge also serves as a permanent retainer.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/23.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/23_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, overview of treatment</label><caption><p>Composite views, crossbite correction/molar uprighting.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Molar Uprighting: Summary and Conclusions</title><pageText><p>Molar uprighting can improve the periodontal prognosis for teeth adjacent to the missing tooth or teeth, and facilitate restorative procedures. Some important considerations to remember:</p>
<ul class="spaced"><li>a partial fixed appliance almost always is the best method--removable appliances are largely ineffective because they are limited in the type of tooth movement they can produce and are difficult for the patient to tolerate</li>
<li>in the mandibular arch, a bonded canine-to-canine lingual wire increases the anchorage value of a premolars-canine anchorage unit--but this is rarely indicated in the maxillary arch</li>
<li>if a molar to be uprighted is not severely tipped, a continuous flexible archwire segment (usually NiTi wire) is effective</li>
<li>greater tipping of the molar usually is managed best with the use of an auxiliary uprighting spring</li>
<li>crossbite correction with cross-elastics can be done simultaneously with uprighting, but long-term retention is likely to be needed--and a fixed bridge with two abutments is a permanent retainer</li>
<li>mesial root movement to close space can be managed with a T-loop archwire segment, and is easier to accomplish in the maxillary arch, where root inclination is not as critical as in the mandibular arch</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Forced Eruption</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Indications for Forced Eruption</title><pageText><p>If a tooth has a defect in the cervical third of the root (from fracture, resorption, 
decay or periodontal problems), extensive crown lengthening would be necessary 
to gain access for treatment. Poor esthetics and adverse changes in 
the crown-root ratio are likely problems.</p>

<p>For many patients, controlled extrusion (forced eruption) is an excellent alternative. 
It improves endodontic access and can allow crown margins to be placed on sound tooth 
structure while maintaining the gingival contour. Although a tooth with a single 
tapering root is the ideal candidate for extrusion, multirooted teeth 
also can be managed in this way.</p>

<p>The distance of extrusion is determined by</p>

<ul class="spaced"><li>the location of the defect relative to the alveolar crest</li>
<li>space for placement of the restoration margin (1 mm)</li>
<li>allowance for the gingival attachment (2 mm)</li>
</ul><p>For this patient, the crown of a maxillary first premolar fractured beneath a 
restoration, leaving a defect extending 2 mm below the alveolar crest (images 1 
and 2). To prepare this tooth for a new crown, 5 mm extrusion would be needed: 
2 mm to reach the defect, 1 mm to place the restoration margin, and 
2 mm allowance for the gingival attachment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="498" resourceHeight="299" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/24a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/24a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, lateral view</label><caption><p>Fractured crown, defect extends 2 mm below gingival margin.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="338" resourceHeight="266" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/24b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="102" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/24b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, occlusal view</label><caption><p>Fractured crown, defect extends 2 mm below gingival margin.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Forced Eruption</title><pageText><p>Extrusion requires relatively light force (50-100 grams). Too much force can produce tissue damage and ankylosis. A tooth can be extruded at a rate up to 1 mm/week without biologic damage, so a few weeks of treatment time almost always is sufficient.</p>
<p>For this patient, to extrude the damaged premolar, a button was bonded on its occlusal surface, and edgewise brackets were bonded on the adjacent canine and second premolar (image 1). A segment of rectangular wire with a loop that faced downward initially was rotated into position and tied to the button, creating a force of approximately 100 grams to extrude the premolar (image 2). It elongated about 5 mm in as many weeks (images 3 and 4).</p>
<p>Compare the change in position of the fractured tooth over that period of time (image 5). Note that when a tooth is extruded, both bone and gingival tissue tend to come with it.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/25a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/25a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, appliance set-up</label><caption><p>Bonded button on fractured tooth, brackets on adjacent teeth.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/25b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/25b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, extrusion spring</label><caption><p>Extrusion spring rotated into position, tied to button.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="500" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/25c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/25c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, 5 weeks later</label><caption><p>Extrusion completed, 5 weeks later.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="498" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/25d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/25d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, 5 weeks later</label><caption><p>Extrusion completed, 5 weeks later.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/26.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/26_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, change in position</label><caption><p>Change in position with extrusion—note the change in gingival contour as 
well as the change in tooth position.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Forced Eruption (cont.)</title><pageText><p>With the extrusion completed, the brackets and button were removed, and the now-passive spring was bonded directly to serve as a fixed retainer (image 1). An extruded tooth should be held in its new position at least 4 weeks, until the rebound tendency from stretched gingival and periodontal tissues subsides.</p>
<p>Because gingival tissues tend to follow the extruding crown, usually it is necessary to perform a gingivoplasty before a new crown can be placed (image 2). This is much less extensive than a crown-lengthening procedure without the extrusion, however.</p>
<p>At that point a new crown can be placed, with a better crown-root ratio and better gingival contours than would have been the case without the extrusion (images 3 and 4).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/27a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/27a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, bonded retainer</label><caption><p>Spring wire, now passive, bonded as fixed retainer.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="500" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/27b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/27b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, gingivoplasty</label><caption><p>Gingivoplasty before completion of new crown preparation.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/27c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/27c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, new crown, oblique 
      view</label><caption><p>New crown, oblique view—note gingival contours.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="502" resourceHeight="301" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/27d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="133" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/27d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, new crown, lateral view</label><caption><p>New crown, lateral view.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Inter-Arch Elastics for Forced Eruption</title><pageText><p>Sometimes the anchorage for extrusion can be the teeth in the opposite dental arch. This 60-year-old patient fractured off the facial surface of a mandibular first molar, with the fracture line extending subgingivally.</p>
<p>For extrusion of the fractured molar, the maxillary premolars and first molar were bonded, placing the brackets so that a straight wire would fit passively (image 1). The occlusal surface of the fractured tooth was reduced to provide space for extrusion. Then a button was bonded to the fractured lower molar, and a light elastic was used to extrude the tooth (image 2) until the fracture line was accessible. After 4 weeks (image 3), the fracture line was far enough above the alveolar crest that a crown with proper margins could be fabricated.</p>
<p>The force from an interarch elastic is not as constant as from a spring on a fixed appliance. Anything about an orthodontic appliance that can be removed will be—the elastic will not be worn all the time, even by a highly cooperative patient. So the rate of extrusion is less predicable with this method, but it can work very well for a fractured molar.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="389" resourceHeight="252" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/28a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/28a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, appliance set-up</label><caption><p>Button bonded to fractured molar, maxillary segment for anchorage.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="306" resourceHeight="246" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/28b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="100" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/28b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, extrusive elastic in place</label><caption><p>Interarch elastic for extrusion, 100 gm force.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="404" resourceHeight="266" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/28c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="122" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/28c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, 4 weeks later</label><caption><p>Extrusion completed, 4 weeks later.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Forced Eruption to Maintain Bridge Abutment Tooth</title><pageText><p>For this patient in her 60s, the bridge in the maxillary left quadrant was failing, and the canine abutment had cervical decay that extended subgingivally (arrow in image points to the subgingival carious area).</p>
<p>The plan was to</p>
<ul><li>section the bridge, maintaining the molar crown that was the distal abutment of the bridge while removing the pontic and the canine crown</li>
<li>restore the canine temporarily</li>
<li>fabricate a new crown after it was extruded to the point that proper margins could be placed</li>
</ul><p>Extruding the canine would also provide a better crown-root ratio, but the damaged tooth would not be an adequate abutment for a long-span replacement bridge, so an implant in the premolar area to replace the bridge pontic also was planned.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="391" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/29.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/29_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Panoramic radiograph, bridge failure, subgingival decay on maxillary 
left canine.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Forced Eruption to Maintain Abutment Tooth (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The other maxillary teeth were used as anchorage. A tube was bonded to the crown on the molar, brackets were bonded to the incisors and the other canine, and a button was bonded to the temporary amalgam restoration in the canine. A flexible nickel-titanium wire was used to generate the extrusive force (images 1 and 2). As the canine extruded, amalgam from the core of the previous crown was ground away to keep the tooth out of occlusion, and the button was rebonded at a higher level.</p>
<p>After 8 weeks, the button could be bonded on the root surface, and the tooth was extruded to its final position, with the old amalgam core completely removed (image 3). It was held there for a month before the orthodontic appliance was removed. Total elongation was about 6 mm, with treatment time of 3 months.</p>
<p>The panoramic radiograph near the completion of the restorative treatment (image 4) shows the elongated canine with a temporary crown in place and implants replacing the bridge pontic and the right lateral incisor.</p>
<p>Remember that patients with this type of adjunctive orthodontic treatment must be seen every 1-2 weeks to reduce the occlusal surface of the tooth being extruded, control inflammation, and monitor progress. Stabilization for 3-6 weeks after extrusion is completed allows for reorganization of the PDL and minimizes relapse.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="374" resourceHeight="249" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/30a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/30a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, auxiliary spring for extrusion</label><caption><p>Anterior teeth and molar bonded for anchorage, button bonded to amalgam core 
of canine from previous crown preparation.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="354" resourceHeight="227" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/30b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="125" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/30b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, space for extrusion</label><caption><p>NiTi auxiliary spring for extrusion, amalgam core reduced to provide space.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="390" resourceHeight="264" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/30c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/30c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, extrusion completed</label><caption><p>Extrusion completed: 6 mm total elongation.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="403" resourceHeight="203" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/31.jpg" thumbnailWidth="159" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/31_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, post-treatment radiograph</label><caption><p>Post-treatment panoramic radiograph, temporary crown on elongated canine, 
implant in place.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Forced Eruption: Summary and Conclusions</title><pageText><p>Forced eruption as an adjunctive orthodontic procedure:</p>
<ul class="spaced"><li>is indicated as a way to make restoration of fractured teeth possible</li>
<li>usually requires a partial fixed appliance (an exception using magnets in attraction can be seen in Module 23, Biology of Orthodontic Treatment)</li>
<li>should be done using relatively light force (50-100 gm)</li>
<li>occurs at a rate of about 1 mm per week</li>
<li>often requires recontouring the gingiva, and sometimes requires recontouring alveolar bone, after the tooth movement is completed.</li>
</ul><p>One theory of forced eruption has been that it should be done very quickly (in a few days) with heavy force, so that bone and gingiva would not follow the movement of the remaining part of the tooth. This is undesirable because it injures the periodontal support apparatus of a tooth that already has been damaged. That is too high a price to pay for avoiding recontouring of the tissues before a final restoration is placed--and recontouring often is required anyway.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Maxillary Incisor Alignment</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Appliances for Maxillary Incisor Alignment</title><pageText><p>Another frequent indication for adjunctive orthodontics is to prepare for restoration of maxillary incisors. Cosmetic dentistry in this region--for example, the placement of veneers on discolored or fractured teeth--is facilitated by properly aligning the teeth initially.</p>
<p>There are two ways to accomplish this:</p>
<ul class="spaced"><li>bonded brackets, flexible arch wires, and coil springs over the wire to reposition the teeth (image 1); or</li>
<li>a series of transparent plastic aligners (image 2).</li>
</ul><p>At this point, brackets and wires remain the most cost-effective approach. For modest degrees of tooth movement, plastic aligners are a feasible (but expensive) alternative.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="365" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/32a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="131" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/32a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Bonded brackets, wire, and coil springs to open space for build-ups of 
lateral incisors.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="444" resourceHeight="316" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/32b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/32b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Plastic aligners, made by resetting teeth on a dental cast with small movements, are an alternative for minor tooth movements.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Maxillary Incisor Alignment, Fixed Appliance</title><pageText><p>Ed was age 47 when he asked his dentist if it was possible to put crowns 
on his upper incisors to close the large central diastema (image 1), which 
he had never liked. The result of that, however, would be a pair of the 
world’s largest central incisors, hardly an esthetic improvement.</p>

<p>He was told that what he really needed was repositioning of the incisors 
to distribute the space equally among them, then esthetic restorations 
with build-ups of all four maxillary incisors would be possible. He accepted 
that plan, which called for placing a fixed appliance on his upper arch 
only. The estimated orthodontic treatment time was about 6 months. The 
treatment objective was to partially close the large central diastema 
(images 2, 3) by bringing the central incisors closer together, opening 
space mesial and distal to the lateral incisors as this was done, and 
then to restore all four maxillary incisors.</p>

<p>Although his lower incisors were mildly irregular (image 4), this was 
not a problem, either from the point of periodontal maintenance or esthetics, 
and no treatment for the lower arch was planned.</p>

<p>His periodontal health was good, so disease control measures before beginning 
orthodontic treatment were not necessary. But remember that any pathologic 
processes must be brought under control before orthodontics begins.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="316" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/33a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/33a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, smile</label><caption><p>Ed, age 47, pretreatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="400" resourceHeight="235" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/33b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="136" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/33b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, diastema</label><caption><p>Ed, age 47, pretreatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="340" resourceHeight="251" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/34a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="108" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/34a_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, upper arch</label><caption><p>Occlusal view, upper arch: large central diastema, small incisors.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="370" resourceHeight="256" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/34b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="116" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/34b_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, lower arch</label><caption><p>Occlusal view, lower arch: mild crowding, no problem.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Fixed Appliance Treatment</title><pageText><p>For Ed, first molars were banded, and brackets were bonded on all other maxillary teeth except the upper left second premolar. It had a ceramic crown that would be difficult to bond and was not really needed as part of the anchorage unit.</p>
<p>Coil springs on a light steel arch wire were used to obtain the desired spacing of the incisors, which had been determined by the restorative dentist. This was achieved in 5 months. The soft tissues in the midline tolerated the partial closure of the diastema well--but sometimes diastema closure leads to enough tissue reaction to require periodontal surgery. Ed did not need that, though he had been warned that it might be necessary.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="379" resourceHeight="210" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="144" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Repositioning completed, 5 months treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="355" resourceHeight="238" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="119" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right lateral</label><caption><p>Repositioning completed, 5 months treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="337" resourceHeight="201" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, left lateral</label><caption><p>Repositioning completed, 5 months treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="376" resourceHeight="270" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="111" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, maxillary occlusal</label><caption><p>Repositioning completed, 5 months treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/35_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, progress composite</label><caption><p>Repositioning completed, 5 months treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Fixed Appliance Treatment (cont.)</title><pageText><p>When the appliance was removed after 5 months, a thermoplastic suckdown retainer was placed immediately to maintain the teeth in position until the restorations could be placed (image 1).</p>
<p>This retainer looks just like a plastic aligner (shown in this program in the next few screens), and is identical except that it holds the teeth in position rather than moving them a little.</p>
<p>Before the build-ups are done, it is important to evaluate tooth-lip relationships (image 2). For best smile esthetics in this case, it was apparent that slight lengthening of the central incisor crowns was needed, in addition to closing the interproximal spaces.</p>
<p>For Ed, composite plastic build-ups for the four upper incisors were completed a few weeks later (image 3). It is critically important to coordinate the completion of the orthodontics and the restoration of the repositioned teeth. Unless the restorations are placed immediately after the appliance is removed (which often is the best plan), a retainer <b>must</b> be placed immediately, otherwise the teeth will drift.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="381" resourceHeight="212" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/36a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="144" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/36a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, completion of treatment</label><caption><p>Ready for appliance removal, suckdown retainer to be placed immediately.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="402" resourceHeight="238" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/36b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="135" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/36b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, tooth-lip relationships</label><caption><p>4 weeks later, tooth-lip relationships just prior to composite build-ups.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="390" resourceHeight="231" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/36c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="135" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/36c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, build-ups completed</label><caption><p>Same day, build-ups completed.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Retention After Completion of Restorations</title><pageText><p>Ed was very pleased with the change in his smile esthetics (image 1). Restorations alone, without repositioning the incisors first, would not have been nearly as successful.</p>
<p>When a maxillary central disastema is closed, there always is a tendency for it to reopen because the gingival circumferential fiber system is interrupted in the region of a large diastema. Like many adults, Ed did not tolerate a palate-covering maxillary retainer and much preferred a fixed retainer.</p>
<p>There are two ways to make a fixed retainer to hold central incisors together. The first type (image 2), consisting of a rigid bar, is both less effective (more likely to break) and less physiologic (splints the teeth too much).</p>
<p>The better way, bonding the teeth together with a piece of flexible wire, which was done for Ed, is shown in image 3. He will need a retainer of this type indefinitely.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="417" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/37.jpg" thumbnailWidth="115" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/37_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, change in smile esthetics</label><caption><p>Improved smile esthetics, before/after treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="391" resourceHeight="227" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/38a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="138" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/38a_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, rigid bonded retainer</label><caption><p>Fixed retainer, rigid wire: less satisfactory.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="385" resourceHeight="270" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/38b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="114" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/38b_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, flexible bonded retainer</label><caption><p>Fixed retainer, flexible wire: preferred.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Maxillary Incisor Alignment, Removable Aligner</title><pageText><p>An alternative for incisor alignment is a series of plastic aligners. This approach is less effective when space closure is needed (and so wouldn’t have worked as well for Ed, the case immediately above). It is better suited for the correction of mild crowding.</p>
<p>These aligners are made on a series of computer-generated casts, with a small amount of movement of teeth (not more than 0.5-mm increments) between aligners. Each aligner is worn for approximately 2 weeks, then is replaced with the next in a series.</p>
<p>This patient (courtesy Dr. Richard Beane) wanted alignment of her maxillary incisors, which had relapsed into mild crowding after previous orthodontic treatment nearly 20 years ago (images 1, 2).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="389" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/39a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/39a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Pam, age 35, mild relapse into maxillary incisor crowding.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="427" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/39b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="113" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/39b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, occlusal view</label><caption><p>Pam, age 35, mild relapse into maxillary incisor crowding.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Removable Aligner Treatment</title><pageText><p>For this patient, a series of 16 aligners was fabricated using computer technology (image) (at a laboratory cost of $1500). The plan was for the patient to wear each aligner all the time for 2 weeks, then switch to the next one.</p>
<p>In this case, treatment time was just under one year, as opposed to the theoretical 32 weeks, because compliance with wearing the appliance all the time left something to be desired. The treatment sequence depends on completing the movement created by any aligner before proceeding to the next one.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="357" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/40.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/40_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>A series of aligners are worn sequentially full-time for 2 weeks or until 
the appliance is passive.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Removable Aligner Treatment (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The result of treatment was satisfactory alignment of the incisors, as well as correction of the premolar positions.</p>
<p>The last aligner would continue to be worn as a retainer full-time for at least 3 months, then just at night. Maintaining perfect alignment long-term would require long-term retention, and the last aligner would eventually have to be replaced with a new retainer. With multiple teeth involved, a plastic suckdown retainer, essentially identical to the last aligner, would be the best choice.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/41.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/41_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Before (left) and after 11 months of treatment with a series of aligners.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Mandibular Incisor Alignment</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Indications for Mandibular Incisor Alignment</title><pageText><p>Another indication for adjunctive orthodontics is crowding of lower incisors that poses a restorative problem, creates tissue irritation, or is needed to help control periodontal disease.</p>
<p>A key question with crowded lower incisors that require orthodontic alignment is whether extraction of one lower incisor and space closure, or opening space for alignment and restoration of the tooth, is the best plan. The more severe the crowding, the better the final occlusion would be with extraction of one tooth.</p>
<p>Let’s look at a patient in whom restoration of a fractured lower incisor was quite difficult because of malalignment. She wanted something done about the fractured crown, both because of its appearance and because the fractured edge was irritating.</p>
<p>Should the fractured tooth be extracted and the space closed, or should space be opened for better alignment and a successful restoration?</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="352" resourceHeight="420" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/42a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/42a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Sara, age 60, fractured lower incisor = restorative problem.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="353" resourceHeight="420" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/42b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/42b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Sara, age 60, fractured lower incisor = restorative problem.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Planning for Mandibular Incisor Alignment</title><pageText><p>From the perspective of dental esthetics, three lower incisors versus four is not an important issue, but the lower incisors are exposed more in older patients than in younger ones because the upper and lower lips sag downward with aging. So alignment of these teeth can become more important with increasing age.</p>
<p>In addition, in adults, loss of lip support if the incisors are retracted during space closure can increase facial wrinkles and subtly make the patient look older. For esthetics, it’s better to increase lip support than decrease it. Because of the esthetic sensitivity, mandibular incisor alignment can be considered the most difficult and potentially troublesome type of adjunctive treatment.</p>
<p>Note that Sara has mild crowding in the upper arch and more severe crowding in the lower arch. There is a deep bite anteriorly. The maxillary incisors are upright and tipped lingually in a mild Class II, division 2 pattern (although the molar relationship is Class I). She has a fixed bridge replacing a lower premolar and extensive good-quality restorations. She expects the best in dental care.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="344" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/43a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="139" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/43a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Sara, age 60, fractured lower incisor = restorative problem.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="387" resourceHeight="278" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/43b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="111" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/43b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right lateral</label><caption><p>Sara, age 60, fractured lower incisor = restorative problem.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="346" resourceHeight="247" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/43c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/43c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, left lateral</label><caption><p>Sara, age 60, fractured lower incisor = restorative problem.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="483" resourceHeight="345" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/44a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/44a_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, maxillary occlusal</label><caption><p>Mild maxillary incisor crowding, central incisors tipped lingually.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="363" resourceHeight="241" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/44b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/44b_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, mandibular occlusal</label><caption><p>More severe mandibular incisor crowding.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Planning for Mandibular Incisor Alignment (cont.)</title><pageText><p>At age 60, some loss of lip fullness is to be expected (image 1). Sara’s facial proportions and jaw relationships are normal. The appearance of the fractured tooth is a concern, but facial esthetics is not. On the other hand, treatment certainly shouldn’t make her look worse or older.</p>
<p>The panoramic radiograph (image 2) shows extensive restorations (inlays, onlays, and crowns) in good condition, with a fixed bridge replacing a missing mandibular left premolar.</p>
<p>Alveolar bone levels appear normal in both the panoramic radiograph and in recent bitewings (which are needed for patients with restorations—see the radiographic guidelines in Concepts of Adjunctive Treatment). Clinical examination confirmed no evidence of active periodontal disease.</p>
<p>For this patient, either of the treatment approaches (extract the fractured incisor and close space, ending up with three lower incisors; or expand the arches to allow the fractured tooth to be aligned) would change the position of the incisor(s) and affect lip support. So a cephalometric radiograph and tracing (images 3 and 4) are needed to evaluate the esthetic impact of treatment.</p>
<p>Cephalometric analysis confirms that jaw relationships are within normal limits but with a mild skeletal Class II pattern. There is some retrusion of upper incisors (a mild Class II division 2 pattern), and a normal relationship of the mandibular incisors to the chin.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="342" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/45.jpg" thumbnailWidth="140" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/45_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal/profile views</label><caption><p>Frontal/profile views: normal facial proportions, no esthetic problem.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="324" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/46.jpg" thumbnailWidth="148" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/46_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, panoramic radiograph</label><caption><p>Panoramic radiograph, extensive previous restorative treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="459" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/47.jpg" thumbnailWidth="82" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/47_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, lateral ceph</label><caption><p>Cephalometric radiograph.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="404" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/48.jpg" thumbnailWidth="72" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/48_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, ceph tracing/analysis</label><caption><p>Cephalometric tracing: mild Class II division 2 pattern.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Treatment Options: the Patient Decides</title><pageText><p>For Sara, extracting one lower incisor and closing the space would deepen the bite and could lead to tissue damage lingual to the upper incisors. In addition, lip support from the teeth would decrease, which has an aging effect. On the positive side, there would be no need to restore the fractured tooth and no worry about maintaining the restoration long term.</p>
<p>The alternative treatment would be expansion of the lower arch to make room for the fractured incisor, so that it could be restored properly. It would be necessary to correct the lingual tipping of the upper incisors to gain enough overjet to expand the lower arch, so alignment of the upper incisors would be necessary. This would slightly increase lip support and improve dental and facial esthetics. Treatment time would be about the same with both approaches.</p>
<p>Computer predictions help patients understand the esthetic impact of changing jaw or tooth position (image 1). Sara was shown computer image predictions of the effect on her profile of the alternative treatment possibilities, so she could choose between them. This, of course, is her decision--both morally and legally, she is entitled to make the decision.</p>
<p>As the predictions show, for Sara the esthetic impact on the profile of either treatment plan would be subtle, but increased lip fullness makes you look younger—which is as desirable at age 60 as age 40. Smile esthetics also would be better with arch expansion and alignment of the teeth in both arches. Since her primary motivation was esthetics, Sara preferred arch expansion rather than extraction and space closure.</p>
<p>The plan, therefore, was a bonded fixed appliance for both arches. Because of the deep bite, only the upper arch was bonded initially, and the upper incisors were tipped facially to create some overjet. Then the lower arch was bonded, and space was opened so that the crowded incisors could be aligned. Since major tooth movement was not required in the upper arch, clear brackets were satisfactory for treatment and were more esthetic.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/49.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/49_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Treatment Completion</title><pageText><p>The orthodontic treatment required 6 months. As anticipated, expansion of the maxillary incisor segment gave space to expand the mandibular incisor area, and produced excellent occlusion and incisor function. The rotated mandibular right canine was not corrected because a preliminary set-up of the teeth showed that there was not quite enough space to allow this.</p>
<p>She was referred for restoration of the fractured lower incisor immediately after braces were removed, and wore plastic suckdown retainers in both arches until the restoration could be accomplished. Then a clip-on lower retainer was used, and the suckdown retainer for the upper arch was continued at night for a few months.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="362" resourceHeight="241" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/50a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/50a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Sara, completion of orthodontic and restorative treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="360" resourceHeight="263" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/50b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="110" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/50b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, right lateral</label><caption><p>Sara, completion of orthodontic and restorative treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="360" resourceHeight="263" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/50c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="110" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/50c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, left lateral</label><caption><p>Sara, completion of orthodontic and restorative treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="358" resourceHeight="242" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/51a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/51a_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, maxillary occlusal</label><caption><p>Sara, completion of orthodontic and restorative treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="320" resourceHeight="230" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/51b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="111" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/51b_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, mandibular occlusal</label><caption><p>Sara, completion of orthodontic and restorative treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Post-Treatment Esthetics</title><pageText><p>Dental and facial esthetics were satisfactory after restoration of the incisor, which took place a few weeks after the orthodontic appliance was removed (images 1-4). In this case, both better occlusion and better esthetics were accomplished with arch expansion rather than extraction of the fractured incisor, at the cost of one more restoration to be maintained. Treatment time would have been the same or longer with extraction, and the cost of the two possible orthodontic approaches also would be quite similar.</p>
<p>It came down to understanding what the patient wanted, offering her alternatives that she understood, and letting her make an informed decision (see Concepts of Adjunctive Treatment).</p>
<p>It is interesting to compare the computer image prediction, which was based on predicted changes in incisor position on the cephalometric tracing, to the real profile posttreatment (image 5).</p>
<p>Computer image predictions are not perfect, but if done carefully can be quite close to reality. It’s one thing to explain to a patient what the effect of treatment is likely to be, and something else to show them a picture. Patients like the feeling of better communication that seeing the predictions provides, and there is minimal risk that they will think the reality is not as good as the prediction.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="394" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/52a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/52a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal, smile</label><caption><p>Sara, facial appearance at completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="374" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/52b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="66" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/52b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, frontal, relaxed</label><caption><p>Sara, facial appearance at completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="363" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/53a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="65" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/53a_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, oblique, smile</label><caption><p>Sara, facial appearance at completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="361" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/53b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="64" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/53b_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, profile, relaxed</label><caption><p>Sara, facial appearance at completion of treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/54.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/54_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, prediction versus actual profile</label><caption><p>Predicted profile compared to actual posttreatment profile.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Retention After Mandibular Incisor Alignment</title><pageText><p>Whenever incisors are repositioned in adults, retainers are needed. Sara had a suckdown upper retainer (similar to the removable aligner, but passive) and an acrylic-wire clip-on lower retainer.</p>
<p>For Sara, the lower retainer will be worn just at night, indefinitely. It has two purposes:</p>
<ol class="spaced"><li>maintaining the lower incisor alignment, and</li>
<li>controlling the overbite, as the facial aspect of this retainer is contoured to do.</li>
</ol><p>After the teeth have stabilized initially, preventing the bite from deepening also will maintain the alignment of the upper incisors, so an upper retainer is not needed long term. She discarded it after 4 months.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="398" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/55b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/55b_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, lower retainer, occlusal</label><caption><p>Mandibular clip-on retainer.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="398" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/55a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/55a_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, lower retainer, frontal</label><caption><p>Mandibular clip-on retainer.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Mandibular Incisor Alignment (cont'd.)</title><pageText><p>Comparison of smile esthetics from before to after treatment shows the 
improvement that was achieved.</p>

<p>Note that there were two components to the esthetic change:</p>

<ul class="spaced"><li>restoration of the fractured incisor, and</li>
<li>improved lip support.</li>
</ul><p>Adjunctive treatment to change incisor positions must always take both 
into account.</p>

<p>In modern dentistry, adjunctive orthodontic treatment offers the possibility 
of better management of other dental problems. For that reason, adjunctive 
orthodontics for adults is a rapidly growing part of clinical treatment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="350" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/56.jpg" thumbnailWidth="137" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/56_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Smile before treatment and six months later.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Conclusions</title><pageText><p>Mandibular incisor alignment in adults:</p>
<ul class="spaced"><li>is one of the more difficult adjunctive treatment procedures.</li>
<li>in a patient with severe incisor crowding and a fractured or endodontically-involved incisor, extraction and space closure can be the most effective treatment.</li>
<li>non-extraction alignment of less severely crowded lower incisors often requires repositioning of the upper incisors as well,</li>
<li>whatever the type of treatment in an adult, long-term retention will be needed. Initially, a suckdown retainer can be satisfactory; in the long-term, either a clip-on removable retainer or a bonded lingual flexible wire performs better</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Summary of Adjunctive Treatment</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Summary: Molar Uprighting, Crossbite Correction</title><pageText><p>There are five major types of adjunctive orthodontic treatment for adults:</p>
<p>1. Uprighting of drifted molars to facilitate restorations</p>
<ol><li>Distal tipping of crowns—the preferred method in the lower arch, and usually in the upper arch as well; requires removal of third molar if second molar is to move significantly distally</li>
<li>Three steps:<ol><li>align/upright: active, flexible arch wires; with or without auxiliary spring</li>
<li>consolidate space: coil spring on rigid wire</li>
<li>retention: bonded intracoronal wire</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Mesial movement of roots—difficult but possible, more feasible in the upper arch because root paralleling is not as critical; allows retention of third molar</li>
</ol><p>2. Correction of posterior crossbite, also to facilitate restorations</p>
<ol><li>Cross-elastics are effective, if some extrusion of the teeth can be tolerated</li>
<li>The alternative is an active arch wire (see Chapter 20, <i>Contemporary Orthodontics</i>)</li>
</ol></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary: Extrusion, Maxillary Incisor Alignment</title><pageText><p>The five major types of adjunctive orthodontic treatment for adults:</p>
<p>3. Extrusion of fractured teeth, an alternative to crown-lengthening surgery that may produce an esthetic problem</p>
<ol><li>How far do you have to extrude?<ol><li>enough movement to bring the fracture line to the surface</li>
<li>an additional 1 mm for placement of the gingival margin of the restoration</li>
<li>an additional 2 mm for gingival contours</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Requires a bonded attachment (usually a button rather than a bracket) on the tooth to be extruded</li>
<li>Anchor teeth can be adjacent (usually preferred) or in the opposite arch (requires use of vertical elastics)</li>
</ol><p>4. Alignment of maxillary incisors, usually to redistribute spaces in preparation for build-ups</p>
<ol><li>Fixed appliance with bonded brackets and coil springs: the usual method</li>
<li>Removable aligners: a new method involving computer-generated casts on which a sequence of aligners can be made</li>
</ol></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary: Mandibular Incisor Alignment</title><pageText><p>The five major types of adjunctive orthodontic treatment for adults:</p>
<p>5. Alignment of mandibular incisors, usually for the correction of crowding</p>
<ol><li>One possibility: extraction of one incisor and space closure<ol><li>may or may not be compatible with good occlusion</li>
<li>reduces lip support, may tend to make the patient look subtly older</li>
</ol></li>
<li>The other possibility: arch expansion<ol><li>likely to require treatment of both the upper and lower arch</li>
<li>esthetic considerations are the key in this decision</li>
</ol></li>
<li>This is the most difficult and potentially troublesome of the adjunctive procedures</li>
</ol><p>Adjunctive orthodontics is an increasingly important of comprehensive treatment for adults, with the potential to improve periodontal health and improve the quality of restorative dentistry.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Self-Test Referral</title><pageText><p>The self-test section of this program is designed to help you be sure you have understood the material. Read the section on adjunctive treatment in adults in <i>Contemporary Orthodontics</i> (5th ed., pages 627-637; 4th ed., pages 639-651). Then take the self-test, and use it as a guide for further study and review.</p>
<p>Copyright 2013, UNC Dept. of Orthodontics</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>(A) Unlike other types of tooth loss, first molars still are lost to caries 
as frequently as ever because (B) Fluoridation does not protect against 
pit and fissure caries that can lead to pulpal involvement.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct, the first statement is false, but the second one is true. First 
molars are not lost nearly as frequently as they were 50 years ago, even 
though fluoridation does not protect against the occlusal decay in pits 
and fissures that is the usual reason these teeth once were extracted. More 
children now are seen by dentists before the tooth becomes an emergency 
and have pit and fissure sealants or restorations.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The first statement is false, but the second one is 
true. First molars are not lost nearly as frequently as they were 50 years 
ago, even though fluoridation does not protect against the occlusal decay 
in pits and fissures that is the usual reason these teeth once were extracted. 
More children now are seen by dentists before the tooth becomes an emergency 
and have pit and fissure sealants or restorations.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="431" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/58.jpg" thumbnailWidth="77" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/58_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>When a mandibular second molar is to be uprighted, which of the following are 
reasons for extracting the third molar in that quadrant before doing the 
uprighting?</p>

<p>
a. Improves the periodontal prognosis for the second molar<br/>
b. Makes it possible to tip the crown distally rather than moving the roots 
mesially<br/>
c. Eliminates occlusal interferences from the opposing upper molars<br/>
d. Eliminates the need to use fixed appliances because less anchorage is 
required
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>c and d</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the first two statements are correct, the other two are not. Removing 
the third molar makes it possible to reduce or eliminate the pocket usually 
found on the mesial of a tipped lower molar as it is uprighted and may improve 
the periodontal condition on the distal as well. But uprighting does not 
eliminate occlusal interferences. Usually it is necessary to reduce the 
crown height to control interferences when a molar is uprighted. Because 
anchorage is important, this type of movement almost always requires a fixed 
appliance. With removable appliances, there are both biomechanical and compliance 
problems. The removable appliances don’t work very well, and adults 
won’t wear them very well anyway.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The first two statements are correct, the other two 
are not. Removing the third molar makes it possible to reduce or eliminate 
the pocket usually found on the mesial of a tipped lower molar as it is 
uprighted and may improve the periodontal condition on the distal as well. 
But uprighting does not eliminate occlusal interferences. Usually it is 
necessary to reduce the crown height to control interferences when a molar 
is uprighted. Because anchorage is important, this type of movement almost 
always requires a fixed appliance. With removable appliances, there are 
both biomechanical and compliance problems. The removable appliances don’t 
work very well, and adults won’t wear them very well anyway.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="344" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/59.jpg" thumbnailWidth="61" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/59_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>Which of the following are appropriate ways to upright a mesially tipped 
lower molar?</p>

<p>
a. Flexible rectangular wire in premolar brackets and molar tube <br/>
b. Auxiliary spring and continuous wire in brackets and tube <br/>
c. Segmented wire in brackets and auxiliary spring to molar tube<br/>
d. Elastics from the upper molar on the same side to the tipped lower molar
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice><choice>c and d</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the first three methods are appropriate for uprighting. An elastic 
from the upper molar to the lower one is a way to correct a crossbite relationship 
but is not effective for correction of mesial tipping.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The first three methods are appropriate for uprighting. 
An elastic from the upper molar to the lower one is a way to correct a crossbite 
relationship but is not effective for correction of mesial tipping.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="277" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/08.jpg" thumbnailWidth="49" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/08_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>Which of the following are characteristics of cross-elastics to correct posterior 
crossbite?</p>

<p>
a. Pull the teeth across the line of occlusion<br/>
b. Extrude the teeth to which they attach<br/>
c. Require extremely high force<br/>
d. May create a need to eliminate occlusal interferences
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice><choice>a, b, and d</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, cross-elastics pull the teeth across the occlusion, also extrude 
the teeth to which they are attached, and for that reason may create a need 
to eliminate occlusal interferences—but they don’t require extremely 
high force. In fact, if very high force is used, the undesirable extrusive 
effect is magnified more than the desired crossbite correction, so very 
high force is a mistake.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. Cross-elastics pull the teeth across the occlusion, 
also extrude the teeth to which they are attached, and for that reason may 
create a need to eliminate occlusal interferences—but they don’t 
require extremely high force. In fact, if very high force is used, the undesirable 
extrusive effect is magnified more than the desired crossbite correction, 
so very high force is a mistake.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/60.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/60_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>Which of the following are indications for the use of a T-loop appliance in 
uprighting a mesially tipped maxillary molar?</p>

<p>
a. Need to tip the crown distally<br/>
b. Need to bring the roots mesially<br/>
c. Tooth in crossbite<br/>
d. Extensive bone loss around anchor teeth
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>a and c</choice><choice>b and d</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct, a T-loop appliance is appropriate both for distal tipping of the 
crown of a molar that needs uprighting or for mesial movement of the roots 
of the teeth. For distal tipping, the distance from the anchor teeth is 
allowed to increase, so that the crown can move distally. For mesial root 
movement, the loop is restrained so that the crown cannot move distally. 
This loop design is not effective for crossbite correction, however, and 
bone loss is not an indication for its use.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. A T-loop appliance is appropriate both for distal tipping 
of the crown of a molar that needs uprighting or for mesial movement of 
the roots of the teeth. For distal tipping, the distance from the anchor 
teeth is allowed to increase, so that the crown can move distally. For mesial 
root movement, the loop is restrained so that the crown cannot move distally. 
This loop design is not effective for crossbite correction, however, and 
bone loss is not an indication for its use.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/61.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/61_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>(A) In occlusal rehabilitation it is particularly important to upright tipped 
maxillary second molars rather than closing the old first molar extraction 
site because (B) Unless there is good root parallelism at an old maxillary 
first molar extraction site, periodontal problems are inevitable.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, both these statements are false. Good periodontal health is more 
likely around a tipped maxillary than mandibular second molar. Closing a 
maxillary molar extraction site, therefore, is more likely to be a feasible 
treatment choice. Uprighting maxillary molars usually is indicated for better 
restorations, not for better periodontal health.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. Both these statements are false. Good periodontal 
health is more likely around a tipped maxillary than mandibular second molar. 
Closing a maxillary molar extraction site, therefore, is more likely to 
be a feasible treatment choice. Uprighting maxillary molars usually is indicated 
for better restorations, not for better periodontal health.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/20.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/20_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is the most time-efficient way to obtain the desired 
spacing of maxillary incisors before restorations are placed?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>Modified Hawley retainer with finger springs</choice><choice>Fixed functional appliance (like the Herbst appliance)</choice><choice>A series of suckdown plastic aligners</choice><choice>Bonded brackets with full-dimension superelastic arch wires</choice><choice>Bonded brackets with undersized rigid wires and coil springs</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct. A fixed appliance with bonded brackets, undersized rigid wires 
(so the teeth can slide as needed along the arch wire), and coil springs 
is the most time-efficient way to position maxillary incisors. This is very 
difficult with full-dimension arch wires of any material, because of friction 
between the wire and the bracket. It can be done with a series of plastic 
aligners, but that takes longer, so this method is not as time-efficient. 
Neither a fixed functional appliance nor a modified retainer with finger 
springs is an effective way to accomplish the precise spacing needed in 
preparation for restorations.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. A fixed appliance with bonded brackets, undersized rigid 
wires (so the teeth can slide as needed along the arch wire), and coil springs 
is the most time-efficient way to position maxillary incisors. This is very 
difficult with full-dimension arch wires of any material, because of friction 
between the wire and the bracket. It can be done with a series of plastic 
aligners, but that takes longer, so this method is not as time-efficient. 
Neither a fixed functional appliance nor a modified retainer with finger 
springs is an effective way to accomplish the precise spacing needed in 
preparation for restorations.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/32.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/32_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>After closure of a maxillary central diastema, what is the most effective 
method for the long-term retention that almost always is required?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>Flexible bonded wire</choice><choice>Rigid bonded wire</choice><choice>Removable plastic aligner</choice><choice>Hawley retainer</choice><choice>Doesn’t matter, long-term retention isn’t needed after restorations are placed</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, a flexible bonded wire on the lingual of the incisors is the most 
effective method. A rigid bonded wire is more likely to break. Any removable 
appliance tends not to be worn as much or as consistently as needed to keep 
the midline space from reopening enough to be noticeable, so a fixed retainer 
is preferred.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s incorrect. A flexible bonded wire on the lingual of the incisors 
is the most effective method. A rigid bonded wire is more likely to break. 
Any removable appliance tends not to be worn as much or as consistently 
as needed to keep the midline space from reopening enough to be noticeable, 
so a fixed retainer is preferred.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/38.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/38_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>When a series of plastic aligners are used to reposition teeth, how much 
can any tooth be moved relative to the ones adjacent to it with any one aligner?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>0.25 mm</choice><choice>0.5 mm</choice><choice>0.75 mm</choice><choice>1 mm</choice><choice>2 mm, but only with computer technology</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, 0.5 mm is about as much movement as can be produced with reasonable 
control with a single aligner—which is why a large number of aligners 
often are needed for a course of treatment.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. 0.5 mm is about as much movement as can be produced 
with reasonable control with a single aligner—which is why a large 
number of aligners often are needed for a course of treatment.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="357" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/40.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/40_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>Which of the following are potential problems in correcting crowded lower 
incisors by extracting one incisor and closing the space?</p>

<p>
a. Creation of excess overjet<br/>
b. Deepening of the bite anteriorly<br/>
c. Decrease in lip support that accentuates facial wrinkles<br/>
d. TMD because of increased bruxism
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice><choice>b, c, and d</choice><choice>all of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the first three statements are correct, but the last one isn’t. 
If only one lower incisor is extracted, overjet is likely to increase, and 
this can be a problem in some patients. Extraction of one incisor also tends 
to deepen the bite anteriorly, and it can increase the prominence of facial 
wrinkles by decreasing lip support. These are potential problems, but not 
things that are inevitable—they don’t occur in patients correctly 
selected for this treatment. Extraction of one lower incisor has nothing 
to do with TMD due to bruxism. This extraction pattern, like other orthodontic 
extractions, is unlikely to either cause or cure TMD.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. The first three statements are correct, but the last 
one isn’t. If only one lower incisor is extracted, overjet is likely 
to increase, and this can be a problem in some patients. Extraction of one 
incisor also tends to deepen the bite anteriorly, and it can increase the 
prominence of facial wrinkles by decreasing lip support. These are potential 
problems, but not things that are inevitable—they don’t occur 
in patients correctly selected for this treatment. Extraction of one lower 
incisor has nothing to do with TMD due to bruxism. This extraction pattern, 
like other orthodontic extractions, is unlikely to either cause or cure 
TMD.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="366" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/42.jpg" thumbnailWidth="131" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/42_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 11</title><pageText><p>Which of the following are <b>not</b> effective orthodontic appliances in 
nonextraction alignment of crowded lower incisors?</p>

<p>
a. Fixed functional appliance (like Herbst appliance)<br/>
b. Aseries of suckdown plastic aligners<br/>
c. Bonded brackets with full-dimension superelastic arch wires<br/>
d. Bonded brackets with undersized wires and coil springs
</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>a and b</choice><choice>b and c</choice><choice>a and c</choice><choice>b and d</choice><choice>a, b, and c</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, a fixed functional appliance is not an effective way to correct 
crowded lower incisors (totally inappropriate in fact—such appliances are 
used in children to guide jaw growth, and crowding of lower incisors is 
a possible side effect). Neither is a fixed appliance with a full-dimension 
wire (because that makes sliding teeth along the arch wire almost impossible, 
and teeth need to slide to open up space). Plastic aligners are effective 
but slow and expensive. The best approach is bonded brackets, undersized 
arch wires, and coil springs.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. a fixed functional appliance is not an effective way 
to correct crowded lower incisors (totally inappropriate in fact—such 
appliances are used in children to guide jaw growth, and crowding of lower 
incisors is a possible side effect. Neither is a fixed appliance with a 
full-dimension wire (because that makes sliding teeth along the arch wire 
almost impossible, and teeth need to slide to open up space). Plastic aligners 
are effective but slow and expensive. The best approach is bonded brackets, 
undersized arch wires, and coil springs.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/63.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/63_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 12</title><pageText><p>(A) After crowded lower incisors in an adult have been aligned by expanding 
the arch, a retainer usually is needed long term because (B) Teeth with 
decreased alveolar bone height in an adult are less stable and more likely 
to relapse after orthodontic tooth movement.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct, both these statements are true, but they aren’t related. 
After expansion to align the lower incisors, a retainer would be needed 
long-term whether bone loss had occurred or not, because the pattern of 
lip-tongue pressures that determines the position of incisors would not 
change after treatment in an adult. That’s why long-term retention 
is needed to keep the teeth aligned. A wire and plastic clip-on retainer 
like this one often is the best choice for long-term retention of lower 
incisors in a cooperative adult.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. Both these statements are true, but they aren’t related. After 
expansion to align the lower incisors, a retainer would be needed long-term 
whether bone loss had occurred or not, because the pattern of lip-tongue 
pressures that determines the position of incisors would not change after 
treatment in an adult. That’s why long-term retention is needed to 
keep the teeth aligned. A wire and plastic clip-on retainer like this one 
often is the best choice for long-term retention of lower incisors in a 
cooperative adult.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/55.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="adjunctprocedures/images/55_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>