<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<presentation><title>The Study of Physical Growth</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>William R. Proffit<br/>
Dept. of Orthodontics, UNC School of Dentistry<br/></additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/titlepage.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Growth vs. Development</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Growth</title><pageText><p>If you are not careful&copy;&#189;&amp;, the very word &#8220;growth&#8221; can cause some 
difficulties.</p>

<p>Growth certainly refers to an increase in size, but it&#8217;s more that that. 
More than anything else, growth indicates change&#8212;which is why it&#8217;s 
possible sometimes to speak of negative growth.</p>

<p>Development indicates new capabilities, often bigger and better, perhaps at some 
cost. In this course on growth an development, it&#8217;s important to distinguish 
these terms.</p>

<p>For our use:</p>

<p>Growth, most of the time, will refer to a change, almost always an increase, in 
size or number, generally with an anatomic reference. Occasionally, however, it will be 
used to indicate more of an increase in complexity than size.</p>

<p>Development will be used primarily to refer to an increase in complexity&#8212;especially 
when this carries with it an overtone of specialization and loss of potential.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_04.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="262" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_04_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="73"><label>Test label <b>dsfjslkfjslkdfj</b></label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_05.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_05_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth / Development: Why?</title><pageText><p>As a dental student, why should you study growth and development?</p>

<p>There are two important reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>You have to understand normal dental, facial and psychosocial growth 
and development to work with children. You can't distinguish the abnormal 
from the normal if you don't understand the normal pattern of development.</li>
<li>The dentist can manipulate growth to some extent, and it is important 
to do so in treating developmental problems in children. For example, 
headgear devices, like the ones shown here often are used to treat 
problems like protruding upper teeth and the deficient lower jaw that 
often is a major part of the problem.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_06.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="382" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_06_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="126" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Concepts of Pattern, Variability and Timing</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Pattern</title><pageText><p>Let's start with the important concept of growth pattern. Think about the 
pattern for an article of clothing. As the pattern increases in size, there are 
changes in some areas that are larger or smaller than changes in other 
areas&#8212;it isn't just blown up like a balloon. In this way, the pattern 
reflects a complex set of proportional relationships.</p>

<p>Pattern in growth is a higher level pattern, a step beyond the pattern that 
gets clothes to fit or describes body proportions at any one time. It refers to 
the predictable changes in body proportions over time as the individual grows.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_01.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="173" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_01_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="48"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Pattern: Proportion Changes</title><pageText><p>There are striking changes in body proportions over time.</p>

<p>Note that at the end of the second month in utero, the head and face comprise almost 
50% of the total body length. In contrast, the limbs are still rudimentary and the trunk 
underdeveloped. It may seem strange that at one time your nose was as big as your hand, but 
that was the case in early life.</p>

<p>The proportion of total body size contributed by the head and face steadily decreases 
after the 3rd month of fetal lfe. By the time of birth, greater growth of the truck and 
limbs has reduced the head to 25% of the entire body. This pattern continues, so that the 
head and face contribute proportionally less and less to the total body length. This relative 
reduction in head and face size is because the craniofacial structures developed earlier. In 
later growth, structures away from the head grow more to catch up. This is called the 
cephalocaudal gradient of growth, and it's an important part of the growth pattern that 
you need to always keep in mind.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="357" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Pattern: Cephalocaudal Gradient</title><pageText><p>Even within the head and face, the cephalocaudal gradient of growth leads to changes 
in proportionality during growth. When the skull of a newborn is compared to that of an 
adult, it is easy to see that postnatally there's relatively more growth of the face than 
the cranium. This reflects the early growth of the nervous system. The cranium, the part 
of the head that serves as a housing for the brain, must grow rapidly early on, and grows 
less later.</p>

<p>Within the face, structures closer to the brain grow more earlier and less later. Thus 
the mandible is less developed at an early point than the maxilla and grows more postnatally.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_04.jpg" resourceWidth="593" resourceHeight="284" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_04_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Variability</title><pageText><p>Now let's turn to the concept of variability. Obviously, everyone is not alike in the 
way they grow. In dealing with a child, you'll need to know if the size (growth) or development 
stage (complexity) is normal. How would you determine that?</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_05.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_05_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Variability: Distributions</title><pageText><p>Normal variation leads to the well-known bell-shaped curve in the distribution 
of individuals within a group, so that most individuals cluster near 
a midpoint and few are found at the extremes. The bigger the group, 
the more obvious the clustering near the mean. Notice what happens when 
heights are plotted for these two groups.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_06plus07.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="317" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_06plus07_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="151" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Variability: Distributions (cont.)</title><pageText><p>There are several ways to express the distribution of values within a group:</p>

<ul>
<li>The <b>range</b> is from the smallest to the largest value.</li>
<li>The <b>mean</b> is the arithmetic average.</li>
<li>The <b>standard deviation </b>is calculated from a mathematical formula is a 
way to describe the variability.</li>
</ul>

<p>One standard deviation encompasses 67% of the people in a normal distribution, two 
S.D. includes 95% and three S.D. includes 99%. In the two groups shown here, the larger 
standard deviation on the left implies greater variability&#8212;but the number of 
individuals in the group can affect the values. With only a few individuals, each one 
heavily influences the values, and the standard deviation for a small group is likely 
to be large. Larger samples give more reliable data for mean and S.D.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_08plus09.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="331" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_08plus09_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="145" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Variability: Distributions (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Another way to describe the central tendency of a group is to use the median, 
or middle person in each distribution. Usually the median is less sensitive to one 
or two individuals at the extremes. Often it is better descriptor of small samples, 
as you see here.</p>

<p>Percentiles also can be used to note where an individual stands relative to his 
or her peers.</p>

<p>The middle of a distribution is the 50th percentile. At the 20th percentile, 80% 
of the group are taller than that individual. At the 90th percentile, only 10% would be taller.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_08plus09.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="331" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_08plus09_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="145" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Variability: Growth Charts</title><pageText><p>Growth charts, expressed in percentiles, often are used to show how a patient 
compares to his or her peers  in height and weigh, and how that  changes over 
time. The lines indicate the percentiles, the x axis is time and the y axis indicates 
height or weight. The charts for boys and girls are different (although the differences 
are surprisingly small prior to adolescence).</p>

<p>For this normal girl, height and weight values plot consistently near the 50th percentile, 
but normal variation is relatively large. As a general guideline, a child who is between the 
3rd and 97th percentiles is considered within the normal range. Outside that, abnormality must 
be suspected.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1.jpg" resourceWidth="321" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Variability: Growth Charts (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Normal growth is shown on a growth chart not so much by being at the 50th 
percentile, as by maintaining about the same percentile over time. A child who plots 
at the 20th percentile consistently is just a small but normal child.</p>

<p>Crossing the percentiles, particularly crossing several of them, usually indicates 
abnormal growth and some problem. In this respect, height is a more sensitive indicator 
than weight.</p>

<p>Here we see the plot for a boy who developed a medical problem that affected growth at 
age 10, with partial recovery at age 13, but a long-term growth deficit.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart2.jpg" resourceWidth="318" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart2_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Variability: Other Charts</title><pageText><p>Many body dimensions, not just height and weight, can be plotted against time to see if 
growth is normal.</p>

<p>This graph shows the change in the height of the face for boys and girls, based on 
measurements from radiographs.</p>

<p>You could check your patient's face height, and its change over time, against a 
standard graph of this type. Note that there's a different value for boys and girls, and 
the male-female difference gets larger as the children get older.</p>

<p>This is largely due to variations in timing,which is the next concept to be discussed.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/mgs188.jpg" resourceWidth="327" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/mgs188_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="58" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Timing: Description</title><pageText><p>Boys and girls get bigger over time, of course, but differences between individuals of the 
same age and gender, and differences between the sexes, are most notable near adolescence. 
That is because sexual maturation leads to an adolescent growth spurt. This happens at a 
different time in girls and boys and happens at different times in individuals of the same 
gender. On the average, girls have their adolescent growth spurt 2 years ahead of boys. That 
doesn't mean that all girls mature faster than all boys--there's too much individual variation 
for that to be true.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/concept-timing.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/concept-timing_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Timing: Description (cont.)</title><pageText><p>This diagram plots the increase in height each year for three girls, who experienced 
a growth spurt at different times because of a difference in timing of sexual maturation. 
M-1, M-2 and M-3 show for each girl the age (age range between measurements) at which menses 
began (called menarche). Note that the rate of growth for each girl was declining by then.</p>

<p>Sometimes differences in the timing of puberty, whether an individual matures unusually 
early or late, causes him or her to cross percentile lines during adolescence. This should not be 
considered an indication of a growth problem, especially if the plot for the early or late 
maturing preson returns toward the range where it was initially.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic2.jpg" resourceWidth="460" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic2_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="82" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Timing: Chronologic vs. Biologic Age</title><pageText><p>Because of timing variability, chronologic age often is not a good indicator of an 
individual's growth status. It is possible to measure age biologically, in terms of 
progress towards achievement of certain development markers. For dentists and 
orthodontists, a good way to do this is to use the cervical vertebrae, which are seen 
in the cephalometric radiographs that are obtained for most orthodontic patients.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/timing-chrono1.jpg" resourceWidth="563" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/timing-chrono1_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="100" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/timing-chrono2.jpg" resourceWidth="563" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/timing-chrono2_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="100" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Timing: Chronologic vs. Biologic Age (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The stages in maturation of the cervical vertebrae correlate well with the adolescent growth spurt, 
which is the best time for most orthodontic treatment. Stage 2 indicates that peak growth at 
adolescence is still a year or so ahead. Stage 3 indicates that it is less than one year to 
peak growth, a good place to begin treatment. Stages 4, 5 and 6 are increasing distances 
beyond peak growth.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/timing-chrono3.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="234" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/timing-chrono3_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="65"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Timing: Biologic Age</title><pageText><p>These biologic ages also could be called developmental or maturation ages. Many different 
types of maturation, not just the skeletal age calculated from vertebrae or other skeletal 
indicators, can be determined and quantified in biologic terms. Dentists use dental age all 
the time, judging the state of development of the dentition against the usual chronologic 
markers. You will be learning about that in detail later in this course.</p>

<p>For example, from the standard charts it would be possible to calculate a height age. 
When you're the height of an average nine year old (just over 130 cms), your height age is 9, 
regardless of your chronologic age. Intellectual development can be calculated in the same 
way. Intellectual development relative to chronologic age usually is called IQ, for 
intelligence quotient, but it's just another developmental age.</p>

<p>It is interesting that the various developmental ages tend to be highly correlated. If 
you're bigger than other children the same age, you're probably also more developed 
mentally and socially. Correlated, of course, doesn't mean that this is always the 
case, just that it's more likely to be that way.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1.jpg" resourceWidth="393" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Timing: Biologic Age (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The use of biologic age is a way to control timing as a variable in growth studies. 
Look again at the growth curves for our three girls with early, average and late 
menarche (image 1). Now use menarche as a biologic marker and call that time zero and 
plot growth increments before and after (image 2).</p>

<p>Note how similar the growth curves are for the group of girls after this simple 
transformation. They all had a very similar acceleration of growth leading up to 
menarche and decrease afterward. Using chronologic age instead of biologic age often 
can be misleading when developmental events are studied, as we will see when we 
consider cross-sectional vs longitudingal studies.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic2.jpg" resourceWidth="460" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic2_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="82" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic3.jpg" resourceWidth="408" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic3_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="72" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Methods for Studying Growth</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Introduction: Types of Growth Data</title><pageText><p>Growth studies may either be longitudinal or cross-sectional in design. When you look at 
growth data, it is important to know whether the study was longitudinal or cross-sectional.</p>

<p>In cross-sectional studies, rather than seeing the same individual at age 9,10,11, etc., 
data are taken for a group of 9 year olds, a different group of 10 year olds, another different 
group of 11 year olds, and so on. This is quicker and easier, but the amount of individual 
variation tends to be understated. The mean for the group (the black line) when chronologic 
age is used as the time base gives a very misleading picture of what happens to 
any individual.</p>

<p>Longitudinal studies, in which the same individual is followed over time, provide more 
information about individual variation, but these studies take a long time and become quite 
expensive. Note that longitudinal data give a much better picture of what an individual would 
experience.</p>

<p>Now remember the effect of plotting the individual data with menarche as a base. Using biologic 
age in that way with cross-sectional data can make it easier to avoid distortions due to different 
timing in different individuals.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_01.jpg" resourceWidth="360" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_01_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="64" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Longitudinal Growth, Distance</title><pageText><p>This graph shows the first published longitudinal study of growth, done by the French 
aristocrat De Montebillard in the 1700's. He plotted the height of his son from birth to age 18, 
measuring the boy repeatedly over those 18 years. Many fathers or grandfathers still do this, often 
with marks on a door frame as a child grows.</p>

<p>You can see that the growth in height didn't occur in a steady fashion. It was very rapid at first, 
trailed off after about age 2, then accelerated from ages 14 to 16 and was still continuing at age 18.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_02.jpg" resourceWidth="476" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_02_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="85" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Longitudinal Growth, Distance vs. Velocity</title><pageText><p>It's easier to see changes in the rate of growth if the same data are plotted in a different 
way, showing the amount of change in each interval rather than the total height. Note how the 
very rapid growth at first, slower rate in childhood prior to adolescence, and the adolescent 
growth spurt stand out when the amount of change is plotted. The first curve is called a 
distance curve, the second a velocity curve.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_03.jpg" resourceWidth="508" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_03_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="90" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Other Data Transformations</title><pageText><p>Various other mathematical transformations of data can make it easier to understand what 
is occurring during growth. In image 1, the graph showing the increase in weight of early 
embryos, you can see that there is an exponential acceleration in weight with increasing 
time.</p>

<p>In image 2, the same data are plotted after a logarithmic transformation. This shows a 
straight line, indicating that the rate of multiplication of individual cells remains almost 
constant. It's not that cells are dividing faster as the embryo gets older, it's that 
increasingly there are more cells to divide.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/2-12_4thed_bluelinedel.jpg" resourceWidth="494" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/2-12_4thed_bluelinedel_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="88" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/2-12_4thed.jpg" resourceWidth="494" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/2-12_4thed_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="88" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Methods for Studying Growth: Growth Measurement Techniques</title><pageText><p>There are four basic measurement techniques for physical growth:</p>

<ol>
<li>Craniometry</li>
<li>Anthropometry</li>
<li>Cephalometric radiography</li>
<li>3D radiography (computed tomography)</li>
</ol></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/jme07.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/jme07_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Craniometry</title><pageText><p>The science of physical anthropology began with craniometry, which is based 
on measurements of human skulls (or other bones, in which case it would be 
osteometry).</p>

<p>Although most craniometric studies have been done on the remains of populations 
from earlier times, study of contemporary skulls or other bones obviously would 
be possible. Distortions of the skull during growth can occur, and now are understood 
better after study of skeletal remains. A good example is the effect 
of premature fusion of sutures.</p>

<p>In the individual shown in image 1, the mid-sagittal 
suture fused prematurely and was entirely missing in adult life. Note 
the extremely narrow width of the cranium. In compensation, the brain 
and skull became abnormally long posteriorly. In image 2, note the effect 
of, premature fusion of sutures on the right side of the cranial base. This led to 
a marked asymmetry that affected both the cranium and cranial base. 
Once effects of this type have been noted in studies of skulls, the 
likely cause of similar asymmetries in living patients becomes apparent.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_07.jpg" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_07_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>In this individual, an increase in width of the cranium was not possible because 
of premature fusion of the mid-sagittal suture. The result was a remarkably narrow 
cranial vault, which forced a change in the shape of the brain.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_08.jpg" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_08_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>For this individual, premature fusion of sutures on the right side of the cranial 
base led to a major asymmetry that also affected the cranium.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Anthropometry</title><pageText><p>Anthropometry refers to measurements on living individuals. Various landmarks on the 
skull were established by investigators studying skeletal material, and the soft tissue 
points overlying those landmarks (or other soft tissue points that can be found 
repeatedly) can be used to study living individuals.</p>

<p>Varying soft tissue thickness introduces a source of error, but it is highly advantageous 
to follow the growth of an individual directly, making the same measurement repeatedly 
at different times.</p>

<p>This produces longitudinal rather than cross-sectional 
data and shows individual variation much more precisely. Much of what 
we know about cranial and facial growth was first deduced from anthropometric 
studies. Anthropometric measurements are still important in clinical 
examination of orthodontic patients. They are used now primarily to 
establish facial proportions.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_09.jpg" resourceWidth="315" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_09_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Anthropometric measurement of bi-zygomatic width, which is important in clinical 
orthodontics because of its relationship to the width of the maxillary dental arch 
and in establishing face height-width proportions</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_10.jpg" resourceWidth="315" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_10_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Anthropometric measurement of anterior face height, the other part of 
face height-width proportions. The relationship of face height to width 
is the "facial index".</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cephalometric Radiology</title><pageText><p>The third important measurement technique is cephalometric radiology. Using x-ray 
pictures of the  head and face provides a way to combine the advantages of crainometry 
and anthropometry.</p>

<p>It allows direct measurement of the skeleton because the soft tissue thickness can be 
ignored&#8212;but the soft tissues also are imaged and can be measured if desired.</p>

<p>Proper positioning of the subject in a head holder is necessary, so that repeated 
x-rays can be made with the head positioned exactly the same. This allows longitudinal 
study of growth (or treatment) changes in an individual.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_11.jpg" resourceWidth="300" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_11_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>The head-holder for obtaining cephalometric radiographs, which is necessary to 
obtain longitudinal records that can be compared accurately.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cephalometric Radiology (cont.) </title><pageText><p>The disadvantages of cephalometrics are that exposure to x-rays is required, and that 
the radiograph is a two-dimensional representation of three-dimensional structures. Some 
measurements are not possible and others are distorted in projection. The recent development 
of cone-beam computed tomography, which greatly reduces the radiation dose to obtain 3-D images 
of the head and face, means that this method is likely to replace traditional cephalometrics for 
many purposes.</p>

<p>But cephalometric radiographs give an excellent view of many skeletal and dental structures 
that aren't accessible for anthropometric study, and these radiolographs are used routinely in 
dentistry to monitor growth and treatment of patients. A patient like this one, with too much 
growth of the lower jaw, has to be followed with serial cephalometric radiographs to determine 
the best time for treatment. You'll be learning a lot more about how to use cephalograms for 
this purpose.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_12.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="448" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_12_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Lateral cephalometric radiograph of an individual with disproportionate growth of the 
upper and lower jaws. Serial cephs to monitor growth are an important tool in clinical 
treatment of problems of this type.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Newer Imaging: Computed Tomography (CT)</title><pageText><p>With newer imaging methods like computed tomography (CT), it is possible to 
reconstruct facial images in three dimensions.</p>

<p>These CT views of a patient with hemifacial microsomia (under-development of one 
side of the face) make the defects obvious, and the image can be rotated and manipulated 
to provide other perspectives. Axial CT, which is used in most hospital applications, is 
very precise but has two problems for studies of growth: it is expensive and delivers a 
relatively large radiation dose.</p>

<p>Recently, the introduction of cone-beam CT (CBCT) for images of the head has offered a 
significant reduction in both cost and radiation, and CBCT is rapidly becoming an important 
tool in dentistry for both improved diagnosis and for growth studies. CBCT is not quite as 
accurate as axiall CT, but its precision is adequate for growth studies.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_13.jpg" resourceWidth="350" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_13_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="62" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Computed tomography provides information about structures at any depth in the facial 
skeleton, and at any orientation. Structures can be colored to make it easier to visualize 
them. Another CBCT examination of this patient can reveal exactly which areas are growing 
and how much.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>CB-CT Superimpositions</title><pageText><p>For growth studies, it is important to see changes over time. This requires 
superimposition of images of the same individual that were taken at different times. 
With cephalometric radiographs, tracings based on identification of landmarks 
typically are used.</p>

<p>That doesn't work with 3-D images, but now it is possible to superimpose on surface 
contours, and changes between sequential 3-D images can be discerned by color maps. This allows 
you to look at the amount of change at  thousands of points that can be viewed from any 
orientation, instead of being limited to tens of points seen from one orientation in a 
cephalometric radiograph. The superimposed images here show changes in the position of 
the jaws created in an adult by orthognathic surgery to reposition his maxilla, but the 
same approach can be used in growth studies, and such studies now are being undertaken.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_14.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="341" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_14_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="141" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>A, Changes created by surgery to advance the maxilla in this patient with maxillary 
deficiency, and B, Changes from immediate post-surgery to one year later. The colors reveal 
the amount of change and its direction. Red shows anterior or outward movement, green shows areas 
of little or no change, and blue shows areas of posterior or inward movement. The intensity of 
the red and blue indicates the magnitude of the change.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Methods</title><pageText><p>The second way to study growth is with marker techniques. These are classic 
experimental methods for studying growth. Using these methods, it is possible to 
follow either processes or physical changes by visualizing the marker.</p>

<p>Those techniques include:</p>

<ol>
<li>Vital staining</li>
<li>Autoradiography</li>
<li>Cephalometric superimposition on Implants</li>
<li>Molecular techniques</li>
</ol></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/jme08.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/jme08_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Vital Staining</title><pageText><p>In vital staining, dyes that are incorporated into bone (or sometimes other tissues) 
are injected into animals. Bone that was growing at the time the dye was injected is 
stained, and the amount of growth between two injections or since the last injection 
can be seen.</p>

<p>The technique goes back to the famous English anatomist John Hunter, who observed 
that the dyes in textile wastes fed to pigs stained their bones in interesting ways. 
He experimented to find which dyes were best for staining bone. Alizarin proved to 
be best.</p>

<p>This young rat had four injections of alizarin dye at 2-week intervals, first red, 
then blue, then red again, then blue again.  The dye is excreted rapidly, so the 
staining occurs during only a few hours after each injection.</p>

<p>As you look carefully at the mandible (the condylar process is in the center), you 
can see the sequential bands of color. The white bone at the tip of the condylar process 
grew there since the last injection. Both the sites of growth and the rate of growth 
in various areas can be seen. The sites of growth are the areas where new bone is 
being formed, or removed by the remodeling that accompanies bone growth. The rate of 
growth is shown by the distance between bands of color that were deposited at known 
times when the dye was injected.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_17.jpg" resourceWidth="351" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_17_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="62" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Bands of alizarin staining in this preparation of the ramus of the mandible indicate 
where bone was forming at the time of the injection. Note the white unstained bone at 
the tip of the coronoid and condylar processes. This is bone that was formed in the 
last 2 weeks, after the final injection.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Autoradiography</title><pageText><p>Autoradiography is based on causing tissues to take their own pictures. Radioactively labeled 
substances are injected, tissue specimens are prepared, and when photographic film is exposed 
by placing it over the tissue specimen in the dark, the location of radioactive materials in 
the tissue is revealed as radiation activates silver grains in the film layer.</p>

<p>This is an autoradiograph of a small bone that was growing in organ culture. Tritium-labelled 
thymidine was incorporated into the culture medium, and was taken up when DNA of new cells was 
formed at the time of cell division. The black dots are nuclei that contain the labeled thymidine, 
which means they must have been formed by cell division that occurred since the tritiated 
thymidine was added to the culture medium.</p>

<p>In this experiment, carbon 14-labelled proline also was added to the medium. Proline, an amino 
acid, is a major constituent of collagen, which in turn is the major component of connective tissues 
and bone matrix. The dark label away from the cell nuclei shows where proline is being incorporated 
into newly-formed collagen, and therefore shows where collagen formation is taking place. Note 
that it is most active in the area where maturing collagen is being replaced by bone spicules. 
With radioactive labeling, essentially any substance can be turned into the equivalent of a 
vital stain.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_18.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="394" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_18_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="122" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Implant Radiology</title><pageText><p>Implant radiology is based on visualizing metal pins placed in the skeleton. Perhaps you 
know that when bones are fractured, metal pins often are placed to hold them while they heal, 
and often the pins are left in place. A long time after the fracture has healed, the pin will 
still be visible on x-rays as a marker of the fracture site. It is possible experimentally 
to place small metallic implants in bones anywhere in the skeleton, including the face and 
jaws, as permanent markers.</p>

<p>This girl has small pieces of tantalum wire in her jaws, placed in areas where little growth 
occurs, as markers, so that the changes in jaw contours as she grows can be followed more 
precisely. The implants were placed from inside the mouth by anesthetizing the muscosa over 
the area where the implant is to be placed, then using small spring-loaded device to drive 
the implant through the soft tissue into the bone. It is a simple and painless procedure. 
When another cephalogram is taken later, one can superimpose on the markers, and then 
changes due to remodeling of the surfaces of the bone can be seen clearly.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/img2-17.jpg" resourceWidth="455" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/img2-17_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="81" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Implant Radiology (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Implants have been placed in a number of children whose growth pattern was followed 
longitudinally, using cephalometric x-rays to detect the location of the pins. Then the 
pins were used to superimpose the outline of the jaws, so that growth changes could be 
seen relative to the pins.</p>

<p>This method was originated by Professor Bjork in Copenhagen, and has been responsible 
for much of our current understanding of jaw growth patterns. In this superimposition on 
pins in the mandible, you can see that bone was added to the posterior surface of the 
ramus and to the condylar and coronoid processes, but was removed from the gonial angle 
area. Note also that a great deal of remodeling of the condyles occurred. What was once 
the condyle at age 4 became a part of the ramus at age 10, and then was partially resorbed 
away as the condylar process continued to grow upward. Note also how the teeth erupted 
upward and forward relative to the pins in stable areas of the bone. Until cephalometric 
superimpositions on markers was done, the large amount of remodeling of the bone as the 
jaws grew had not been appreciated.</p>

<p>You'll be seeing more tracings of cephalometric radiographs superimposed on implants 
in the future, and you must understand the concept.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_15.jpg" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_15_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Molecular Techniques</title><pageText><p>It also is possible to use the techniques of molecular biology to study growth, and 
this holds great promise for the near future. An example of such methods is diagrammed 
on this slide. Genetic information carried by plasmids can be injected into the nucleus 
of a mouse egg, which is then implanted into a pseudopregnant mouse.</p>

<p>When the mouse gives birth, if the new genetic information is active and has been copied, 
the progeny have foreign DNA and are known as transgenic mice. These genetically-altered mice 
can be examined for morphologic differences, extracts can be made to test for inactivated 
hormones or enzymes, etc.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_16.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="123" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_16_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="34"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Molecular Techniques (cont.)</title><pageText><p>One of these mice strains was injected with a plasmid carrying genes coding for growth 
hormone. The impressively large size of the animal on the left confirms the activity of this 
genetic information in these transgenic mice. Because normal growth patterns are so precise 
and specific, genetic control is obvious.</p>

<p>Experiments of this type have great promise in explaining exactly how the control 
is mediated.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/mice.jpg" resourceWidth="150" resourceHeight="175" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/mice_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary</title><pageText><p>In studies of growth and development:</p>

<ul>
<li>growth (increase in size) and development (increase in complexity with specialization 
and loss of potential) are different concepts</li>
<li>growth pattern refers to predictable changes in proportions with growth</li>
<li>children outside the 3rd and 97th percentiles on standard growth charts may be 
beyond normal variation</li>
<li>the timing of adolescence is a major contributor to variability in growth</li>
<li>biologic ages based on physiologic events can be used to reduce variation related to timing</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Important measurement techniques to know:</p>
<ul>
<li>Craniometry</li>
<li>Anthropometry</li>
<li>Cephalometric radiology</li>
<li>Cone-beam CT</li>
</ul>

<p>Remember: the timing of adolescence is a major contributor to variability in growth</p>

<p>Cross-sectional growth studies:</p>
<ul>
<li>quicker, less expensive, less precise in detecting typical timing fluctuations</li>
</ul>

<p>Longitudinal growth studies:</p>
<ul>
<li>slow, expensive and hard to maintain, very efficient and excellent in showing details</li>
</ul>

<p>Experimental marker techniques to know:</p>
<ul>
<li>vital staining</li>
<li>autoradiography</li>
<li>implant superimposition </li>
</ul>

<p>Molecular biology techniques: The way of the future in growth studies.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>(A) Anthropometric data are preferred over craniometric data in the study of 
growth because (B) soft tissue rather than hard tissue landmarks are used in 
craniometric studies.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, anthropometric data are preferred over craniometric data in growth 
studies, not because soft tissue landmarks are used in anthropometry, but because 
they are (or can be) longitudinal rather than cross-sectional. Craniometric data, 
which are obtained from skulls (no soft tissue available), always are cross-sectional. 
The soft tissue landmarks are a disadvantage of anthropometry for studies of skeletal 
growth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong! It's true that anthropometric data are preferred over craniometric 
data in growth studies, and false that craniometry uses soft tissue landmarks. 
Anthropometric data are presferred, not because of the soft tissue landmarks, but 
because they are (or can be) longitudinal rather than cross-sectional. Craniometric 
data, which are obtained from skulls (no soft tissue available), always are 
cross-sectional. The soft tissue landmarks are a disadvantage of anthropometry for 
studies of skeletal growth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_09.jpg" resourceWidth="315" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_09_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Anthropometric measurement of bi-zygomatic width, which is important in clinical 
orthodontics because of its relationship to the width of the maxillary dental arch and 
in establishing face height-width proportions</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_10.jpg" resourceWidth="315" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_10_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption><p>Anthropometric measurement of anterior face height, the other part of the face 
height-width proportionality.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>In fetal and postnatal growth, what is meant by the "cephalocaudal gradient 
of growth?"</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>head grows faster than trunk and limbs</choice><choice>trunk and limbs grow faster than head</choice><choice>cephalic structures are more important for growth</choice><choice>caudal structures are more important for growth</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. In very early (embryonic) development, the cranium represents 25% of 
the whole individual, and the head about half. From then on, the trunk and limbs grow 
faster than the head, and the face more than the cranium.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. In very early (embryonic) development, the cranium represents 25% of 
the whole individual, and the head about half. From then on, the trunk and limbs grow 
faster than the head, and the face more than the cranium. The cranium and head aren't 
more or less important than the other structures, they just grow at different times.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="357" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>How would you establish a child's reading age?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>compare against standards for social development</choice><choice>compare against standards for reading development</choice><choice>evaluate with scores of standard IQ tests</choice><choice>not possible, developmental ages relate to physical characteristics only</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, there are standards for reading development just as there are 
standards for development on other physical and social-psychological scales. A 
child can be advanced or slow in reading just as he or she could be in physical 
development. It's interesting that the different types of development are 
highly correlated.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's incorrect. There are standards for emotional development just as there 
are standards for development on other physical and social-psychological scales, and 
a child can be evaluated in relation to those scales. A child can be advanced or slow 
in emotional development just as he or she could be in physical development.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1.jpg" resourceWidth="393" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is the most appropriate description of the concept 
of pattern in growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>proportional size relationships</choice><choice>changes in proportions over time</choice><choice>conservation of proportions as size increases</choice><choice>changes in proportions as size increases</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. Pattern in growth refers to the way in which proportional relationships 
change (or are maintained) as the individual changes over time (whether or not he gets 
bigger). The changing proportions of the face describe its growth pattern.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. Pattern in growth refers to the way in which proportional relationships 
change (or are maintained) as the individual changes over time (whether or not he gets 
bigger). There is a pattern in the size relationships of parts at any one time, but that 
isn't the growth pattern. And everything doesn't have to get bigger as you grow. The 
changing proportions of the face describe its growth pattern.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_01.jpg" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_01_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Newborn</label><caption>Newborn</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_02.jpg" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_02_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Age 8</label><caption>Age 8</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_03.jpg" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_03_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Young adult</label><caption>Young adult</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_04.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="262" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_04_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="73"><label>All together</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>On growth charts with 6-month data plots, what is the significance of a 
child "crossing the percentiles" downward?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>indicates growth disturbance, perhaps chronic illness or chronic problem</choice><choice>Indicates increasingly active growth, perhaps tumor</choice><choice>no significance over this period of time, quick changes more important</choice><choice>no significance, changes in channels typically occur during normal growth</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, a downward movement across the percentile channels over a 6 month 
period indicates a growth disturbance and raises the question of some chronic illness 
or other chronic problem. A normal child usually stays within his or her channel.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. A decrease in the percentile channels over a 6 month period 
indicates a growth disturbance and raises the question of some chronic illness or 
other chronic problem. A normal child usually stays within his or her channel. Note 
the effect of growth hormone (HGH) deficiency in the plot for this child, and then 
the catch-up effect of administering the hormone.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>(A) Girls grow earlier than boys at adolescence because (B) girls mature 
sexually earlier than boys.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. As a group, girls grow earlier than boys at adolescence, and the 
reason is their earlier sexual maturation. In an important sense, adolescence and 
adolescent growth is a sexual phenomenon.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, you're wrong. As a group, girls grow earlier than boys at adolescence, and the 
reason is their earlier sexual maturation. In an important sense, adolescence is a 
sexual phenomenon. The group tendency, of course, doesn't mean that every individual 
is that way. Some boys mature before some girls.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is not appropriately described as growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>increase in size</choice><choice>increase in number</choice><choice>increase in complexity</choice><choice>increase in specialization</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct. Growth refers to an increase in size, number or occasionally complexity, 
but not to increased specialization. The term "development" often is used to 
describe an increase in specialization of biologic functions, but sometimes it is used 
to describe an increase in complexity--so sometimes there is an overlap with growth, 
sometimes there isn't.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. Growth refers to an increase in size, number or occasionally complexity, but 
not to increased specialization. The term "development" often is used to describe 
an increase in specialization of biologic functions, but sometimes it is used to describe 
an increase in complexity--so sometimes there is an overlap with growth, sometimes there isn't.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_05.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_05_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>The value of implants, such as metallic pins placed in the jaws, in radiographic 
studies of growth is that:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>the implants mark areas of bone that are growing</choice><choice>the implants mark areas of bone that are remodeling</choice><choice>the implants mark areas of bone that are not growing or remodeling</choice><choice>the implants outline areas of bone of particular interest so they can be evaluated</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct, the implants mark areas that are not growing or remodeling. This 
provides stable areas for superimposition of longitudinal x-rays, and then you can 
see which other areas are changing and how much, and which areas are not changing. 
As this superimposition on implants in the mandible shows, implant studies are an 
excellent way to determine the changing proportions that define the growth pattern.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's not the best answer, implants do that only indirectly. The implants mark 
areas that are not growing or remodeling. This provides stable areas for superimposition 
of longitudinal x-rays, and then you can see which areas are changing and how much, and 
which areas are not changing. As this superimposition on implants in the mandible shows, 
implant studies are an excellent way to determine the changing proportions that define 
the growth pattern.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>What percentage of a normally distributed population is within two standard 
deviations of the mean?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>50%</choice><choice>66%</choice><choice>78%</choice><choice>87%</choice><choice>95%</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, 95% of the population are within two standard deviations of the mean, 
and 99% are within three standard deviations. But when you're treating patients with 
problems, you're likely to encounter individuals who are at the extremes of the 
normal distribution.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. 95% of the population are within two standard deviations of the mean, 
and 99% are within three standard deviations. But when you're treating patients with problems, you're 
likely to encounter individuals who are at the extremes of the normal distribution. Sometimes 
doctors begin to think that almost everybody is abnormal, because they see so many of the 
extreme variations.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_02.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_02_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>How do vital stains contribute to the study of growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>stain everything that was present when they were administered</choice><choice>stain everything that was growing when they were administered</choice><choice>stain everything that grew after they were administered</choice><choice>stain specific things that were growing at the time they were administered</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct. A vital stain marks specific things that were growing when it was 
administered, for instance, the bone that was being laid down at that time. Different 
vital stains are used for different tissues. If it stained everything, you couldn't 
distinguish one structure from another.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. A vital stain marks specific things that were growing when 
it was administered, for instance, the bone that was being laid down at that 
time. Different vital stains are used for different tissues. If it stained everything, 
you couldn't distinguish one structure from another.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_17.jpg" resourceWidth="351" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_17_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="62" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 11</title><pageText><p>Within the face, the postnatal cephalocaudal gradient of growth predicts that:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>the face grows faster than the cranium</choice><choice>the mandible grows faster than the maxilla</choice><choice>the maxilla grows faster than the cranium</choice><choice>all of the above</choice><choice>none of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. The cephalocaudal gradient of growth predicts (correctly) that a structure further 
away from the cranium grow faster than one closer to it. So in postnatal life both jaws grow faster 
than the cranium and the mandible grows faster than the maxilla.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. The cephalocaudel gradient of growth predicts (correctly) that the structures 
further away from the cranium grow faster than those closer to it, so in postnatal life both 
jaws grow faster than the cranium and the mandible grows faster than the maxilla.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="357" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 12</title><pageText><p>If a girl's bone age is 12, what is her chronologic age most likely to be?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>10</choice><choice>11</choice><choice>12</choice><choice>13</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, the greatest probability is that the developmental age matches 
the chronologic age. That's how the developmental age was established. But for any 
individual, the chronologic and developmental ages may or may not coincide.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. The greatest probability is that the developmental age matches 
the chronologic age. That's how the developmental age was established. But for any 
individual, the chronologic and developmental ages may or may not coincide.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1.jpg" resourceWidth="321" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 13</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is the major disadvantage of cephalometric radiography 
in the study of growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>requires damaging x-rays</choice><choice>requires complex head positioning equipment</choice><choice>makes it difficult to see soft tissue landmarks</choice><choice>offers a two-dimensional view of three-dimensional objects</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. All of the responses are disadvantages to some extent, but the 
biggest disadvantage is the two-dimensional view that the radiograph provides. Changes 
in distances between points that are not in the same plane will be distorted. The 
compensating advantage is that longitudinal data for skeletal dimensions can be 
obtained by superimposing tracings of serial cephalometric radiographs.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. All of the responses are disadvantages to some extent, but the 
biggest disadvantage is the two-dimensional view that the radiograph provides. Changes 
in distances between points that are not in the same plane will be distorted. The 
compensating advantage is that longitudinal data for skeletal dimensions can be 
obtained by superimposing tracings of serial cephalometric radiographs.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 14</title><pageText><p>The difference between a growth distance curve and a growth velocity curve is that:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>distance curve plots total achieved, velocity curve plots increment</choice><choice>distance curve plots increment, velocity curve plots total achieved</choice><choice>both curves plot increment, but velocity curve magnifies it </choice><choice>both curves plot total achieved, but distance curve magnifies it</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. Distance curves plot the total growth achieved, velocity curves 
plot the growth increment since the last measurement. Both types of plots are valuable, 
depending on what you're trying to observe--but velocity plots make it easier to 
appreciate the changes that are occurring, as at adolescence.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's incorrect. Distance curves plot the total growth achieved, velocity curves 
plot the growth increment since the last measurement. Both types of plots are valuable, 
depending on what you're trying to observe&#8212;but velocity plots make it easier to 
appreciate the changes that are occurring, as at adolescence.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_03.jpg" resourceWidth="508" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_03_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="90" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 15</title><pageText><p>(A) Longitudinal growth data are quite inefficient in terms of the amount of information 
obtained from each subject because (B) the longitudinal data highlight individual 
variations.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. Longitudinal data are very efficient, not inefficient, for growth studies, so 
the first statement is false. It's true that the longitudinal data highlight individual 
variations, so the second statement is true. That's another advantage of longitudinal 
versus cross-sectional data.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. Longitudinal data are very efficient, not inefficient, for growth 
studies, so the first statement is false. It's true that the longitudinal data highlight 
individual variations, so the second statement is true. That's another advantage of 
longitudinal versus cross-sectional data.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1.jpg" resourceWidth="393" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 16</title><pageText><p>What does it mean to say that a child is in the 95% percentile for height?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>she's in the shortest 5% of the population her age</choice><choice>she's in the tallest 5% of the population her age</choice><choice>she's more than two standard deviations below the mean</choice><choice>she's more than two standard deviations above the mean</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct, she's in the tallest 5%, taller than 95% of her age group. But that puts 
her within two standard deviations of the mean, in her case, exactly two above.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. She's in the tallest 5% of her age group, taller than 95%. But 
that puts her exactly two standard deviations above the mean, not more than two above.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1.jpg" resourceWidth="321" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart2.jpg" resourceWidth="318" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart2_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>