<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<presentation><title>The Study of Physical Growth</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>William R. Proffit<br/>Dept. of Orthodontics, UNC School of Dentistry<br/></additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/titlepage.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Introduction, Background</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Introduction</title><pageText><p>Before viewing this program, you should have looked at the short video introduction to this course, Level I in the Growth and Development sequence.</p>
<p>As with this and all the other computer teaching programs, it's important to read the assigned material in Contemporary Orthodontics. For this program, the assigned material is pages 2-4 and 20-40 in the 5th edition, and pages 2-4 and 18-36 in the 6th edition, and of course you also will view the program.</p>
<p>Then you will take the self-test, the last section of the teaching module, and use it to consolidate the information and to be sure that you really understand it. Remember, the test is a teaching tool. Its purpose isn’t to evaluate you and provide some sort of grade—that doesn’t happen. Its purpose is to help you master the material.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Learning Objectives</title><pageText><p>The general learning objectives of this program are to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Introduce the Angle classification of malocclusion as a background for the Class I, Class II and Class III terms frequently used in describing growth patterns</li>
<li>Distinguish the somewhat overlapping terms of “growth” and “development” from each other</li>
<li>Discuss the concepts of pattern, variability, and timing as they are applied to the study of growth and development</li>
<li>Provide an overview of the methods for studying growth from which our current knowledge was derived</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Edward Angle and Occlusion/Malocclusion</title><pageText><p>Terminology is important in understanding anything, and in our discussion of growth and development, that’s critically important. We need to start with the major contribution of Edward Angle, his definition of malocclusion and his concept of normal occlusion.</p>
<p> In the late 19th century, Dr. Angle partcipated in the development of rules for dental occlusion in prosthodontics, at the time the concepts that are still the foundation for full denture prostheses were written. He extended the prosthodontic rules into the developed the first useful classification for the human dentition. You must understand it because it will appear repeatedly in the discussion of growth in this course.</p>
<p> Angle’s postulate was that normal occlusion had two critical characteristics: correct alignment of the teeth in the dental arches, and correct occlusion when the upper and lower teeth were brought together. Neither had not been previously defined.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Angle painting     <i>﻿This is </i><i>Fig 1-1 in Contem Orthod</i></label><caption><p>Edward Angle in his 50s, after he had promulgated the Angle classification and established himself as the first dental specialist. By then he was the proprietor of the Angle School of Orthodontics.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Characteristics of Normal Occlusion and Malocclusion</title><pageText><p>Angle used the “line of occlusion” to define how the teeth should be aligned. It was a smooth (catenary) curve—catenary means that it had the form of a flexible chain suspended from a horizontal bean to which each end was attached. The curve specified the position of each tooth relative to the adjacent teeth in its dental arch (Fig. 1). If any teeth were malpositioned relative to the line of occlusion, they were not in the normal relationship.</p>
<p>The line of occlusion required an anchor point to fit this single line against both arches, and Angle specified that this was the position of the maxillary first molar and the relationship of the mandibular first molar to it. This resulted in the Angle classification system, which defined normal occlusion and three types of malocclusion (Figures 2-5). Malocclusion is a word that he introduced—it had not appeared previously.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Angle's line of occlusion     <i><b>﻿Fig 1.2, C Orthod</b></i></label><caption><p>The line of occlusion ran along the incisal edges of the lower incisors, canine tip and  buccal cusp tips of the lower posterior teeth, and though the occlusal fossae of maxillary posterior teeth and along the cingulae of the maxillary canines and incisors.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Classification: normal occlusion    <i><b>Fig 1.3A</b></i></label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Classification: Class I malocclusion     <i><b>Fig 1.3B</b></i><i><b>Fig 1.3A</b></i></label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Classification: Class II malocclusion     <i><b>Fig 1.3C</b></i></label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Classification: Class III malocclusion<b/><i><b>     Fig 1.3D</b></i></label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Extended Angle Classification</title><pageText><p>Angle’s classification scheme immediately was widely adopted and used. Cephalometric radiology was introduced in the 1930s. It was and is based on the use of a head holder so that a patient can be placed in a precise relationship with the x-ray apparatus (and the same patient could be positioned identically for a later radiograph if desired). Both frontal and lateral views were made in early research studies, and gradually the lateral ceph (the term we will use from now on) became a standard part of orthodontic diagnosis.</p>
<p>Cephs made it possible to determine jaw relationships. It became clear that many Class II and Class III malocclusions were due to faulty jaw relationships, and Angle’s terms were extended to the relationships of the jaws (Figs. 1,2 and 3 below).</p>
<p>The term skeletal Class I described a jaw relationship would lead either to normal occlusion or Class I malocclusion, while skeletal Class II would predispose to Class II malocclusion, and skeletal Class III would almost always produce a Class III malocclusion. Similarly, a growth pattern that maintained a normal jaw relationship came to be called a Class I growth pattern, while Class II and Class III growth patterns described growth that created or maintained skeletal Class II and Class III jaw relationships.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Skeletal Class I (normal)</label><caption><p><i><b>﻿no captions for these--all 3 are new cephs</b></i></p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Skeletal Class II</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Skeletal Class III</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Superimposed Cephalometric Tracings to Evaluate Growth Patterns</title><pageText><p>If a cephalometric tracing from a patient at an earlier time is superimposed on a tracing from a later time, it is possible to view and measure exactly how much change (growth and/or treatment response) occurred during that time. The superimposition usually is on the cranial base, which does not grow after neural growth is largely completed at about age 6. The relative growth of the maxilla and mandible can be seen in a way that made cephalometrics important for evaluating growth, and the Angle terminology is used to describe the growth patterns (Figures 1-3).</p>
<p>With superimposed cephalometric tracings, it also distinguish modification of jaw growth during treatment from just tooth movement, at least to some extent (Figure 4), and the extended Angle terminology also is used to distinguish whether changes in the occlusion were due to changes in jaw growth or just to tooth movement. </p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig 1, Class I growth pattern   <i><b>all 3 of these tracings are new</b></i></label><caption><p>Note that the jaw relationship for this patient was reasonably normal (Class I) in the first tracing, and the two jaws grew about the same amount in the interval between the two cephs. This is a classic Class I growth pattern.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig 2, Class II growth pattern</label><caption><p>This patient had a deficient mandible that was the major reason for his Class II malocclusion, and there was very little forward growth of the mandible relative to the maxilla in the time up to the second tracing.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig 3, Class III growth pattern</label><caption><p>This patient had a prominent mandible when the first ceph was taken, and it got worse over time.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig 4, Successful growth modification</label><caption><p>Between the two cephs, this patient had treatment to restrict forward growth of the maxilla and encourage forward growth of the mandible. It worked--note the improvement in the jaw relationship.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth</title><pageText><p>If you are not careful, the very word “growth” can cause some difficulties.</p>
<p>Growth certainly refers to an increase in size, but it’s more that that. More than anything else, growth indicates change—which is why it’s possible sometimes to speak of negative growth.</p>
<p>Development indicates new capabilities, often bigger and better, perhaps at some cost. In this course on growth and development, it’s important to distinguish these terms.</p>
<p>For our use:</p>
<p>Growth, most of the time, will refer to a change, almost always an increase, in size or number, generally with an anatomic reference. Occasionally, however, it will be used to indicate more of an increase in complexity than size.</p>
<p>Development will be used primarily to refer to an increase in complexity—especially when this carries with it an overtone of specialization and loss of potential. It's a general outcome of biologic development that as cells become more specialized, there is a loss of potential to become something else. This is where the terms growth and development overlap, and where you have to read carefully not to become confused.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="262" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_04.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="73" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_04_s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s01_p03_02.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s01_p03_02s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth / Development: Why?</title><pageText><p>As a dental student, why do you have to study growth and development?</p>
<p>There are three important reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>You have to understand normal dental and craniofacial growth, and psychosocial development to work with children. </li>
<li>You can't distinguish the abnormal growth or development if you don't understand the normal pattern.</li>
<li>Dentists / orthodontists can manipulate craniofacial growth to some extent, and this can be important in treating growth problems. Whether or not you personally provide this kind of treatment, you have to understand how it works and when it's indicated.</li>
</ul>
<p>In the rest of the teaching programs in this program, you're going to learn a lot about all of these things.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary</title><pageText><p>Now you know what the Angle classes are, right? How many are there?</p>
<p>Surely you thought four—or did you think three? Remember, Angle classification has four categories:</p>
<ul>
<li>normal occlusion</li>
<li>Class I malocclusion</li>
<li>Class II      “</li>
<li>Class III     “</li>
</ul>
<p>And you understand that the extensions of the types of malocclusion to jaw relationships and growth patterns don’t include the normal occlusion category, but do include the three types of malocclusion that go along with them. You still have a lot to learn about growth and growth patterns, but now we can use the Angle terminology when we talk about those things.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Concepts of Pattern, Variability and Timing</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Pattern</title><pageText><p>Let's start with the important concept of growth pattern. Think about the 
pattern for an article of clothing. As the pattern increases in size, there are 
changes in some areas that are larger or smaller than changes in other 
areas—it isn't just blown up like a balloon. In this way, the pattern 
reflects a complex set of proportional relationships.</p>

<p>Pattern in growth is a higher level pattern, a step beyond the pattern that 
gets clothes to fit or describes body proportions at any one time. It refers to 
the predictable changes in body proportions over time as the individual grows.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s02_p01_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s02_p01_01s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Pattern: Proportion Changes</title><pageText><p>There are striking changes in body proportions over time.</p>
<p>Note that at the end of the second month in utero, the head and face comprise almost 50% of the total body length. In contrast, the limbs are still rudimentary and the trunk underdeveloped. It may seem strange that at one time your nose was as big as your hand, but that was the case in early life.</p>
<p>The proportion of total body size contributed by the head and face steadily decreases after the 3rd month of fetal life. By the time of birth, greater growth of the trunk and limbs has reduced the head to 25% of the entire body. This pattern continues, so that the head and face contribute proportionally less and less to the total body length. This relative reduction in head and face size is because the craniofacial structures developed earlier. Then in later growth, structures away from the head grow more and catch up.</p>
<p>This is called the cephalocaudal gradient of growth, and it's an important part of the human growth pattern that you need to always keep in mind.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="357" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Rates by Tissue Type: Scammon's Curves</title><pageText><p>Part of the reason for the changes in bodily proportions is that the major tissue types in the body have very different growth curves--that is, they don't all grow at the same time or rate. This is shown in the classic graph of "Scammon's curves".</p>
<p>Note first the neural growth curve, which shows that neural growth, primarily brain growth, is all but complete at about age 6, with very little increase in size after that (but, of course, a lot of development). That requires rapid early growth of the cranium, which is the reason that your upper head size is so large so early.</p>
<p>It also is the reason for the cephalocaudal growth gradient, which is created by the difference in the growth rate between neural and general body growth. The general body curve flattens out during the elementary school years and then has an increased in growth rate at adolescence, which is very much related to the rapid growth in the genital tissues at that time. The lymphoid curve may surprise you: rapid early growth, a peak at 10-12 years with almost twice as much lymphoid tissue then as you will have as an adult, and loss of tissue over the next 10 years--a good example of a growth curve that shows negative growth. </p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Scammon's curves   <i><b>﻿pick up from other location, to be specified</b></i></label><caption><p>The growth curves for four major tissue types, showing the path from birth to early adult life at about age 20.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Pattern: Cephalocaudal Gradient</title><pageText><p>Even within the head and face, the cephalocaudal gradient of growth leads to changes in proportionality during growth. When the skull of a newborn is compared to that of an adult, it is easy to see that postnatally there has been more growth of the face than the cranium. As we have noted, this reflects the early growth of the brain. The cranium, the part of the head that serves to protect the brain, must grow rapidly early on, and grows less later.</p>
<p>Within the face, structures closer to the brain grow more earlier and less later. Thus the mandible is less developed at an early point than the maxilla and grows more postnatally.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="593" resourceHeight="284" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_04.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_04_s.jpg"><label>Facial proportions at birth (left) and in early adult life.</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Charts</title><pageText><p>Now let's turn to the concept of variability. Obviously, everyone is not alike in the way they grow. In dealing with a child, you'll need to know if the size (growth) or development stage (complexity) is normal. How would you determine that?</p>
<p>Growth charts, expressed in percentiles, often are used to show how a patient compares to his or her peers in height and weight, and how that changes over time. In fact, many pediatricians follow their patients' growth using a chart like this, and will make it available to the dentist if he requests it.</p>
<p>The lines indicate the percentiles, the x axis is time and the y axis indicates height or weight. The charts for boys and girls are different (although the differences are surprisingly small prior to adolescence).</p>
<p>Percentiles here are used to show where a child is relative to the distribution of a very large group of American children (there are other charts like this for other population groups). For this normal girl, height and weight values plot consistently near the 50th percentile, but normal variation is relatively large. As a general guideline, a child who is between the 3rd and 97th percentiles is considered within the normal range. Outside that, abnormality must be suspected.</p>
<p>To view this chart more clearly (it's hard to make it large enough on the computer screen), look at Figure 2-4 in <i>​Contemporary Orthodontics</i>​ (5th or 6th ed.).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="321" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1_s.jpg"><label>Growth chart of American girls age 2-20</label><caption><p>Note that this particular girl has stayed at about the 75th percentile for both height and age from age 6 to age 12, which means that she is both taller and heavier than 75% of the female population. But that position in the population group is absolutely normal, and the fact that she has stayed in the same channel over that time also is an indication of a normal growth pattern.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Charts (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Normal growth is shown on a growth chart not so much by being at the 50th percentile and therefore in the middle of the normal distribution, as by maintaining about the same percentile over time. A child who plots at the 20th percentile consistently is just a small but normal child.</p>
<p>Crossing the percentiles, particularly crossing several of them, usually indicates abnormal growth and some problem. In this respect, height is a more sensitive indicator than weight.</p>
<p>Here we see the plot for a boy who developed a medical problem that affected growth at age 10, with partial recovery at age 13, but a long-term growth deficit. To see it better, look at Figure 2-4b in <i>​Contemporary Orthodontics</i>​.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="318" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart2.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart2_s.jpg"><label>Growth chart for American males age 2-20.</label><caption><p>This chart shows a change in the growth pattern in the way that the height plot and to a lesser extent, the weight plot, moved downward in the percentiles after a serious illness at age 10. He didn't grow normally for the next 3 years, then moved upward along the 20th percentile for the next year. So at least he stopped getting worse at that point.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Other Charts</title><pageText><p>Many body dimensions, not just height and weight, can be plotted against time to see if growth is normal. These plots often are done as curves for growth progress, which you have been looking at up to this point, but often are best understood as curves for growth increments per year.</p>
<p>This is a classic plot, the first of its type, showing both growth progress and growth increments for a typical French boy. What the growth increments curve shows is that there is very rapid growth in height up to about age 3, then a flattening of the growth rate to about age 8, a further decrease between age 8 to the onset of puberty at about age 11, a rapid increase in the growth rate with a peak at about age 14, and then a decline to almost no further increase in height beyond about age 18. Why the "about" statements? Because this boy is typical, but in a population group, there is considerable variation in the timing of the adolescent growth spurt.</p>
<p>Now we need to discuss this variability, understand why it occurs, and consider what it would affect the way you would evaluate the growth status of your new child or adolescent patient. </p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Growth progress and increments for De Montebielard's son  <i><b>transfer from other screen, to be specified</b></i></label><caption><p>The plot of growth increments makes it much easier to understand the fluctuations in the growth progress chart.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Timing: Description</title><pageText><p>Boys and girls get bigger over time, of course, but differences between individuals of the same age and gender, and differences between the sexes, are most notable near adolescence. That is because sexual maturation leads to an adolescent growth spurt, which you saw earlier in Scammon's curvers. This happens earlier in girls than boys and happens at different times in individuals of the same gender. On the average, girls have their adolescent growth spurt 2 years ahead of boys. That doesn't mean that all girls mature faster than all boys--there's too much individual variation for that to be true.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Growth increments shown in growth velocity curves for 3 normal girls (Fig 2-6)</label><caption><p>For these 3 normal girls, there was a considerable variability in the time of sexual maturation, and that produced quite different growth curves that ultimately ended close to the same space.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Growth Variability: Timing</title><pageText><p>This diagram plots the increase in height each year for three girls, who experienced a growth spurt at different ages because of a difference in timing of sexual maturation. The M-1, M-2 and M-3 points on each increment curve show for each girl the age  at which menses began (called menarche). Note that the rate of growth for each girl was declining by then.</p>
<p>Sometimes differences in the timing of puberty, whether an individual matures unusually early or late, causes him or her to cross percentile lines on a growth spurt during adolescence. This should not be considered an indication of a growth problem, especially if the plot for the early or late maturing preson returns toward the range where it was initially.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="460" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic2.jpg" thumbnailWidth="82" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic2_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Chronologic vs. Biologic Age</title><pageText><p>Because of timing variability, chronologic age often is not a good indicator of an individual's growth status. It is possible to measure age biologically, in terms of progress towards achievement of certain development markers.</p>
<p>For the same 3 girls whose growth velocity we just saw, it is instructive to use biologic development rather than age to compare them. In this case it is easy to do that by superimposing the three curves on the point of maximum growth velocity--and if you do that, it is easy to see that the shape of the curves are almost identical, although the early maturer grew faster during puberty than the late maturer.</p>
<p>There are many ways to use biologic landmarks rather than age in plotting growth or development, and we will be looking at several of these as we continue with an examination of the methods used to study growth.</p>
<p><i><b>move the CVM cephs to location to be specified later; only figure on this page is the superimposed growth curves = Fig 2.7, but we have it on another page to be moved here</b></i></p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="237" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s02_p13_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="66" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s02_p13_01s.jpg"><label>Image 1, an individual at CVM 4</label><caption><p>The yellow boxes surround the second, third, and fourth cervical vertebrae. The shape of these bones indicate this person is at stage 4 on the scale of Cervical Vertebral Maturation (CVM 4).</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="237" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s02_p13_02.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="66" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s02_p13_02s.jpg"><label>Image 2, an individual at CVM 5</label><caption><p>The yellow boxes surround the second, third, and fourth cervical vertebrae. The shape of these bones indicate this person is at stage 5 on the scale of Cervical Vertebral Maturation (CVM 5).</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Growth curves for 3 normal girls, superimposed on peak growth</label><caption><p>With this superimposition on peak growth, it is easy to see that the shape of the curves is quite similar, so the growth pattern was the same although timing produced a lot of variability in when it occurred.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Chronologic vs. Biologic Age (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The stages in maturation of the cervical vertebrae correlate reasonably well with the adolescent growth spurt, which is the best time for most orthodontic treatment, and determining the CVM stage can be quite helpful in deciding when to start treatment.</p>
<p>As shown below, Stage 2 indicates that peak growth at adolescence is still a year or so ahead. Stage 3 indicates that it is less than one year to peak growth, a good place to begin treatment. Stages 4, 5 and 6 are increasing distances beyond peak growth.</p>
<p>For now, you just need to understand the concept of evaluating growth using biologic markers instead of years. Later you will learn more about using both cervical vertebrae and hand-wrist bone stages to calculate skeletal age, and about how to use that knowledge to improve clinical decisions.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="234" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/timing-chrono3.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="65" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/timing-chrono3_s.jpg"><label>Stages in development of the cervical vertebrae</label><caption><p>The cervical vertebrae are seen well in a lateral cephalometric radiograph, which is needed for almost all orthodontic patients, and assessing the CVM stage is an important aspect of treatment planning for adolescents.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Timing: Biologic Age</title><pageText><p>These biologic ages also could be called developmental or maturation ages. Many different types of maturation, not just the skeletal age calculated from vertebrae or other skeletal indicators, can be determined and quantified in biologic terms. Dentists use dental age all the time, judging the state of development of the dentition against the usual chronologic markers. You will be learning about that in detail later in this course.</p>
<p>For example, from the standard charts it would be possible to calculate a height age. When you're the height of an average nine year old (just over 130 cms), your height age is 9, regardless of your chronologic age. Intellectual development can be calculated in the same way. Intellectual development relative to chronologic age usually is called IQ, for intelligence quotient, but it's just another developmental age.</p>
<p>It is interesting that the various developmental ages tend to be highly correlated. If you're bigger than other children the same age, you're probably also more developed mentally and socially. Correlated, of course, doesn't mean that this is always the case, just that it's more likely to be that way.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="393" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1_s.jpg"><label>A group of biologic growth curves, which are surprisingly correlated with each other.</label><caption><p>Note that dental age doesn't correlate well with the height curve for growth, which makes it a relatively poor predictor of the pattern for growth in height. This is your first exposure, but certainly not the last, to the idea that the stage of development of the dentition doesn't tell you very well the stage of development of other characteristics. You will hear a lot more about the clinical significance of this.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Methods for Studying Growth</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Introduction: Types of Growth Data</title><pageText><p>Growth studies may either be longitudinal or cross-sectional in design. When you look at growth data, it is important to know whether the study was longitudinal or cross-sectional.</p>
<p>In cross-sectional studies, rather than seeing the same individual at age 9,10,11, etc., data are taken for a group of 9 year olds, a different group of 10 year olds, another different group of 11 year olds, and so on. This is quicker and easier, but the amount of individual variation tends to be understated. The mean for the group (the dark line in this figure) when chronologic age is used as the time base gives a very misleading picture of what happens to any individual.</p>
<p>Longitudinal studies, in which the same individual is followed over time, provide more information about individual variation, but these studies take a long time and become quite expensive. Note that longitudinal data give a much better picture of what an individual would experience.</p>
<p>Now remember the effect of plotting the individual data with menarche as a base, which you just saw above. Using biologic age in that way with cross-sectional data can make it easier to avoid distortions due to different timing in different individuals.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="360" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="64" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_01_s.jpg"><label>Individual vs mean data for growth pattern</label><caption><p>It is clear that the mean pattern of change in growth smooths out the individual changes, which is why longitudinal rather than cross-sectional growth data gives a much clearer picture of the pattern that an individual is likely to experience.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Other Data Transformations</title><pageText><p>Various  mathematical transformations of data can make it easier to understand what is occurring during growth. In image 1, the graph showing the increase in weight of early embryos, you can see that there is an exponential acceleration in weight with increasing time.</p>
<p>In image 2, the same data are plotted after a logarithmic transformation. This shows a straight line, indicating that the rate of multiplication of individual cells remains almost constant. It's not that cells are dividing faster as the embryo gets older, it's that increasingly there are more cells to divide.</p>
<p>Many years ago, the English anatomist D'Arcy Thompson showed that mathematical transformation of a grid could account for the changes in the shape of the face from man (A) to chimpanzee (B) to monkey (C) to dog (D) or other animals. It's interesting to see how proportional the skeletal changes are.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="494" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/2-12_4thed_bluelinedel.jpg" thumbnailWidth="88" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/2-12_4thed_bluelinedel_s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Weight change during embryonic growth</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="494" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/2-12_4thed.jpg" thumbnailWidth="88" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/2-12_4thed_s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Plot of logarithm of weight change, which results in a straight line--and shows that the rate of increase in cells is the same over this amount of time.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>D'Arcy Thompson's mathematical transformation of faces  <i><b>﻿Fig 2-14 in C Orthod</b></i></label><caption><p>This technique led to recognition of previously unsuspected similarities among various primates.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Methods for Studying Growth: Growth Measurement Techniques</title><pageText><p>There are now four basic measurement techniques for physical growth:</p>
<ol><li>Craniometry</li>
<li>Anthropometry</li>
<li>Cephalometric radiography</li>
<li>3D radiography (computed tomography)</li>
</ol></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s03_p05_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s03_p05_01s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Craniometry</title><pageText><p>The science of physical anthropology began with craniometry, which is based 
on measurements of human skulls (or other bones, in which case it would be 
osteometry).</p>

<p>Although most craniometric studies have been done on the remains of populations 
from earlier times, study of contemporary skulls or other bones obviously would 
be possible. Distortions of the skull during growth can occur, and now are understood 
better after study of skeletal remains. A good example is the effect 
of premature fusion of sutures.</p>

<p>In the individual shown in image 1, the mid-sagittal 
suture fused prematurely and was entirely missing in adult life. Note 
the extremely narrow width of the cranium. In compensation, the brain 
and skull became abnormally long posteriorly. In image 2, note the effect 
of, premature fusion of sutures on the right side of the cranial base. This led to 
a marked asymmetry that affected both the cranium and cranial base. 
Once effects of this type have been noted in studies of skulls, the 
likely cause of similar asymmetries in living patients becomes apparent.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_07.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_07_s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>In this individual, an increase in width of the cranium was not possible because 
of premature fusion of the mid-sagittal suture. The result was a remarkably narrow 
cranial vault, which forced a change in the shape of the brain.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_08.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_08_s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>For this individual, premature fusion of sutures on the right side of the cranial 
base led to a major asymmetry that also affected the cranium.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Anthropometry</title><pageText><p>Anthropometry refers to measurements on living individuals. Various landmarks on the skull were established by investigators studying skeletal material, and the soft tissue points overlying those landmarks (or other soft tissue points that can be found repeatedly) can be used to study living individuals.</p>
<p>Varying soft tissue thickness introduces a source of error if the goal is to measure growth of the facial skeleton, but it is highly advantageous to follow the growth of an individual directly, making the same measurement repeatedly at different times.</p>
<p>This produces longitudinal rather than cross-sectional data and shows individual variation much more precisely. Much of what we know about cranial and facial growth was first deduced from anthropometric studies. Anthropometric measurements are still important in clinical examination of orthodontic patients. They are used now primarily to establish facial proportions--which are important in planning orthodontic treatment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="315" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_09.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_09_s.jpg"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Anthropometric measurement of bi-zygomatic width, which is important in clinical 
orthodontics because of its relationship to the width of the maxillary dental arch 
and in establishing face height-width proportions</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="315" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_10.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_10_s.jpg"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Anthropometric measurement of anterior face height, the other part of 
face height-width proportions. The relationship of face height to width 
is the "facial index".</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cephalometric Radiology</title><pageText><p>The third important measurement technique is cephalometric radiology. Using x-ray pictures of the head and face provides a way to combine the advantages of crainometry and anthropometry.</p>
<p>It allows direct measurement of the skeleton because the soft tissue thickness can be ignored—but the soft tissues also are imaged and can be measured if desired.</p>
<p>Proper positioning of the subject in a head holder is necessary (Fig. 1), so that rotation of the head to one side or up or down is avoided, and so that repeated x-rays can be made with the head positioned exactly the same. This allows longitudinal study of growth (or treatment) changes in an individual using superimposed ceph tracings.</p>
<p>Fig. 2 shows the lateral ceph for this position. What skeletal classification would you give him? Yes, he has normal jaw relationships, and that's a Class I skeletal pattern.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="300" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_11.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_11_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>The head-holder for obtaining cephalometric radiographs, which is necessary to obtain longitudinal records that can be compared accurately.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Lateral ceph of this patient</label><caption><p>You don't have to measure--just look at the facial proportions and jaw relationship--to recognize this as normal and a skeletal Class I.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cephalometric Radiology (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The disadvantages of cephalometrics are that exposure to x-rays is required, and that the radiograph is a two-dimensional representation of three-dimensional structures. Some measurements are not possible and others are distorted in projection. The recent development of cone-beam computed tomography, which greatly reduces the radiation dose to obtain 3-D images of the head and face, means that this method is likely to replace traditional cephalometrics for many purposes.</p>
<p>But cephalometric radiographs give an excellent view of many skeletal and dental structures that aren't accessible for anthropometric study, and these radiolographs are used routinely in dentistry to monitor growth and treatment of patients. A patient like this one, with too much growth of the lower jaw that is predisposing him to a Class III malocclusion (i.e., he's a skeletal Class III), has to be followed with serial cephalometric radiographs to determine the best time for treatment. You'll be learning a lot more about how to use cephalograms for purposes like this.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="448" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_12.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_12_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Lateral cephalometric radiograph of an individual with disproportionate growth of the upper and lower jaws. Serial cephs to monitor growth are an important tool in clinical treatment of problems of this type.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Newer Imaging: Computed Tomography (CT)</title><pageText><p>With newer imaging methods like computed tomography (CT), it is possible to reconstruct facial images in three dimensions.</p>
<p>Axial CT, which is used in most hospital applications, is very precise but has two problems for studies of growth: it is expensive and delivers a relatively large radiation dose.</p>
<p>The introduction of cone-beam CT (CBCT) for images of the head has offered a significant reduction in both cost and radiation, and CBCT is now an important tool in dentistry for improved diagnosis and treatment planning.  CBCT is not quite as accurate as axial CT, but its precision is adequate for most applications in dentistry, including the study of growth.</p>
<p>This CBCT view of a patient with an impacted canine makes the position of the affected tooth clear (indicated by the yellow arrow), and the image can be rotated and manipulated so you can see exactly the impacted tooth's relationship with other teeth. That information is critical in determining how to move the impacted tooth into the dental arch without bringing it into contact with other tooth roots that would damage them.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s03_p10_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s03_p10_01s.jpg"><label>3D CBCT Volume</label><caption><p>3D images like this one are valuable because hard tissue can be evaluated from multiple perspectives. Note the impacted maxillary canine (yellow arrow).</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Cone-beam CT (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Among the advantages of CBCT is that you can view either the soft tissue contours of the face or the underlying bone, can use different colors to visualize different structures (such as the maxilla and mandible), and can follow the progress of treatment with superimposition of longitudinal images.</p>
<p>For this girl with a severe facial asymmetry, CBCT imaging is a necessity for adequate diagnosis and treatment planning. In image 3, you can see that bone screws have already been used in placement of a bone graft to create a link between the mandible and skull on the left side, where the entire condylar process was missing.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Fig. 1. Frontal view, 8-year-old with major facial asymmetry  (Fig 2-9A)</label><caption><p>This patient was born with severe hemifacial microsomia that totally obliterated the mandibular ramus on the left and retarded vertical growth on the left side of the face.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>CBCT image of the facial surface (Fig 2-9B)</label><caption><p>CBCT shows the contours of the facial surface accurately, but is far from a photograph in distinguishing the various tissues that the eye can see.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>View of underlying hard tissues on the left side (Fig 2=9C)</label><caption><p>In CBCT images, it is possible to remove the soft tissue and view the underlying hard tissues, and to distinguish the skull, maxilla and mandible by using different colors.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>CB-CT Superimpositions</title><pageText><p>For growth studies, it is important to see changes over time. This requires superimposition of images of the same individual that were taken at different times. You have already seen how this done with cephalometric  tracings.</p>
<p>That doesn't work with 3-D images, but now it is possible to superimpose on bony surface contours, and changes between sequential 3-D images can be discerned by color maps. This allows you to look at the amount of change at thousands of points that can be viewed from any orientation, instead of being limited to tens of points seen from one orientation in a cephalometric radiograph.</p>
<p>The superimposed images here show changes in the position of the jaws created in an adult by orthognathic surgery to reposition his maxilla and mandible. The green color shows no change between the superimposed images; the red color shows forward movement, our of the image toward you, and the depth of color indicates the amount (dark red= 5 mm change); and the blue color shows movement away from you, into the screen (dark blue = 5 mm). </p>
<p>So the surgery brought the maxilla forward 5 mm in the deficient paranasal area on the patient's right side, but rotated it transversely so that the left side came forward only about 3 mm, also rotated it down anteriorly so that the teeth came forward only about 1 mm. The mandible was rotated up and back posteriorly, with more retraction of the teeth than the chin.</p>
<p>The same superimposition of CBCT images can be used to show the details of growth changes, but the radiation means that images of no benefit to the individual cannot be justified--so there are no CBCT studies of growth in untreated individuals and there will not be any.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="447" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s03_p11_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="79" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s03_p11_01s.jpg"><label>Cone Beam CT Superimposition</label><caption><p>Changes created by surgery to advance the maxilla and set back the mandible in this patient. The colors reveal the areas that were changed and the intensity of the color shows the amount of change. </p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Experimental Methods in the Study of Growth</title><pageText><p>The second way to study growth is with marker techniques. These are classic experimental methods for studying growth. Using these methods, it is possible to follow either processes or physical changes by visualizing the marker. Most of these techniques are used in animal studies because the analysis may be destructive.</p>
<p>The marker techniques include:</p>
<ol>
<li>Vital staining</li>
<li>Autoradiography</li>
<li>Cephalometric superimposition on Implants</li>
<li>Molecular biology</li>
</ol></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Vital Staining</title><pageText><p>In vital staining, dyes that are incorporated into bone (or sometimes other tissues) are injected into animals. Bone that was growing at the time the dye was injected is stained, and the amount of growth between two injections or since the last injection can be seen.</p>
<p>The technique goes back to the famous English anatomist John Hunter, who observed that the dyes in textile wastes fed to pigs stained their bones in interesting ways. He experimented to find which dyes were best for staining bone. Alizarin proved to be best.</p>
<p>This young rat had four injections of alizarin dye at 2-week intervals, first red, then blue, then red again, then blue again. The dye is excreted rapidly, so the staining occurs during only a few hours after each injection.</p>
<p>As you look carefully at the mandible (image A, the condylar process is in the center), you can see the sequential bands of color. The white bone at the tip of the condylar process grew there since the last injection. Both the sites of growth and the rate of growth in various areas can be seen. The sites of growth are the areas where new bone is being formed or removed by remodeling that accompanies bone growth. The rate of growth is shown by the distance between bands of color that were deposited at known times when the dye was injected.</p>
<p>Image B shows the zygomatic arch. Note that new bone is being formed on the outside of the arch, while bone is being resorbed on the inside. The arch is growing outward by being constantly remodeled. In a view like this one, you can not only see where changes are occurring, you can tell how quickly if you know the timing of injections of the dye.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="351" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="62" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_17_s.jpg"><label>Vital Staining of (A) mandible and (B) zygomatic arch</label><caption><p>Bands of alizarin staining in this preparation of the ramus of the mandible (A) indicate where bone was forming at the time of the injection. Note the white unstained bone at the tip of the coronoid and condylar processes and on the outer surface of the zygomatic arch. This is bone that was formed in the last 2 weeks, after the final injection.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Vital staining of developing teeth</title><pageText><p>It is interesting (and distressing) that inadvertent vital staining of teeth can occur when some medications are used in young children. The image here shows the effect of the antibiotic tetracycline, which produced a band of color across the maxillary incisors that were forming while this boy was being treated for repeated respiratory infections in early childhood.</p>
<p>Tetracyclines are not used much any more, for obvious reasons. Veneers to cover the facial surface of those teeth would be the modern treatment for this condition. This patient's dental staining is much more severe than most, but stained lines across the teeth developed in many children who had tetracycline treatment. You should recognize what happened when you see a line like that--which now would be created by a different drug but can still happen.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="575" resourceHeight="323" resourceLocation="images/placeholder.jpg" thumbnailWidth="142" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="images/placeholder_s.jpg"><label>Severe tetracycline staining of teeth  <i><b>﻿Fig 2-16 in C Orthod</b></i></label><caption><p>Note the dark purple areas of staining of both maxillary and mandibular incisors, which is impossible to remove because the color is incorporated into the tooth. It's not just on the surface.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Autoradiography</title><pageText><p>Autoradiography is based on causing tissues to take their own pictures. Radioactively labeled substances are injected, tissue specimens are prepared, and when photographic film is exposed by placing it over the tissue specimen in the dark, the location of radioactive materials in the tissue is revealed as radiation activates silver grains in the film layer.</p>
<p>This is an autoradiograph of a small bone that was growing in organ culture. Tritium-labelled thymidine was incorporated into the culture medium, and was taken up when DNA of new cells was formed at the time of cell division. The black dots are nuclei that contain the labeled thymidine, which means they must have been formed by cell division that occurred since the tritiated thymidine was added to the culture medium.</p>
<p>In this experiment, carbon 14-labelled proline also was added to the medium. Proline, an amino acid, is a major constituent of collagen, which in turn is the major component of connective tissues and bone matrix. The dark label away from the cell nuclei shows where proline is being incorporated into newly-formed collagen, and therefore shows where collagen formation is taking place. Note that it is most active in the area where maturing collagen is being replaced by bone spicules. With radioactive labeling, essentially any substance can be turned into the equivalent of a vital stain.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="394" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_18.jpg" thumbnailWidth="122" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_18_s.jpg"><label>Autoradiograph, looking through a film layer at the tissue below</label><caption><p>The black dots are over cells in which radioactive thymidine was taken into the cell when it divided while growing; the generally darkened areas show where labeled proline was incorporated into new bone.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Implant Radiology</title><pageText><p>Implant radiology is based on visualizing metal pins placed in the skeleton. Perhaps you know that when bones are fractured, metal pins often are placed to hold them while they heal, and often the pins are left in place. A long time after the fracture has healed, the pin will still be visible on a radiograph as a marker of the fracture site. It is possible experimentally to place small metallic implants in bones anywhere in the skeleton, including the face and jaws, as permanent markers.</p>
<p>This girl has small pieces of tantalum wire in her jaws, placed in areas where little growth occurs, as markers, so that the changes in jaw contours as she grows can be followed more precisely. The implants were placed from inside the mouth by anesthetizing the muscosa over the area where the implant is to be placed, then using small spring-loaded device to drive the implant through the soft tissue into the bone. It is a simple and painless procedure. When another cephalogram is taken later, one can superimpose on the markers, and then changes due to remodeling of the surfaces of the bone can be seen clearly.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="455" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/img2-17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="81" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/img2-17_s.jpg"><label>Cephalometric radiograph with implant markers</label><caption><p>This technique was used in classic growth studies in the mid-20th century--that cannot be repeated now because of restrictions on radiation exposure.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Implant Radiology (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Implants have been placed in a number of children whose growth pattern was followed 
longitudinally, using cephalometric x-rays to detect the location of the pins. Then the 
pins were used to superimpose the outline of the jaws, so that growth changes could be 
seen relative to the pins.</p>

<p>This method was originated by Professor Bjork in Copenhagen, and has been responsible 
for much of our current understanding of jaw growth patterns. In this superimposition on 
pins in the mandible, you can see that bone was added to the posterior surface of the 
ramus and to the condylar and coronoid processes, but was removed from the gonial angle 
area. Note also that a great deal of remodeling of the condyles occurred. What was once 
the condyle at age 4 became a part of the ramus at age 10, and then was partially resorbed 
away as the condylar process continued to grow upward. Note also how the teeth erupted 
upward and forward relative to the pins in stable areas of the bone. Until cephalometric 
superimpositions on markers was done, the large amount of remodeling of the bone as the 
jaws grew had not been appreciated.</p>

<p>You'll be seeing more tracings of cephalometric radiographs superimposed on implants 
in the future, and you must understand the concept.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_15.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_15_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Molecular Techniques</title><pageText><p>It also is possible to use the techniques of molecular biology to study growth, and 
this holds great promise for the near future. An example of such methods is diagrammed 
on this slide. Genetic information carried by plasmids can be injected into the nucleus 
of a mouse egg, which is then implanted into a pseudopregnant mouse.</p>

<p>When the mouse gives birth, if the new genetic information is active and has been copied, 
the progeny have foreign DNA and are known as transgenic mice. These genetically-altered mice 
can be examined for morphologic differences, extracts can be made to test for inactivated 
hormones or enzymes, etc.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="123" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_16.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="34" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_16_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Molecular Techniques (cont.)</title><pageText><p>One of these mice strains was injected with a plasmid carrying genes coding for growth 
hormone. The impressively large size of the animal on the left confirms the activity of this 
genetic information in these transgenic mice. Because normal growth patterns are so precise 
and specific, genetic control is obvious.</p>

<p>Experiments of this type have great promise in explaining exactly how the control 
is mediated.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="150" resourceHeight="175" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/mice.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/mice_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary</title><pageText><p>In studies of growth and development:</p>
<ul>
<li>growth (increase in size) and development (increase in complexity with specialization and loss of potential) are different concepts</li>
<li>growth pattern refers to predictable changes in bodily or craniofacial proportions with growth</li>
<li>children outside the 3rd and 97th percentiles on standard growth charts may be beyond normal variation</li>
<li>the timing of adolescence is a major contributor to variability in growth</li>
<li>biologic ages based on physiologic events can be used to reduce variation related to timing</li>
<li>experiments with animal models continue to reveal insights into growth and its control</li>
</ul></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Summary (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Important measurement techniques to know:</p>
<ul><li>Craniometry</li>
<li>Anthropometry</li>
<li>Cephalometric radiology</li>
<li>Cone-beam CT</li>
</ul><p>Remember: the timing of adolescence is a major contributor to variability in growth</p>

<p>Cross-sectional growth studies:</p>
<ul><li>quicker, less expensive, less precise in detecting typical timing fluctuations</li>
</ul><p>Longitudinal growth studies:</p>
<ul><li>slow, expensive and hard to maintain, very efficient and excellent in showing details</li>
</ul><p>Experimental marker techniques to know:</p>
<ul><li>vital staining</li>
<li>autoradiography</li>
<li>implant superimposition </li>
</ul><p>Molecular biology techniques: The way of the future in growth studies.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Referral to Self-Test</title><pageText><p>The self-test section of this program is designed to help you be sure you have understood the material.</p>
<p>Now that you have gone through the module, do the assigned reading in <i>Contemporary Orthodontics </i>(pages 20-33 in the 5th ed.; pages 18-29, 6th ed.) Then take the self-test, and use it as a guide for further study and review. You should be sure you understand the correct answer to all questions that you didn't get right on your first try.</p>
<p>Remember, there's no grading of self-tests--they are there just to help you learn--but the questions for the exam that is graded are very similar to those of the self-test. Ample experience has confirmed that if you do the self-tests and read the assigned pages in the textbook, you will do very well on the exam. And if you don't ...</p>
<p>Copyright 2018, UNC Dept. of Orthodontics</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>(A) Anthropometric data are preferred over craniometric data in the study of 
growth because (B) soft tissue rather than hard tissue landmarks are used in 
craniometric studies.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, anthropometric data are preferred over craniometric data in growth 
studies, not because soft tissue landmarks are used in anthropometry, but because 
they are (or can be) longitudinal rather than cross-sectional. Craniometric data, 
which are obtained from skulls (no soft tissue available), always are cross-sectional. 
The soft tissue landmarks are a disadvantage of anthropometry for studies of skeletal 
growth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong! It's true that anthropometric data are preferred over craniometric 
data in growth studies, and false that craniometry uses soft tissue landmarks. 
Anthropometric data are presferred, not because of the soft tissue landmarks, but 
because they are (or can be) longitudinal rather than cross-sectional. Craniometric 
data, which are obtained from skulls (no soft tissue available), always are 
cross-sectional. The soft tissue landmarks are a disadvantage of anthropometry for 
studies of skeletal growth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="315" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_09.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_09_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Anthropometric measurement of bi-zygomatic width, which is important in clinical 
orthodontics because of its relationship to the width of the maxillary dental arch and 
in establishing face height-width proportions</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="315" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_10.jpg" thumbnailWidth="56" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_10_s.jpg"><label/><caption><p>Anthropometric measurement of anterior face height, the other part of the face 
height-width proportionality.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>In fetal and postnatal growth, what is meant by the "cephalocaudal gradient 
of growth?"</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>head grows faster than trunk and limbs</choice><choice>trunk and limbs grow faster than head</choice><choice>cephalic structures are more important for growth</choice><choice>caudal structures are more important for growth</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. In very early (embryonic) development, the cranium represents 25% of 
the whole individual, and the head about half. From then on, the trunk and limbs grow 
faster than the head, and the face more than the cranium.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. In very early (embryonic) development, the cranium represents 25% of 
the whole individual, and the head about half. From then on, the trunk and limbs grow 
faster than the head, and the face more than the cranium. The cranium and head aren't 
more or less important than the other structures, they just grow at different times.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="357" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>How would you establish a child's reading age?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>compare against standards for social development</choice><choice>compare against standards for reading development</choice><choice>evaluate with scores of standard IQ tests</choice><choice>not possible, developmental ages relate to physical characteristics only</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, there are standards for reading development just as there are 
standards for development on other physical and social-psychological scales. A 
child can be advanced or slow in reading just as he or she could be in physical 
development. It's interesting that the different types of development are 
highly correlated.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's incorrect. There are standards for emotional development just as there 
are standards for development on other physical and social-psychological scales, and 
a child can be evaluated in relation to those scales. A child can be advanced or slow 
in emotional development just as he or she could be in physical development.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="393" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is the most appropriate description of the concept 
of pattern in growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>proportional size relationships</choice><choice>changes in proportions over time</choice><choice>conservation of proportions as size increases</choice><choice>changes in proportions as size increases</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. Pattern in growth refers to the way in which proportional relationships 
change (or are maintained) as the individual changes over time (whether or not he gets 
bigger). The changing proportions of the face describe its growth pattern.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. Pattern in growth refers to the way in which proportional relationships 
change (or are maintained) as the individual changes over time (whether or not he gets 
bigger). There is a pattern in the size relationships of parts at any one time, but that 
isn't the growth pattern. And everything doesn't have to get bigger as you grow. The 
changing proportions of the face describe its growth pattern.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_01.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_01_s.jpg"><label>Newborn</label><caption>Newborn</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_02.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_02_s.jpg"><label>Age 8</label><caption>Age 8</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_03_s.jpg"><label>Young adult</label><caption>Young adult</caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="262" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_04.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="73" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/01_04_s.jpg"><label>All together</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>On growth charts with 6-month data plots, what is the significance of a 
child "crossing the percentiles" downward?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>indicates growth disturbance, perhaps chronic illness or chronic problem</choice><choice>Indicates increasingly active growth, perhaps tumor</choice><choice>no significance over this period of time, quick changes more important</choice><choice>no significance, changes in channels typically occur during normal growth</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, a downward movement across the percentile channels over a 6 month 
period indicates a growth disturbance and raises the question of some chronic illness 
or other chronic problem. A normal child usually stays within his or her channel.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. A decrease in the percentile channels over a 6 month period 
indicates a growth disturbance and raises the question of some chronic illness or 
other chronic problem. A normal child usually stays within his or her channel. Note 
the effect of growth hormone (HGH) deficiency in the plot for this child, and then 
the catch-up effect of administering the hormone.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>(A) Girls grow earlier than boys at adolescence because (B) girls mature 
sexually earlier than boys.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. As a group, girls grow earlier than boys at adolescence, and the 
reason is their earlier sexual maturation. In an important sense, adolescence and 
adolescent growth is a sexual phenomenon.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, you're wrong. As a group, girls grow earlier than boys at adolescence, and the 
reason is their earlier sexual maturation. In an important sense, adolescence is a 
sexual phenomenon. The group tendency, of course, doesn't mean that every individual 
is that way. Some boys mature before some girls.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is not appropriately described as growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>increase in size</choice><choice>increase in number</choice><choice>increase in complexity</choice><choice>increase in specialization</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct. Growth refers to an increase in size, number or occasionally complexity, 
but not to increased specialization. The term "development" often is used to 
describe an increase in specialization of biologic functions, but sometimes it is used 
to describe an increase in complexity--so sometimes there is an overlap with growth, 
sometimes there isn't.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. Growth refers to an increase in size, number or occasionally complexity, but 
not to increased specialization. The term "development" often is used to describe 
an increase in specialization of biologic functions, but sometimes it is used to describe 
an increase in complexity--so sometimes there is an overlap with growth, sometimes there isn't.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s01_p03_02.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s01_p03_02s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>The value of implants, such as metallic pins placed in the jaws, in radiographic 
studies of growth is that:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>the implants mark areas of bone that are growing</choice><choice>the implants mark areas of bone that are remodeling</choice><choice>the implants mark areas of bone that are not growing or remodeling</choice><choice>the implants outline areas of bone of particular interest so they can be evaluated</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct, the implants mark areas that are not growing or remodeling. This 
provides stable areas for superimposition of longitudinal x-rays, and then you can 
see which other areas are changing and how much, and which areas are not changing. 
As this superimposition on implants in the mandible shows, implant studies are an 
excellent way to determine the changing proportions that define the growth pattern.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's not the best answer, implants do that only indirectly. The implants mark 
areas that are not growing or remodeling. This provides stable areas for superimposition 
of longitudinal x-rays, and then you can see which areas are changing and how much, and 
which areas are not changing. As this superimposition on implants in the mandible shows, 
implant studies are an excellent way to determine the changing proportions that define 
the growth pattern.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>What percentage of a normally distributed population is within two standard 
deviations of the mean?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>50%</choice><choice>66%</choice><choice>78%</choice><choice>87%</choice><choice>95%</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, 95% of the population are within two standard deviations of the mean, 
and 99% are within three standard deviations. But when you're treating patients with 
problems, you're likely to encounter individuals who are at the extremes of the 
normal distribution.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. 95% of the population are within two standard deviations of the mean, 
and 99% are within three standard deviations. But when you're treating patients with problems, you're 
likely to encounter individuals who are at the extremes of the normal distribution. Sometimes 
doctors begin to think that almost everybody is abnormal, because they see so many of the 
extreme variations.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s02_p06_02.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/s02_p06_02s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>How do vital stains contribute to the study of growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>stain everything that was present when they were administered</choice><choice>stain everything that was growing when they were administered</choice><choice>stain everything that grew after they were administered</choice><choice>stain specific things that were growing at the time they were administered</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct. A vital stain marks specific things that were growing when it was 
administered, for instance, the bone that was being laid down at that time. Different 
vital stains are used for different tissues. If it stained everything, you couldn't 
distinguish one structure from another.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. A vital stain marks specific things that were growing when 
it was administered, for instance, the bone that was being laid down at that 
time. Different vital stains are used for different tissues. If it stained everything, 
you couldn't distinguish one structure from another.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="351" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="62" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_17_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 11</title><pageText><p>Within the face, the postnatal cephalocaudal gradient of growth predicts that:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>the face grows faster than the cranium</choice><choice>the mandible grows faster than the maxilla</choice><choice>the maxilla grows faster than the cranium</choice><choice>all of the above</choice><choice>none of the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. The cephalocaudal gradient of growth predicts (correctly) that a structure further 
away from the cranium grow faster than one closer to it. So in postnatal life both jaws grow faster 
than the cranium and the mandible grows faster than the maxilla.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. The cephalocaudel gradient of growth predicts (correctly) that the structures 
further away from the cranium grow faster than those closer to it, so in postnatal life both 
jaws grow faster than the cranium and the mandible grows faster than the maxilla.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="357" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/02_03_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 12</title><pageText><p>If a girl's bone age is 12, what is her chronologic age most likely to be?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>10</choice><choice>11</choice><choice>12</choice><choice>13</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right, the greatest probability is that the developmental age matches 
the chronologic age. That's how the developmental age was established. But for any 
individual, the chronologic and developmental ages may or may not coincide.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. The greatest probability is that the developmental age matches 
the chronologic age. That's how the developmental age was established. But for any 
individual, the chronologic and developmental ages may or may not coincide.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="321" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 13</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is the major disadvantage of cephalometric radiography 
in the study of growth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>requires damaging x-rays</choice><choice>requires complex head positioning equipment</choice><choice>makes it difficult to see soft tissue landmarks</choice><choice>offers a two-dimensional view of three-dimensional objects</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. All of the responses are disadvantages to some extent, but the 
biggest disadvantage is the two-dimensional view that the radiograph provides. Changes 
in distances between points that are not in the same plane will be distorted. The 
compensating advantage is that longitudinal data for skeletal dimensions can be 
obtained by superimposing tracings of serial cephalometric radiographs.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. All of the responses are disadvantages to some extent, but the 
biggest disadvantage is the two-dimensional view that the radiograph provides. Changes 
in distances between points that are not in the same plane will be distorted. The 
compensating advantage is that longitudinal data for skeletal dimensions can be 
obtained by superimposing tracings of serial cephalometric radiographs.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 14</title><pageText><p>The difference between a growth distance curve and a growth velocity curve is that:</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>distance curve plots total achieved, velocity curve plots increment</choice><choice>distance curve plots increment, velocity curve plots total achieved</choice><choice>both curves plot increment, but velocity curve magnifies it</choice><choice>both curves plot total achieved, but distance curve magnifies it</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. Distance curves plot the total growth achieved, velocity curves 
plot the growth increment since the last measurement. Both types of plots are valuable, 
depending on what you're trying to observe--but velocity plots make it easier to 
appreciate the changes that are occurring, as at adolescence.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's incorrect. Distance curves plot the total growth achieved, velocity curves 
plot the growth increment since the last measurement. Both types of plots are valuable, 
depending on what you're trying to observe—but velocity plots make it easier to 
appreciate the changes that are occurring, as at adolescence.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="508" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="90" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/03_03_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 15</title><pageText><p>(A) Longitudinal growth data are quite inefficient in terms of the amount of information 
obtained from each subject because (B) the longitudinal data highlight individual 
variations.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's right. Longitudinal data are very efficient, not inefficient, for growth studies, so 
the first statement is false. It's true that the longitudinal data highlight individual 
variations, so the second statement is true. That's another advantage of longitudinal 
versus cross-sectional data.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that's wrong. Longitudinal data are very efficient, not inefficient, for growth 
studies, so the first statement is false. It's true that the longitudinal data highlight 
individual variations, so the second statement is true. That's another advantage of 
longitudinal versus cross-sectional data.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="393" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/biologic1_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 16</title><pageText><p>What does it mean to say that a child is in the 95% percentile for height?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>she's in the shortest 5% of the population her age</choice><choice>she's in the tallest 5% of the population her age</choice><choice>she's more than two standard deviations below the mean</choice><choice>she's more than two standard deviations above the mean</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That's correct, she's in the tallest 5%, taller than 95% of her age group. But that puts 
her within two standard deviations of the mean, in her case, exactly two above.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. She's in the tallest 5% of her age group, taller than 95%. But 
that puts her exactly two standard deviations above the mean, not more than two above.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="321" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart1_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="318" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart2.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="studyphysgrowth/images/growthchart2_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>
