<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<presentation><title>Orthodontic Management of Patients with Cleft Lip and Palate</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>C.-A. Trotman, BDS, MA, MS<br/>William R. Proffit, DDS, PhD<br/>University of North Carolina</additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="clefttx/images/titlepage2.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Overview: Treatment/Facial Growth</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Overview of Treatment</title><pageText><p>From birth to late adolescence, a typical child with a cleft of the lip 
and palate (image 1) undergoes a number of treatments. Ideally, these are 
coordinated by a cleft palate/craniofacial team serving that area 
(image 2). It is important for dentists who interact with the patient’s 
family to understand the treatments and their sequencing—especially 
since you are very likely to be asked about what is happening and whether 
it sounds right to you. As an overview (image 3):</p>

<ul class="spaced"><li> In infancy, to prepare for lip repair, a dental specialist may 
do presurgical orthopedics to align the maxillary cleft segments. 
The surgeon repairs the lip and cleft palate and may place an early 
alveolar bone graft. The social worker counsels parents on future 
care. The geneticist tests for syndromes in the child and the risk 
of the parents to have another child with a cleft. The speech pathologist 
monitors speech development. The audiologist/ENT surgeon monitors 
middle ear function, because children with a cleft palate may need 
tubes in the middle ear for fluid drainage.</li>
<li> During the preadolescent or mixed dentition stage, between the 
ages of 5 and 8 years old, the patient will have a bone graft placed 
in the alveolus—alveolar bone grafting. In conjunction with 
this, there will be an initial phase of orthodontics to align the 
dentition and expand the maxillary arch.</li>
<li> Later during adolescence, there will be a second phase of orthodontics, 
and after the adolescent growth spurt is completed, the patient may 
need orthognathic surgery. Also, decisions will be made to orthodontically 
close spaces for missing teeth or maintain space so missing teeth 
can be prosthetically replaced. Finally, residual soft tissue deficiencies 
and asymmetries of the lip and nasal regions may need to be surgically 
revised by the plastic surgeon for improved esthetics.</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="286" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/03.jpg" thumbnailWidth="51" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/03_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, cleft patient</label><caption><p>Fourteen-year-old girl with typical sequelae of a treated cleft lip and palate.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="561" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/04.jpg" thumbnailWidth="100" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/04_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, cleft team</label><caption><p>Meeting of the UNC Cleft Craniofacial Center Team. Members are seen discussing 
patients’ treatment plans.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/05.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/05_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, cleft team duties</label><caption><p>Cleft treatment: who does what, when.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Overview: Facial Growth and Treatment</title><pageText><p>All the surgical procedures have the potential to adversely affect 
the patient’s facial growth—some more so than others. Data 
in support of this finding comes from adult patients who reside in 
countries where there is little or no medical treatment and who have not 
had surgical repairs. These patients have normal midfacial depth and 
height with obvious dentoalveolar adaptations in the cleft site (image 1).</p>

<p>Repair of an isolated cleft lip usually has little or no effect on facial 
growth, but repair of a palatal cleft often does. During the palate repair, 
soft tissue mucoperiosteal flaps are lifted from the cleft halves of the 
hard palate and are brought together in the midline to close the palatal 
defect. Scar tissue forms as the tissue heals. This scarring restricts 
growth of the maxilla (image 2). Modern surgical techniques do not create 
as much scar tissue as older methods, and the need for orthognathic surgery 
in adolescence for cleft patients because of maxillary deficiency 
is decreasing.</p>

<p>Another factor that influences whether a cleft patient will need orthognathic 
surgery is the patient’s inherited facial profile. In the cleft 
population as in the general population, individuals have inherited facial 
profiles that are Class I, Class II, or Class III (image 3). Those with 
Class II profiles are more able to mask the developing midfacial deficiency, 
while in those with Class I or Class III profiles, midfacial deficiency 
will be more apparent. Thus, the patient’s inherent growth pattern 
may either mask or enhance the midfacial deficiency.</p>

<p>In general, the more severe the cleft of the palate, the worse the midfacial 
deficiency after it is repaired, but the quality of the initial surgery 
is the major determining factor. Image 4 provides a summary of these factors.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="434" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/06.jpg" thumbnailWidth="110" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/06_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, adult with unrepaired cleft</label><caption><p>Note the normal facial proportions in this Sri Lankan adult with an 
unrepaired cleft lip and palate. There are dentoalveolar adaptations in the cleft 
site, but normal jaw growth occurred.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="373" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/07.jpg" thumbnailWidth="129" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/07_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, adult with repaired cleft</label><caption><p>Deficiency of the midface, as seen in these two patients—the one on the 
right is more severe—often occurs once the palate is repaired because scarring 
limits growth.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="380" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/08.jpg" thumbnailWidth="126" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/08_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, cleft patients, skeletal Class II/III</label><caption><p>Patients with Class II profiles are able to mask the midfacial deficiency. On the 
left, the Class II is due mainly to a retrognathic mandible, and on the right, a 
prognathic maxilla.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/09.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/09_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, overview</label><caption><p>Overview of growth effects of palate surgery.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Infancy/Primary Dentition</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Sequence of Cleft Treatment</title><pageText><p>An important early step in treatment is the surgical repair of the cleft 
lip. It is performed within the first 12 weeks of life by the plastic 
surgeon; to facilitate the surgery, either presurgical infant orthopedics 
or a lip adhesion may be recommended (image 1). Once the displaced cleft 
segments (image 2) are repositioned, the surgeon can repair the lip under 
less tension.</p>

<p><i>Infant Orthopedics</i></p>

<ul><li>For the baby with a unilateral cleft lip and palate, an orthopedic 
appliance is used to mold and approximate the maxillary cleft segments 
decreasing the facial asymmetry.</li>
<li> For the baby with a bilateral cleft lip and palate, a similar appliance 
is used to expand the maxillary segments and to retract and approximate 
the premaxillary segment to a more normal position (image 3). </li>
</ul><p>In the 1965-80 era, infant orthopedics was very popular; however, today 
the treatment is considered less useful than originally thought. Many 
centers have discontinued the practice. Those still in favor of it cite 
an improved lip and nasal esthetics, which appears to be true in the 
short term but is questionable in the long term. There are many different 
types of appliances. Some are removable and others are fixed to the 
maxilla with pins (image 4). Newer appliances are designed to mold the 
nasal cartilage as well as the maxillary segments.</p>

<p><i>Lip Adhesion</i></p>

<p>An alternative to molding appliances is a lip adhesion. This is a surgical 
procedure to repair the superficial skin tissues of the lip (image 5). 
This limited lip repair molds the maxillary segments, and once the segments 
are approximated, the surgeon then completes the definitive full-thickness 
repair of the lip muscles.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/10.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/10_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, overview</label><caption><p>Overview of treatment steps in infancy.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="401" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/11.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/11_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, bilateral cleft infant pre-tx</label><caption><p>Collapsed maxillary segments in a baby with a bilateral cleft lip and palate.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="409" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/12.jpg" thumbnailWidth="117" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/12_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, infant with molding appliance</label><caption><p>Orthopedic molding appliance in place to expand the maxillary segments.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="335" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/13.jpg" thumbnailWidth="60" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/13_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, effect of appliance</label><caption><p>Top: Maxillary segments fully expanded. Note the appliance is fixed to the 
maxilla with pins. Bottom: Premaxilla in position after expansion created room 
for it.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="388" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/15.jpg" thumbnailWidth="124" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/15_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, lip adhesion</label><caption><p>Lip adhesion. Superficial tissues of the lip—skin and mucosa—are 
sutured together to mold the segments prior to the definitive lip repair.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Sequence of Cleft Treatment, cont’d.</title><pageText><p>At some centers, a bone graft may be placed in the alveolus around the 
same time as the lip repair. This bony defect in the alveolar process 
requires a graft, and an important question is when the alveolus should 
be grafted. There are three possibilities:</p>

<ol><li>Now, very early as an infant (images 1, 2);</li>
<li>Late—too late—after the permanent dentition has erupted; 
and</li>
<li> In the mixed dentition before the eruption of the permanent teeth 
near the cleft site.</li>
</ol><p>Very early grafting in infancy now is rarely used because studies have 
demonstrated that the practice is detrimental to midfacial growth. Late 
grafts are very difficult to accomplish successfully. Mixed dentition 
grafts now are standard practice.</p>

<p>Another treatment that is sometimes considered during infancy is the 
use of a feeding appliance, which consists of a full-coverage palatal 
acrylic plate that occludes the palatal cleft. The thought is that occluding 
the cleft palate will improve swallowing and hence allow the baby to 
feed more effectively. As the baby grows, these plates must be remade 
to fit the palate. They are discontinued once the palate is repaired 
at around one year of age. Except in special circumstances, however, 
these appliances are not recommended because their effectiveness for 
this purpose has not been demonstrated. The nutritionist or nurse practitioner 
affiliated with the team can advise the parents on the use of special 
nipples and other techniques to maximize bottle feeding without the 
use of a feeding appliance.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="404" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/16.jpg" thumbnailWidth="119" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/16_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, Harvesting bone graft</label><caption><p>Rib graft harvested from the chest cavity of this baby.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="404" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/17.jpg" thumbnailWidth="119" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/17_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, Primary bone graft</label><caption><p>Rib bone being placed in the alveolus of this baby.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Sequence of Cleft Treatment, cont’d.</title><pageText><p>The cleft of the palate is repaired between one to two years of age (image 
1). The exact timing is controversial because the speech pathologist would 
prefer that the repair occurs early (before one year of age) so that an 
intact palate is present as speech development occurs. Conversely, the 
surgeon and orthodontist would prefer to wait until there is sufficient 
development and maturation of the hard and soft tissues to facilitate 
the surgical repair and decrease the chance of impaired growth of the 
maxilla. In most centers,the timing of the surgery has become earlier 
as surgical techniques have improved and the chance of growth problems 
has decreased. At present, the palate usually is repaired around one year 
of age.</p>

<p>The surgery involves lifting soft tissue flaps from the cleft halves of 
the palate and suturing the flaps in the midline to close the bony defect 
(image 2). Thus, the defect is closed with soft tissue only—no bone 
is placed in the midpalatal defect. There are many designs of flaps for 
lip and palate closure. For further information, see <i>Facial Clefts 
and Craniosynostosis: Principals and Management</i> (Eds: TA Turvey, KWL 
Vig, RJ Fonseca. WB Saunders Co., 1996).</p>

<p>At age 3-5 years, there may be the temptation to start orthodontic treatment 
to expand the maxillary arch. Generally, orthodontics at this age has 
little long-term effect and for that reason can be considered a waste 
of time and effort. It is better to wait until the mixed dentition, when 
the permanent incisors and first molars have erupted.</p>

<p>During the preschool years, the child will attend regular team evaluations 
and may have other treatments, such as general dental care and surgeries 
to improve soft palate function, middle ear function (the insertion of 
ear tubes), and lip function and esthetics.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/18.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/18_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, schematic of palate repair</label><caption><p>Diagrammatic view of palate closure. Soft tissue flaps are lifted from the 
palatal halves and sutured in the midline. Note a cleft still remains in the 
bone of the alveolus.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="521" resourceHeight="400" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/19.jpg" thumbnailWidth="104" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/19_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, steps in palate repair</label><caption><p>
A. Outline of incisions are drawn on the tissues (broken line).<br/>
B. Incisions are made and palatal tissues undermined to release the palatal muscles.<br/>
C. Muscles are sutured in the midline.<br/>
D. Overlying skin is sutured to complete the operation.
</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/20.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/20_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, overview</label><caption><p>Overview of treatment age 1-5.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Preadolescent/Mixed Dentition</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Alveolar Graft</title><pageText><p>At around 6 to 8 years of age, if an <b>early</b> alveolar bone graft 
(as an infant) was not placed—and most likely it would not have 
been—then the child is assessed for the proper time to place an 
alveolar bone graft (image 1). Grafting in the mixed dentition is the 
most common practice. Support for this practice comes from studies that 
show minimal effects on midfacial growth from alveolar graft surgery at 
this age. This is because much of the growth of the maxilla (especially 
in width) has already occurred, so the surgery has little negative impact.</p>

<p>In the mixed dentition, just about every child with a cleft has malaligned 
maxillary incisors, and often there is collapse of the posterior segments 
(image 2). The graft is timed either for the eruption of the permanent 
lateral incisor near the cleft site—grafting closer to 6 to 7 years 
of age—or the permanent canine—grafting closer to 7 to 8 years 
of age. In most cases, the lateral incisor near the cleft is missing, 
so it is more common to graft for the canine around 7 to 8 years (image 
2). The graft <i>must</i> be placed before the specific tooth has erupted 
through the bone.</p>

<p>Alveolar bone grafting at this time is generally done in conjunction 
with a first phase of orthodontic treatment. There are two reasons for 
the phase I treatment:</p>

<ol><li> to bring the incisors into position (often they are rotated when 
they erupt, due to stretching of the tissues during palate repair),</li>
<li>and, more important,, to prepare the maxillary arch for the alveolar 
bone graft.</li>
</ol></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/21.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/21_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, overview</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/22.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/22_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, cleft grafting</label><caption><p>If a permanent tooth erupts through the area of an alveolar cleft after a 
graft has been placed, it brings bone with it, and the cleft is obliterated.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Tina S., Age 7 1/2</title><pageText><p>Consider Tina, a 7 1/2-year-old girl with a left unilateral cleft of the 
lip and palate that was repaired in infancy. In the full face view (image 1), 
you can see the lip scar and the difference in shape of the nostril between 
the affected and normal sides. For Tina, both the lip and nose are not 
major problems. Revision of the lip and/or nostril are major reasons for 
additional plastic surgery in children with clefts.</p>

<p>In the profile view (image 2), you can see that she has a straight profile, 
with full lips and less prominence of the midface than is normal for a 
child of this age. The cephalometric radiograph (image 3) and tracing 
(image 4) confirm moderate midface deficiency due to restricted maxillary 
growth, which is almost surely the result of scarring after the palate 
repair.</p>

<p>A periapical radiograph of the cleft area (image 5) shows that the cleft 
of the alveolus extends through the area where the lateral incisors should 
be. Both maxillary lateral incisors are missing.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="268" resourceHeight="376" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/23a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/23a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, full face view</label><caption><p>Tina, age 7 1/2, after cleft surgery in infancy.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="211" resourceHeight="349" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/23b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="48" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/23b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, profile view</label><caption><p>Tina, age 7 1/2, after cleft surgery in infancy.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="321" resourceHeight="271" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/24a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="95" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/24a_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, lateral ceph</label><caption><p>Tina, age 7 1/2, after cleft surgery in infancy.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="252" resourceHeight="300" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/24b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="67" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/24b_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, ceph tracing</label><caption><p>Cephalometric tracing: moderate maxillary deficiency.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="166" resourceHeight="246" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/25.jpg" thumbnailWidth="54" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/25_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, radiograph, cleft area</label><caption><p>Periapical view of the incisor near the cleft site, showing a thin layer of 
bone lining the root and separating it from the cleft site. The lateral incisors 
are missing bilaterally.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Tina S., Age 7 1/2</title><pageText><p>Intraorally, on the cleft side, the permanent central incisor has erupted 
rotated nearly 90 degrees (images 1, 2). This often occurs, presumably 
because of stretching of tissues during repair of the palatal cleft. The 
cleft through the alveolar process, closed only by soft tissue and 
extending up into the base of the nose, can be seen clearly. Note that 
the maxillary dental arch is somewhat V-shaped, because the posterior 
segment on the cleft side is rotated toward the midline as it approaches 
the alveolar cleft (image 2).</p>

<p>The dental occlusion on the noncleft side is essentially normal (image 
3), but there is a posterior crossbite tendency on the cleft side, more 
pronounced in the canine region (image 4). This also is related to scar 
tissue that restricts transverse growth of the repaired palate.</p>

<p>The panoramic radiograph shows that root formation of the permanent canine 
on the cleft side has begun, with about 1/3 of the root already 
completed—so eruptive movement of this tooth has started (image 5). 
Eruption does not occur until root formation begins.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="398" resourceHeight="259" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/26a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/26a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal</label><caption><p>Severe rotation of the incisors on the cleft side often is noted when 
these teeth begin to erupt.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="384" resourceHeight="269" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/26b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="114" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/26b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, maxillary occlusal</label><caption><p>Note the inward rotation of the posterior segment of the dental arch 
on the cleft side.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="400" resourceHeight="248" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/26c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="129" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/26c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, right lateral</label><caption><p>Occlusion is normal on the noncleft side.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="400" resourceHeight="268" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/26d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="119" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/26d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, left lateral</label><caption><p>Posterior crossbite on the cleft side, more in the canine than the molar region.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/27.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/27_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, panoramic radiograph</label><caption><p>Note the cleft through the alveolar process and the beginning of root 
development of the permanent canine on the cleft side.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Tina S., Problems/Plan</title><pageText><p>Tina’s problems are summarized in image 1. At this point, alignment 
of the rotated central incisors and expansion in the canine region are 
needed, but the key factor is placement of a bone graft to the cleft area 
of the alveolar process. This must be timed so that the maxillary canine 
will erupt through it. For Tina, because of the root development of the 
canine—over 1/3 of the root of the canine was developed—there 
was not enough time for pregraft orthodontic alignment, and the graft 
was placed at age 7 years, 11 months. The surgical steps involved in 
alveolar grafting are shown in image 2.</p>

<p>The bone for the graft can be harvested from either the patient’s 
hip or cranium, after which it is ground into bone chips. Once the site 
has been surgically prepared, the bone chips are packed into the area. 
The postgraft panoramic radiograph shows the material packed into the 
cleft, with the canine poised to erupt through this area (image 3).</p>

<p>The purpose of any bone graft is to stimulate its own replacement with 
new bone. As the canine erupts through the grafted area, it brings bone 
with it so that the graft site is completely remodeled. This creates an 
intact maxillary arch much more successfully than trying to graft an 
alveolar defect after the teeth have erupted and also provides sound 
periodontal support for the erupted canine. Delaying the graft until after 
the canine has erupted will result in poor periodontal support for the 
canine. The bone graft also serves to elevate the base of the nose, 
improving the esthetics of the nasolabial area (images 4, 5).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/28.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/28_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, problem list/plan</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="533" resourceHeight="400" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/29.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/29_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, steps in alveolar graft</label><caption><p>
A. Outline of incisions are drawn on the tissues (broken line).<br/>
B. Flaps are reflected buccally and palatally through the cleft and the 
nasal mucosa is sutured together to form a base for the bone graft.<br/>
C. Bone chips are placed in the cleft site and a buccal flap is lifted, 
the tissues undermined, and the flap is used to close the alveolar cleft.<br/>
D. The buccal and palatal tissues are sutured to complete the operation.
</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/30.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/30_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, postgraft pan</label><caption><p>Postgraft panoramic radiograph. The canine now is beginning to erupt toward 
the grafted area.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="409" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/31.jpg" thumbnailWidth="117" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/31_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, facial change</label><caption><p>Facial appearance pre- and postgraft. The improved contour of the nostril on 
the cleft side is due to better support of its base.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="414" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/32.jpg" thumbnailWidth="116" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/32_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, profile change</label><caption><p>Profile appearance before/after graft: minimal change.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Tina S., Treatment Sequence</title><pageText><p>Following the placement of the graft, at age 8 1/2, phase 1 orthodontic 
treatment was started for Tina, with the goal of correcting the severe 
rotation of the maxillary right central incisor and bringing the central 
incisors to the midline. Initially, a flexible rectangular wire (NiTi) 
attached to the central incisors and molars was used (images 1-4).</p>

<p>Incisor alignment may occur either before or after the grafting. During 
incisor alignment prior to grafting, care must be exercised to avoid uprighting 
the root of the permanent incisor near the cleft so that it contacts the 
bony lining of the cleft. This would induce root resorption. Excessive 
orthodontic force will move the root into the cleft where there is no 
bone—an even worse situation. If there is any doubt, the incisors 
should be aligned after grafting to minimize iatrogenic damage to the 
root of the incisor near the cleft. In general, postgraft orthodontic 
treatment can be started soon after the graft has been placed and as long 
as the patient is comfortable enough to tolerate it.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="400" resourceHeight="250" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/33a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="128" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/33a_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, frontal view</label><caption><p>Tina, age 8 1/2 yrs, phase 1 orthodontic treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="348" resourceHeight="234" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/33b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="119" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/33b_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, maxillary occlusal</label><caption><p>Tina, age 8 1/2 yrs, phase 1 orthodontic treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="395" resourceHeight="236" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/33c.jpg" thumbnailWidth="134" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/33c_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, right lateral</label><caption><p>Tina, age 8 1/2 yrs, phase 1 orthodontic treatment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="396" resourceHeight="246" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/33d.jpg" thumbnailWidth="129" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/33d_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, left lateral</label><caption><p>Tina, age 8 1/2 yrs, phase 1 orthodontic treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Tina S., Treatment Sequence</title><pageText><p>At age 9 years, 9 months, the permanent canine was erupting through the graft 
site, and the cleft already was obliterated (image 1). With the position 
of the central incisors corrected, the brackets on the central incisors 
were removed (images 2-3) and the molar bands were left in place to help 
stabilize the removable retainer needed to control the position of the 
incisors (image 3). Soon afterward, the maxillary primary canines were 
extracted to relieve crowding and allow the permanent canines to erupt 
mesially, so that they would replace the missing lateral incisors. This 
usually is the preferred approach to the treatment of cleft patients with 
missing laterals.</p>

<p>In a patient like Tina, because eruption of the canine will occur over 
the next few months, a prosthetic tooth may be attached to the acrylic 
of the retainer for esthetic purposes. In such a situation, the retainer 
must be adjusted regularly to clear the acrylic to allow the canine to 
erupt.</p>

<p>For some patients, the graft placement may be timed for the eruption of 
the lateral incisor near the cleft site (image 4). This tooth often is 
missing, but if it is present grafting is needed earlier—typically, 
at 6 to 7 years of age and certainly before the root is 2/3 formed—so 
that it erupts through the graft site. Having a tooth erupt through the 
grafted area is the key to obliterating the alveolar defect.</p>

<p>Therefore, to reemphasize, it is important to refer a cleft patient to 
the orthodontist by the time the permanent central incisors are erupting. 
Then the final decisions can be made on the timing of graft placement, 
and the need for pregraft orthodontic treatment. The family dentist should 
not assume that surely someone else is taking care of this.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/34.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/34_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, treatment sequence</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/35.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/35_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, intraoral views</label><caption><p>Tina, age 9-9, end phase 1.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/36.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/36_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, occlusal with retainer</label><caption><p>Occlusal view, retainer in place.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/37.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/37_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, early graft indication</label><caption><p>Panoramic radiograph, lateral incisor developing: indication for early graft</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Adolescence/Early Permanent Dentition</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Adolescence/Early Permanent Dentition</title><pageText><p>Despite all the treatment provided previously, adolescent cleft patients almost 
always have some combination of three problems: (1) posterior crossbite, 
(2) spacing/crowding, and (3) skeletal problems of the long face and/or 
maxillary deficiency types. As a result, a second phase of orthodontic 
treatment is needed once the permanent teeth have erupted (image 1). If 
the early surgeries have been atraumatic with minimal scarring, the patient 
will have a minor crossbite and reasonably normal midfacial growth. Then 
routine orthodontic treatment would be undertaken.</p>

<p>This was exactly the situation for Tricia, who had a right unilateral 
cleft of the lip and palate repaired as a baby and had an alveolar bone 
graft placed at age 9 1/2 years. She presented to her orthodontist at 
age 11 years with a convex profile, and a very mild midfacial deficiency 
and asymmetry of the alar rims (image 2). Intraorally (image 3), she had 
an increased overjet and overbite, transposed maxillary right canine and 
first premolar, a supernumary right maxillary lateral incisor, and crowding 
in both arches. Her maxillary left permanent first premolar had been extracted 
previously to relieve the crowding.</p>

<p>One consideration was the region of the grafted cleft site. Because the 
canine and first premolar were transposed—an uncommon situation—the 
first premolar erupted close to the supernumary lateral incisor. However, 
there was still space remaining. The orthodontist had to decide whether 
to extract the supernumary tooth and close the space by substitution of 
the premolar or reopen the space for a prosthetic lateral incisor. A decision 
like this is based largely on the morphology of the premolar crown and 
its suitability to serve as an esthetic replacement—but in fact, 
a premolar with the lingual cusp removed can look remarkably like a lateral 
incisor from the facial view. It should be noted that it is far more common 
for the canine to be substituted for the lateral incisor.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/38.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/38_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, overview</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="410" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/39.jpg" thumbnailWidth="117" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/39_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, full face and profile views</label><caption><p>Facial appearance at age 11, after alveolar bone grafting at age 9, showing 
mild asymmetry of the nasal alae and a moderate skeletal Class II.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/40.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/40_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, occlusion</label><caption><p>Intraoral views at age 11, after alveolar bone grafting.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Adolescence/Early Permanent Dentition, cont'd.</title><pageText><p>The plan for Tricia was to extract the supernumary right lateral incisor and 
use the maxillary right first premolar as a lateral incisor, and finish 
with Class II molars. In addition, the mandibular arch was expanded to 
relieve the mild crowding.</p>

<p>Eruption of the premolar in the lateral incisor position completely obliterated 
the alveolar cleft site (image 1). At the end of orthodontic treatment, 
Tricia had excellent facial symmetry and balance (image 2). Intraorally, 
she finished with an ideal overjet and overbite and Class II molars (image 
3). A Hawley retainer was used for retention in the maxillary arch and 
a bonded lingual retainer in the mandibular arch (image 4).</p>

<p>The lateral cephalometric radiograph (image 5) showed no evidence of maxillary 
deficiency, with slight elongation of face height and a mild skeletal 
Class II due to downward-backward rotation of the mandible. Superimposition 
of the pre- and posttreatment cephalograms show that little growth occurred 
during treatment. The major treatment change during this time was that 
the mandibular incisors were uprighted as the anterior crossbite tendency 
was corrected.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/41.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/41_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, dental relationships during treatment</label><caption><p>Tricia, age 12-4. Note the obliteration of the alveolar cleft with 
good dental health.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="412" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/42.jpg" thumbnailWidth="117" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/42_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, post-tretament facial views</label><caption><p>Tricia, age 13-1, at the end of treatment. She has good facial esthetics, 
with no sign of maxillary deficiency.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/43.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/43_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, post-treatment occlusal views</label><caption><p>Occlusion at the end of treatment. With closure of the space of the missing 
lateral incisors, a Class II molar relationship is necessary and 
functionally acceptable.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/44.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/44_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, post-treatment dental relationships</label><caption><p>Occlusal views. Note the reversed positions of the canine and first premolar</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/45.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/45_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, post-treatment ceph and superimposition tracing</label><caption><p>Lateral cephalometric radiograph showing a mild skeletal Class II jaw 
relationship and superimposition showing that minimal growth occurred during 
the period of treatment.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Adolescence/Early Permanent Dentition, cont'd.</title><pageText><p>If the early surgeries resulted in enough scarring to significantly restrict 
growth, patients will have a greater midfacial deficiency and posterior 
crossbite, and orthognathic surgery to advance the maxilla and/or set 
back the mandible may be required (image 1). For these cases, orthodontics 
and orthognathic surgery are timed for late adolescence, when growth is 
essentially completed. This timing is important because surgery to reposition 
the jaws before facial growth is completed may be negated by later mandibular 
growth, so that a second surgery would be required later to correct the 
discrepancy. Generally, the age for surgery is between 16 to 18 years 
for females and 17 to 19 years for males.</p>

<p>This was the situation for Tina, whose phase 1 treatment we saw previously. 
Here she is at age 13 years 4 months (images 2, 3) . She had been followed 
without additional treatment after she discontinued the upper retainer 
at about age 11. By age 13, she was quite mature physically and in the 
permanent dentition. She was concerned about the appearance of her face 
and teeth, and anxious to get her treatment completed. Her chin was prominent 
and moderately deviated to the left, and the midface was deficient.</p>

<p>The maxillary left canine had erupted to the occlusal plane but remained 
to the lingual, out of the line of the dental arch. The lower incisors 
were mildly crowded and tipped lingually. The maxillary arch was V-shaped, 
quite narrow across the premolars and canines. With teeth missing in the 
upper but not the lower arch, the molar relationship needed to be Class 
II to provide normal occlusion, but the molars were Class I, and she had 
minimal overjet (image 4).</p>

<p>The panoramic radiograph showed normal bone in the alveolar cleft area, 
with the canine in that area having erupted down to the occlusal plane 
(image 5).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/46.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/46_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, overview</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/47.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/47_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, full face / profile view</label><caption><p>Tina, age 13-4, full face and profile. A skeletal Class III 
relationship exists.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="386" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/48.jpg" thumbnailWidth="124" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/48_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, oblique facial views</label><caption><p>The oblique facial views show the maxillary deficiency more clearly.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="392" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/49.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/49_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, occlusion / alignment</label><caption><p>The maxillary arch was quite V-shaped, constricted in the canine-premolar 
region, and she was in crossbite anteriorly and posteriorly as far as the 
first molars.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="397" resourceHeight="209" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/50.jpg" thumbnailWidth="152" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/50_s.jpg"><label>Image 5, panoramic radiograph</label><caption><p>Note the excellent obliteration of the alveolar cleft, with good bone 
support for all teeth and good dental health.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Adolescence/Early Permanent Dentition, cont'd.</title><pageText><p>Tina and her parents agreed that her concerns could not be met without 
orthognathic surgery. The plan was orthodontic treatment to align and 
coordinate the dental arches, while waiting for the completion of growth. 
The surgical plan was to advance the maxilla and set back the mandible more 
on the right than the left side, so as to bring the chin to the midline.</p>

<p>At age 14 years 6 months, because of her level of maturity and lack of 
recent growth, she was judged to be ready for surgery. Her maxillary deficiency 
and prominent/asymmetric chin were more apparent after the lower teeth 
were aligned and positioned properly relative to the mandible (images 
1, 2). The maxillary arch had been expanded to make its arch form compatible 
with the lower arch and the teeth in both arches aligned. The maxillary 
canines now substituted bilaterally for the missing maxillary lateral 
incisors (image 2). The cephalometric radiograph shows the extent of her 
skeletal Class III problem (image 3). A superimposition tracing from the 
beginning of phase 1 treatment (solid lines) shows the downward but not 
forward growth of the maxilla, with considerable downward-forward growth 
of the mandible during adolescent growth (image 4).</p>

<p>A note of caution: Surgical advancement of the midface in a cleft palate 
patient can result in leakage of air through the nose during speech, creating 
nasal “cleft palate speech” that was not present previously. 
This occurs because as the hard palate moves forward along with the rest 
of the maxilla, the soft palate is pulled forward and away from the pharyngeal 
wall. The potential for speech problems should be investigated by the 
craniofacial team before maxillary advancement surgery. For some patients, 
moving the deficient maxilla forward has such a positive effect on facial 
esthetics that it is worth doing even if secondary pharyngeal surgery 
to control speech problems might be necessary afterward. Tina was judged 
to be a minimal risk for speech problems.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="397" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/51.jpg" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/51_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, facial views</label><caption><p>Tina, age 14-4, presurgery.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/52.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/52_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, intraoral views</label><caption><p>Tina, age 14-4, presurgery.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="278" resourceHeight="268" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/53a.jpg" thumbnailWidth="83" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/53a_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, presurg ceph</label><caption><p>Tina, age 14-4, presurgery.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="306" resourceHeight="357" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/53b.jpg" thumbnailWidth="69" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/53b_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, superimposition tracing</label><caption><p>Lateral cephalometric superimpositions show the Class III growth pattern 
from age 7 to 14, with downward growth of the maxilla and downward-forward 
growth of the mandible.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Adolescence/Early Permanent Dentition, cont'd.</title><pageText><p>At surgery, a LeFort I osteotomy was used to move the maxilla forward with 
onlay graphs to the maxilla, and the mandible was moved back more on the 
left than the right sides (image 1). The screws and plates used for rigid 
internal fixation can be seen in the postsurgical radiograph. The cephalometric 
superimposition (image 2) shows the forward movement of the maxilla, with 
downward rotation anteriorly to increase the display of the maxillary 
incisors, and moderate backward movement of the chin.</p>

<p>Finishing orthodontics began 4 weeks postsurgery, and flexible arch wires 
and light elastics were used to bring the teeth into final occlusion (image 
3). The braces were removed 3 months later, at age 14 years 10 months 
(image 4), with a Class II molar relationship because of the maxillary 
space closure but good occlusion.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/54.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/54_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, pre/postsurg cephs</label><caption><p>Cephalometric radiographs before/after orthognathic surgery.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="392" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/55.jpg" thumbnailWidth="70" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/55_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, superimposition tracing</label><caption><p>Superimposition tracing before/after orthognathic surgery.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/56.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/56_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, finishing orthodontics</label><caption><p>Intraoral views showing the typical use of light vertical elastics 
postsurgically to help the patient learn to function in the new jaw relationship.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/57.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/57_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, braces off</label><caption><p>Dental alignment/occlusion at the completion of treatment. The maxillary 
canines have been shaped to simulate lateral incisors.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Adolescence/Early Permanent Dentition, cont'd.</title><pageText><p>Comparison of facial views before and after surgery make the improvement in 
her facial proportions clearly evident (images 1-3).</p>

<p>At the completion of phase 2 orthodontics (with or without orthognathic 
surgery), surgery to improve the esthetics of the lip and nose and to 
correct any residual distortions and asymmetries in these regions is considered. 
For Tina, it was not necessary.</p>

<p>On 2-year recall (image 4), there was slight transverse collapse of the 
maxilla and a mild posterior crossbite tendency, but the dental alignment 
and skeletal relationships were nicely maintained. She enjoyed an active 
social life and was quite pleased with the outcome of treatment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/58.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/58_s.jpg"><label>Image 1, smile view</label><caption><p>Tina, age 14-4 presurgery and age 16-9, 2-year recall.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="406" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/59.jpg" thumbnailWidth="118" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/59_s.jpg"><label>Image 2, oblique view</label><caption><p>Tina, age 14-4 presurgery and age 16-9, 2-year recall.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="402" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/60.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/60_s.jpg"><label>Image 3, profile view</label><caption><p>Tina, age 14-4 presurgery and age 16-9, 2-year recall.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/61.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/61_s.jpg"><label>Image 4, dentition, 2 year recall</label><caption><p>Tina, age 16-9, 2-year recall</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Summary</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Summary</title><pageText><p>In summary, patients with cleft lip and palate require numerous treatments 
during the first 20 years of life, which are summarized in the accompanying 
image.</p>

<p>Treatment procedures required by every patient are shown in yellow; procedures 
that may or may not be needed are shown in white. To maximize the benefits 
and minimize any negative consequences, it is important to properly sequence 
the various treatments. Obtaining an alveolar bone graft before the permanent 
teeth erupt in that area is particularly important and is something that 
the family dentist should keep in mind, especially if the patient’s 
family is not in close contact with a cleft palate team at that time.</p>

<p>Coordination of treatment among the group of specialists who are needed 
in the treatment of a cleft patient is best achieved by a cleft palate 
team. Such a team, a group of specialists who work together for short- 
and long-term treatment planning, exists in most metropolitan areas, usually 
in connection with the local dental school or, if there is no school, 
a major local hospital. Patients who are not being followed by a team 
should be referred to one in your area.</p>

<p>In this review you have been provided with the sequencing of treatments 
from a general perspective. It must be emphasized that your responsibility 
is to provide treatment that is in compliance with the team’s 
recommendations, and for this, you must keep in contact with the team. All 
teams provide their members, and those doctors participating in the care 
of their patients, with reports that are generated after each patient’s 
visit to the team. Recall that patients visit the team on a regular basis 
for follow-up—generally either annually or biannually. You, as the 
general dentist, should feel comfortable contacting either the team 
coordinator, director, or any member on the team for clarification of 
treatment and advice concerning the management of your patient.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/62.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/62_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Self-Test Referral</title><pageText><p>The self-test section of this program is designed to help you be sure you 
have understood the material. Take it now, and use it as a guide for 
further study and review.</p>

<p>Copyright 2003, UNC Dept. of Orthodontics</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>A) Surgery to repair a cleft of the secondary palate causes a deficiency of 
the midface because B) During the surgery bone is placed in the hard palate 
to close the defect.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the surgery to repair the palatal cleft involves lifting 
soft tissue flaps from the palatal halves and suturing the flaps in the 
midline. No bone is placed in the secondary palate during the repair. This 
surgery causes scarring of the tissues, which restricts the growth of the 
maxilla, thus a midfacial deficiency results. The extent of the scarring 
depends on the quality of the surgery—the less traumatic the surgery, 
the less the extent of midfacial deficiency.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No that’s wrong. The surgery to repair the palatal cleft involves lifting 
soft tissue flaps from the palatal halves and suturing the flaps in the 
midline. No bone is placed in the secondary palate during the repair. This 
surgery causes scarring of the tissues, which restricts the growth of the 
maxilla, thus a midfacial deficiency results. The extent of the scarring 
depends on the quality of the surgery—the less traumatic the surgery, 
the less the extent of midfacial deficiency.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="373" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/07.jpg" thumbnailWidth="129" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/07_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>A) Alveolar bone grafting in the mixed dentition is always timed for 
the eruption of the lateral incisor because B) This tooth is most likely 
to be present near the cleft site.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, an alveolar bone graft is generally timed for the 
eruption of the canine near the cleft site but may also be timed for the 
eruption of the lateral incisor, if present. Often, however, the lateral 
incisor near the cleft site is missing or so malformed that it requires 
extraction, so it is not the most likely tooth to be present near the 
cleft site.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that’s wrong. An alveolar bone graft is generally timed for the 
eruption of the canine near the cleft site but may also be timed for the 
eruption of the lateral incisor, if present. Often, however, the lateral 
incisor near the cleft site is missing or so malformed that it requires 
extraction, so it is not the most likely tooth to be present near the 
cleft site.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/27.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/27_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>To ensure the proper timing of placement of the alveolar bone graft, it is 
important for the general dentist to refer a child with an alveolar cleft 
to the orthodontist at which of the following stages?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>Soon after birth</choice><choice>Once the deciduous teeth have erupted</choice><choice>Just as the maxillary central incisors are erupting</choice><choice>In the mixed dentition</choice><choice>In the permanent dentition</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, a child with a cleft of the alveolus should be referred 
to the orthodontist just as the maxillary permanent central incisors 
are erupting. Referral at this time would ensure that the orthodontist 
has sufficient time to assess the child’s eruption status. The 
orthodontist will determine whether there is a viable lateral incisor near 
the cleft site that would require grafting at that time, or whether the 
graft could be placed  later because the lateral is missing.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. A child with a cleft of the alveolus should be referred 
to the orthodontist just as the maxillary permanent central incisors are 
erupting. Referral at this time would ensure that the orthodontist has 
sufficient time to assess the child’s eruption status. The 
orthodontist will determine whether there is a viable lateral incisor near 
the cleft site that would require grafting at that time, or whether the 
graft could be placed  later because the lateral is missing.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/26.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/26_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>A) Orthodontic treatment in the patient with a repaired cleft of the lip and 
palate is generally needed during the primary dentition because B) The collapsed 
maxillary arch must be expanded as early as possible to ensure stability.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s correct, generally it is a waste of time to start orthodontic 
treatment in the primary dentition. Expanding the maxillary arch at this 
time is not necessary and certainly will not ensure stability of the 
expansion. A retainer must be used to hold the expansion. An initial phase 
of orthodontics occurs in the early mixed dentition in conjunction with 
alveolar bone grafting. Then, there is a second phase of orthodontics 
once the permanent teeth erupt during adolescence.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. Generally it is a waste of time to start orthodontic 
treatment in the primary dentition. Expanding the maxillary arch at this 
time is not necessary and certainly will not ensure stability of the 
expansion. A retainer must be used to hold the expansion. An initial phase 
of orthodontics occurs in the early mixed dentition in conjunction with 
alveolar bone grafting. Then, there is a second phase of orthodontics 
once the permanent teeth erupt during adolescence.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>A) Palate repair in a patient with a cleft of the secondary palate should be 
delayed until at least age 2 because B) Delaying surgery to the secondary 
palate allows the tissues to mature and enhances the development of speech.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, both statements are false. There is a trade-off between 
the speech pathologist versus the surgeon and orthodontist regarding the 
timing of palatal closure. The surgeon and orthodontist would like the 
surgery delayed to allow sufficient development and maturation of the hard 
and soft tissues to facilitate the surgical repair and decrease the chance 
of impaired maxillary growth; however, the surgery is not delayed until at 
least age 2 years. It is generally performed around one year of age. This 
is because surgical techniques have improved and the chance of growth 
problems have decreased. Delaying the surgery does not enhance the 
development of speech; in fact, speech development is enhanced the earlier 
the surgery is performed.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. There is a trade-off between the speech pathologist 
versus the surgeon and orthodontist regarding the timing of palatal closure. 
The surgeon and orthodontist would like the surgery delayed to allow 
sufficient development and maturation of the hard and soft tissues to 
facilitate the surgical repair and decrease the chance of impaired 
maxillary growth; however, the surgery is not delayed for as long as 
possible. It is generally performed around one year of age. This is 
because surgical techniques have improved and the chance of growth 
problems have decreased. Delaying the surgery does not enhance the 
development of speech; in fact, speech development is enhanced the earlier 
the surgery is performed.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/18.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/18_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>Which one of the following statements is true about a presurgical infant 
orthopedic appliance?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>It is primarily a feeding appliance.</choice><choice>It is used before palate repair to mold the maxillary arch.</choice><choice>It is used to enhance speech development.</choice><choice>It is a pinned appliance.</choice><choice>It is used before lip repair to mold the maxillary segments.</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, a presurgical infant orthopedic appliance is used to 
mold the maxillary cleft segments restoring symmetry to the arch before the 
lip is repaired. The appliance is made at the request of the surgeon, and 
after the lip is repaired, it is removed. It is not a feeding appliance. 
With proper instructions to the mother, the baby can feed effectively 
without an appliance. The orthopedic appliance does not enhance speech, 
and depending on the design, the appliance may or may not be pinned 
to the maxilla.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. A presurgical infant orthopedic appliance is used to 
mold the maxillary cleft segments restoring symmetry to the arch before the 
lip is repaired. The appliance is made at the request of the surgeon, and 
after the lip is repaired, it is removed. It is not a feeding appliance. 
With proper instructions to the mother, the baby can feed effectively without 
an appliance. The orthopedic appliance does not enhance speech, and depending 
on the design, the appliance may or may not be pinned to the maxilla.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="335" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/13.jpg" thumbnailWidth="60" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/13_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>A) The key to the obliteration of an alveolar cleft is to have the tooth near 
the cleft site erupt thorough the graft because B) An erupting tooth causes 
complete remodeling and replacement of bone in the area through which it 
erupts and this process provides the erupting tooth with sound periodontal 
support.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, an alveolar cleft will be successfully obliterated when 
the tooth near the cleft site, for which the graft placement was timed, 
erupts through the grafted area and causes complete remodeling and 
replacement of bone. This eliminates the bony defect and provides the 
erupting tooth with sound periodontal support.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That's wrong. An alveolar cleft will be successfully obliterated when the tooth 
near the cleft site, for which the graft placement was timed, erupts through 
the grafted area and causes complete remodeling and replacement of bone. This 
eliminates the bony defect and provides the erupting tooth with sound 
periodontal support.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" resourceLocation="clefttx/images/22.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80" thumbnailLocation="clefttx/images/22_s.jpg"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is the most likely speech problem to result from 
maxillary advancement surgery in a patient with a cleft palate?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>Leakage of air through the nose (hypernasal speech)</choice><choice>Labiodental articulation problems</choice><choice>Blockage of air passage through the nose—hyponasal speech</choice><choice>Lisping</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the most likely speech problem to result from maxillary 
advancement surgery in a patient with a cleft palate is leakage of air 
through the nose during speech, or hypernasal speech. This occurs because 
as the hard palate moves forward along with the rest of the maxilla, the 
soft palate is pulled forward and away from the pharyngeal wall, which 
requires greater movement of the soft palate and pharyngeal wall to prevent 
excess air flow through the nose. After surgery to repair a cleft, movement 
of the soft palate is restricted, and then moving it forward can lead to 
inappropriate leakage of air.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. The most likely speech problem to result from maxillary 
advancement surgery in a patient with a cleft palate is leakage of air 
through the nose during speech, or hypernasal speech. This occurs because 
as the hard palate moves forward along with the rest of the maxilla, the 
soft palate is pulled forward and away from the pharyngeal wall, which 
requires greater movement of the soft palate and pharyngeal wall to 
prevent excess air flow through the nose. After surgery to repair a 
cleft, movement of the soft palate is restricted, and then moving it 
forward can lead to inappropriate leakage of air.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>A) For patients who have a cleft of the lip and/or palate the standard of care 
requires a team approach to the management of their care because B) Team 
treatment improves efficiency of care (patients do not have to visit 
several offices) and ensures coordinated treatment.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, the current standard of care for patients with a cleft 
of the lip and/or palate requires that a team approach to treatment is 
used with the various specialists on the team interacting together to 
ensure timely, efficient, and coordinated care for the patients. This is 
important because of the many different treatment needs of these patients.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. The current standard of care for patients with a cleft 
of the lip and/or palate requires that a team approach to treatment is used 
with the various specialists on the team interacting together to ensure 
timely, efficient, and coordinated care for the patients. This is 
important because of the many different treatment needs of these patients.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>A) Orthognathic surgery for a patient with a repaired cleft of the lip and/or 
palate is timed for late adolescence when growth is essentially completed 
because B) The patient is more likely to tolerate surgical treatment at 
this time.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That’s right, orthognathic surgery for a patient with a repaired cleft 
of the lip and/or palate is timed for late adolescence when growth is 
essentially completed because if the surgery is done earlier, before facial 
growth is completed, the outcome may be negated by later mandibular growth 
so that a second surgery would be required to correct the discrepancy. 
Tolerance for surgery is specific to the particular patient and may or may 
not be an age-related factor.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That’s wrong. Orthognathic surgery for a patient with a repaired cleft 
of the lip and/or palate is timed for late adolescence when growth is 
essentially completed because if the surgery is done earlier, before facial 
growth is completed, the outcome may be negated by later mandibular growth 
so that a second surgery would be required to correct the discrepancy. 
Tolerance for surgery is specific to the particular patient and may or 
may not be an age-related factor.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>