<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<presentation><title>Principles in Controlling Orthodontic Force</title><subtitle/><additionalInfo>William R. Proffit<br/>Dept. of Orthodontics, UNC School of Dentistry</additionalInfo><splashImage imageLocation="controlorthoforce/images/titlepage.jpg" imageWidth="600" imageHeight="450"/><sections><section><title>Elastic Materials</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Learning Objectives</title><pageText><p>As you learned from your study of the biology of orthodontics, the trick 
in moving teeth is to use the right amount of force&#8212;and almost always 
the problem is to avoid using too much force. Teeth respond best to light 
continuous force. In an orthodontic appliance, how are things arranged so 
that the force is light and at least reasonably continuous?</p>

<p>The objective of this module is to help you answer that question, from both a 
theoretical and a practical clinical perspective.</p>

<p>In addition to going through the module, read pp. 359-377 and 395-429 in the 
4th edition of Contemporary Orthodontics.</p></pageText><resources/></page><page pageType="content"><title>Precious Metals in Orthodontics</title><pageText><p>If you want to move a tooth, it&#8217;s necessary to use a spring that places 
a light but prolonged force against it&#8212;and that spring must function in 
the mouth, which is accurately described as a hostile environment. The better 
the spring, the less the force it delivers will decrease as a tooth moves. 
One possibility is a rubber band, and if you had orthodontic treatment 
yourself, you may have worn rubber bands connecting the upper and lower 
arches. Why did you have to change them every day? Because even the best 
latex materials lose their elasticity (spring quality) rapidly in the mouth.</p>

<p>The orthodontic appliances of a century ago almost had to be made with gold 
that was alloyed to be as springy as possible, because nothing else would work 
for more than a few days in the mouth, but gold is not known for its spring 
qualities. An interesting appliance from that era is the Crozat appliance 
shown in this image, which had a gold framework and gold springs that were 
slightly activated every time the patient was seen. It&#8217;s interesting 
because it still is used occasionally, by dentists who believe that if 
it&#8217;s made of precious metal, it must be better. Like many other 
antique devices, it works by tipping teeth to a new position&#8212;but 
more slowly than its modern counterparts that use steel springs.</p>

<p>Gold wires also were used with the first fixed appliances, and the edgewise 
appliance that is still the basis of modern orthodontics (which we will 
discuss in more detail below), was engineered for use with gold wires.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-01.jpg" resourceWidth="300" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-01_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Crozat appliance: removable, gold framework, gold springs</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Stainless Steel and Titanium</title><pageText><p>Stainless steel, which has excellent spring qualities, rapidly replaced gold 
when it became available for orthodontic applications. Fortunately, that 
transition was complete before the price of gold increased 10-fold in the 
1960s. More recently, nickel-titanium and beta-titanium materials have come 
into wide use. It is likely that composite plastics will replace them before 
long. Orthodontic technology trails aerospace technology by 10-20 years. As 
a fighter plane made largely with composite plastics (F-22) now is replacing 
its titanium predecessor (F-15), it&#8217;s a safe bet that use of composite 
plastics in orthodontics will follow. Like the materials in high-performance 
aircraft, orthodontic wires and attachments are extremely stressed, and it 
makes sense to use the best materials available.</p>

<p>Whatever the material, however, the same physical laws apply. Different 
materials differ in three principal properties: strength, stiffness / 
springiness (which are different terms for the same property), and range. 
These can be illustrated by a stress / strain plot, as shown here.</p>

<p>On the graph,four measures of strength are shown. The proportional limit is 
the point at which the wire begins to deviate from elastic behavior, but it 
is very difficult to establish. Yield strength, the point at which a 
measurable deviation (like 0,1%) is observed, is taken as the point at which 
the elastic limit of the material is reached and it begins to bend. This value 
is the one typically cited in reports on strength of an orthodontic wire. The 
ultimate tensile strength is the point at which the material begins to fail, 
and the failure point is where it breaks.</p>

<p>The graph also shows springiness and stiffness, which are measures of the same 
thing, as the slope of the line. Springiness = 1 / stiffness and vice versa. 
The stiffer the wire, the more vertical the line will be; the springier it is, 
the more horizontal the line will be.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-3.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="419" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-3_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="115" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Stress and strain are internal characteristics that are related as shown 
in this plot.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Force / Deflection Curves</title><pageText><p>Stress and strain are internal properties of a material. In laboratory 
experiments, the force against a material produces a deflection, and stress 
and strain can be calculated from that interaction. Force / deflection 
curves like the one shown here are what you usually will see in reports of 
material properties. These curves provide the same information as a 
stress / strain curve, as the original laboratory data.</p>

<p>What properties would you want in an elastic material to be used as an 
orthodontic spring? Think about that from the perspective of the three key 
properties seen in a force / deflection plot. You&#8217;d want...</p>

<p>...enough strength that the spring didn&#8217;t get bent out of shape. That 
would mean that the distance along the y axis to the yield point should be as 
large as possible. Note that a spring still works beyond the yield point, 
but it doesn&#8217;t totally spring back to its original position if 
it&#8217;s loaded beyond its yield point.</p>

<p>...the best possible springiness. That would mean that the slope of the line 
should be tilted to the right (i.e., more horizontal), so that the amount of 
force delivered by the spring would be as constant as possible.</p>

<p>...the best possible range. That would mean that the distance along the x axis 
at the point of permanent deformation should be as large as possible.</p>

<p>Obviously, you can&#8217;t have the maximum of all these things. A very 
strong wire would tend to be stiff and to have little range, while one with 
maximum range would tend to be quite springy but not very strong.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-2.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="440" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-2_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="109" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>A force / deflection curve, which looks just like a stress / strain curve, 
is generated by laboratory measurements and is what&#8217;s usually reported in 
the dental literature.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Force / Deflection Curve (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Another property that you are likely to see in descriptions of wire materials 
is resilience. This is the area under the curve up to the elastic limit. It 
gives a measure of a wire&#8217;s combination of the principal properties, 
and so it is likely to be used (especially in advertisements) as a way to 
emphasize the balance that the wire has among strength, springiness and range.</p>

<p>As we have noted, a spring that is deflected beyond its elastic limit still 
has spring properties, it just won&#8217;t completely return to its original 
shape. It&#8217;s easy to bend a wire beyond its elastic limit, and when you 
form the wire into some shape (bend a loop in it, for instance, as you form 
a spring to move a tooth), you&#8217;d also like some distance between the 
elastic limit and the point at which the wire breaks. In fact, to bend wires 
you must have reasonable formability, which is the area under the curve 
between ultimate tensile strength and failure.</p>

<p>Some very springy steel wires allow almost no bending beyond their elastic 
limit&#8212;they break, as one student said, if you look at them cross-eyed. 
They&#8217;re not very useful when you&#8217;re trying to form a clasp or 
finger spring for a removable appliance.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-4.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="397" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-4_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Material Effects on Wire Size</title><pageText><p>The size of a wire obviously would affect its basic properties. The bigger it 
gets, the stronger but the less springy it will be, and the less range it will 
have. This means that for orthodontic purposes there are a range of useful 
wire sizes. You don&#8217;t have to memorize those wire sizes&#8212;you can 
always look them up&#8212;but you do need to understand that concept. Steel 
is stronger than gold or titanium, so all other things being equal, smaller 
steel wires would be used for orthodontic purposes.</p>

<p>Orthodontic springs come in two forms: cantilever beams, which are attached 
only at one end (image 1), and supported beams that are attached at both 
ends (image 2). A finger spring from a removable appliance is an excellent 
example of a cantilever beam, but cantilever beams also can be used with a 
fixed appliance. The section of an arch wire between the brackets on adjacent 
teeth is a supported beam.</p>

<p>As we have said, whatever the material (with the exception of the 
superelastic materials that we will discuss next), the same laws of elastic 
behavior apply. For any orthodontic cantilever beam, the effects of changing 
its size might surprise you (image 3). Doubling the size of wire used to make 
a finger spring:</p>

<ul>
<li>increases its strength 8 times: x * 2x<sup>3</sup> = 8x strength</li>
<li>decreases its springiness 16 times: x * 2x<sup>-4</sup> = 1/16x springiness</li>
<li>decreases its range by half: x * 2x = 1/2x range</li>
</ul>

<p>Doubling the size of a supported beam produces similar but even more 
pronounced change&#8212;it puts a coefficient in front of the multiplier.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-1a.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="376" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-1a_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="128" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-1b.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="179" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-1b_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="50"><label>Image 2</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-12.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="422" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-12_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="114" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Effects of Beam Length</title><pageText><p>A second important variable in determining the principal properties of an 
orthodontic spring, whether it&#8217;s a cantilever or supported beam, is 
its length. The influence of beam length is much greater than you probably 
would have thought&#8212;unless you really paid attention in that 
pre-dental physics course or studied engineering before dental school. 
For a cantilever beam (finger spring), doubling its length:</p>

<ul>
<li>cuts its strength in half: x * 2x = &#189; strength</li>
<li>increases its springiness 8 times: x * 2x<sup>3</sup> = 8x springiness</li>
<li>increases its range 4 times: x * 2x<sup>2</sup> = 4x range</li>
</ul>

<p>It is apparent that increasing beam length produces significantly more 
increase in springiness and range than it costs in lower strength. For a 
spring, length is measured along the wire from which it is formed, not from 
where it is supported to where it ends up. So bending a loop or helix in the 
wire is a common way to gain springiness and range without reducing strength 
too much.</p>

<p>That has a very practical application. In fabricating an orthodontic 
spring, it would be smart to choose a relatively large wire size to gain 
strength, and then obtain springiness and range by making the length of wire 
longer between its attachment and its contact with a tooth. For that reason, 
it is common practice to lengthen finger springs with a helix (image 1), and 
to lengthen the effective distance between two teeth with brackets with loops 
in an arch wire (image 2).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-14.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="390" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-14_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-15a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-15a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Elastic vs. Superelastic Materials</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Superelasticity</title><pageText><p>Hooke&#8217;s law, which applies to all elastic materials, is the basis for 
the information that we just discussed. It was almost shocking when materials 
that violated Hooke&#8217;s law became available for orthodontic purposes in 
the 1980s, not so long ago. These superelastic materials have a different 
force/deflection curve from elastic materials, as shown in this image. Note 
that there is an almost flat portion in the center of the force/ deflection 
curve, with an area at the beginning and end  that looks like the curve for 
an elastic material.</p>

<p>You can see immediately that a superelastic spring that delivered the correct 
force would be quite valuable in orthodontics, because how far you deflected 
it would make little difference in the force it delivered over quite a wide 
range.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-6.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="363" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-6_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="132" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Nature of Superelasticity</title><pageText><p>How is superelasticity possible? Because superelastic materials undergo a 
phase transition with changes in temperature or internal stress. For a 
material with a transition temperature close to mouth temperature, stressing 
it by tying it to irregular teeth literally turns it into a different 
material than the one you picked up off the bracket tray. The word 
&#8220;super&#8221; is overused, often to describe trivial things. This time 
the term super is warranted. You don&#8217;t often get to see physical laws 
apparently overturned.</p>

<p>For orthodontic purposes, a nickel-titanium (NiTi) alloy with a temperature 
transition near mouth temperature is used. It is delivered in an austenitic 
phase that bends elastically when it&#8217;s first deflected (distance A-B 
on this plot), and transitions to a martensitic phase (B-C) as internal 
stress builds up. That&#8217;s the upper almost flat line in a superelastic 
force/deflection curve. Once all the austenite has changed to martensite, 
there&#8217;s again an elastic curve (C-D-E).</p>

<p>Interestingly, the force delivered by the spring differs from the force 
used to deflect it initially. If you deflect the superelastic material to 
point C1 on the graph, the recovery curve is elastic from C1 to F, then 
almost flat from F to G as martensite transitions to austenite, and elastic 
again from G to H. It&#8217;s important to realize that the force 
that&#8217;s delivered to a tooth is shown by the unloading curve, the 
lower (green) line in the plot.</p>

<p>The phase transition that makes superelastic wires so useful in modern 
orthodontics produces an exception to Hooke&#8217;s law, but 
doesn&#8217;t really repeal it. Both the austenitic and martensitic 
phases follow the law, as this plot shows, and their properties are 
affected by wire size and beam length. But that superelastic plateau 
offers a great advantage when your goal is to align crowded and 
irregular teeth.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-6.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="363" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-6_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="132" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Superelastic Wires</title><pageText><p>There&#8217;s another interesting aspect of superelastic springs: the amount 
of force they deliver can be changed by releasing a wire from a bracket on 
a tooth, and then tying or clipping it back into the bracket. The unloading 
curve changes with different degrees of initial activation (image 1). So 
there&#8217;s another magic trick with a superelastic wire. You can 
reactivate it just by releasing it and putting it back where it was. 
Clinically, that&#8217;s rarely important because the plateau is nearly 
flat anyway, but it&#8217;s an amazing property.</p>

<p>Still, even with an almost magical superelastic wire, you never escape some 
disadvantages. The formability of a superelastic wire is almost zero. The 
manufacturer can shape it by controlling temperatures as it is formed, but 
you can&#8217;t.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s interesting to contrast a superelastic force/deflection curve to 
the curve for a stainless steel wire, elastic nickel-titanium (Nitinol) 
and superelastic nickel-titanium (Chinese NiTi on this graph) (image 2). 
The superelastic wire has far greater range and much better springiness. 
For elastic wires, the activation and deactivation curves have the same 
slope; for superelastic wires, they&#8217;re different.</p>

<p>How much force would you want a superelastic spring to deliver? This is 
shown on the plot by the deactivation (unloading) segment of the curve. You 
have already learned the desired force magnitude for the various types of 
tooth movementt in your study of the biology of tooth movement. 
Superelastic orthodontic wires are particularly useful in aligning crowded 
and irregular teeth, which usually requires tipping, rotation and extrusion 
(images 3,4,5). For all these movements, the optimal force is about 50 
grams. So that&#8217;s what you&#8217;d like the superelastic wire to 
deliver during initial alignment.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-7.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="372" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-7_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="129" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Activation (solid line) and deactivation (dashed line) curves for 
a superelastic wire.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-5.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="363" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-5_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="132" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Force-deflection curves for steel, elastic NiTi and superelastic 
NiTi wires</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_14-03a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_14-03a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>Severe crowding prior to treatmen</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_14-03b.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_14-03b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>Progress, using a superelastic NiTi wire</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_14-03c.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_14-03c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 5</label><caption><p>Alignment was nearly completed without adjustment of the initial wire. 
Now a heavier wire can be employed as space closure begins.</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Design Factors in Orthodontic Appliances</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Forces and Moments in Tooth Movement</title><pageText><p>Any force against an object, unless the force is directed through the 
object&#8217;s center of resistance, also creates a moment (image 1). A 
moment, by definition, is a force (grams for our purposes, newtons in 
scientific reports)that is delivered at a distance from the center of 
resistance. Its magnitude is force x distance (gm-mm). If the object is a 
tooth, the force has to be applied to its crown, but the center of resistance 
is at about the middle of the part of the root that is encased by bone. Thus 
we can say that not only is there a force (F) when an orthodontic spring 
contacts the crown of a tooth, there also is a moment of the force 
(M<sub>F</sub>). The effect would be to displace the crown, while tipping the 
tooth so that it rotates around its center of resistance (which also is the 
center of rotation when there&#8217;s only a single force). The periodontal 
ligament would be compressed maximally at the root apex on one side and at the 
height of the alveolar crest on the other side.</p>

<p>A couple, two equal forces in opposite directions, creates a pure moment
(M<sub>C</sub>) that would rotate the object but not displace it. If you had 
equal forces in opposite directions on the corners of a box, it would just 
spin around (image 2).</p>

<p>Consider what would be required to move a tooth bodily, using a force of 
100 gm (which you have already learned is about the right magnitude for 
bodily movement). What&#8217;s the magnitude of the moment of this force? 
That depends on the distance from the point where the force is applied to 
the center of resistance. For a maxillary incisor, it&#8217;s about 
15 mm from the center of the crown (where a bracket typically would be 
placed) to the center of resistance. So now we have M<sub>F</sub> = 1500 gm-mm. 
What M<sub>C</sub> would be needed to move the tooth bodily? That&#8217;s right, 
you&#8217;d need 1500 gm-mm in the opposite direction to the moment created 
by the force against the crown (M<sub>F</sub>) so that M<sub>C</sub> cancels 
M<sub>F</sub>.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-17.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-17_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-18b.gif" resourceWidth="253" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-18b_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="45" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>A couple is a pure moment--so this object would spin around but 
would not be moved to a new location</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Effect of M<sub>C</sub>/ M<sub>F</sub> Ratio on Type of Tooth Movement</title><pageText><p>More generally, we can say that the type of tooth movement that is created 
will depend on the ratio of the moment of the couple (represented by a curved 
line in these diagrams) to the moment of the force. If M<sub>C</sub>/ 
M<sub>F</sub> is zero (image 1), the tooth tips, rotating around its center 
of resistance, and the root goes one way while the crown goes the other. As 
the M<sub>C</sub>/ M<sub>F</sub> ratio becomes positive, the tooth still 
tips, but now the center of rotation is displaced away from the center of 
resistance (image 2), so the amount that the root apex goes the other way 
from the crown decreases. When M<sub>C</sub>/ M<sub>F</sub> = 1, the tooth 
moves bodily, and now the center of rotation is displaced infinitely far 
away from the center of resistance (image 3). When MC/ MF becomes greater 
than 1, torque is created so that the root apex moves more than the crown 
(image 4) and the center of rotation is displaced beyond the crown.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22a.gif" resourceWidth="214" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22a_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="38" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>When <span class="contentText"> M<sub>C</sub>/ M<sub>F</sub></span> = 0, 
the tooth tips  around its center of resistance, so that the center of rotation 
and the center of resistance are the same</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22b.gif" resourceWidth="225" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22b_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="40" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>When <span class="contentText"> M<sub>C</sub>/ M<sub>F</sub></span> is 
&gt;0 but &lt;1, the tooth tips but the center of rotation is moved away from 
the center of resistance</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22c.gif" resourceWidth="199" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22c_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="35" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>When <span class="contentText"> M<sub>C</sub>/ M<sub>F</sub></span> is 1, 
the center of rotation is displaced infinitely far away from the center of 
resistance, and the tooth moves bodily (translates).</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22d.gif" resourceWidth="225" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22d_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="40" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>When <span class="contentText"> M<sub>C</sub>/ M<sub>F</sub></span> is 
&gt;1, the root apex moves more than the crown, and the center of rotation 
is displaced in the other direction</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Creation of a Couple</title><pageText><p>Why are fixed appliances used for almost all orthodontic treatment, and why 
is a fixed appliance almost always required if you want to do anything but 
tip a tooth? Because it takes 2 points of contact against the crown to create 
a couple, and a finger spring from a removable appliance gives you only a 
single point of contact. This produces a force and its moment that causes 
the tooth to tip around its center of resistance.</p>

<p>With great difficulty, two finger springs contacting the tooth at different 
points can create a couple, but they have to push in opposite directions 
(image 1), and that&#8217;s so difficult to arrange that it&#8217;s rarely 
practical. As image 1 shows, in theory you could put one finger spring 
against the center of the crown of an incisor, pushing it back, and another 
one against the lingual surface near the incisal edge, pushing it forward. 
That would create a couple, and because the spring at the incisal edge is 
further from the center of resistance than the one pushing against the crown, 
its force could be less. But to get a net force of 50 grams to move the tooth, 
you&#8217;d have to activate the first spring to 200 gm and the second one 
to 150 gm. Forces of that magnitude almost surely would displace the 
removable appliance. The bottom line: to do anything but tip a tooth, you 
have to have a fixed attachment and 2 points of contact.</p>

<p>How much force would be placed against the corners of a bracket if you 
wanted to move a tooth bodily in a mesio-distal direction (to close a space 
between 2 teeth, for instance)? Now we have to know M<sub>F</sub> and also 
the distance between the equal and opposite forces. Suppose you&#8217;re 
using a 100 gm force, it&#8217;s 15 mm to the center of resistance, and the 
bracket is 4 mm wide (image 2). Then M<sub>F</sub> would be 1500 gm-mm, 
and you&#8217;d need a 1500 M<sub>C</sub> to cancel it. The moment arm 
across the bracket would be 2 mm (the distance to the center of the 
bracket), and the force on each corner of the bracket to get 1500 
gm-mm would be 375 gm x 2 mm + 375 gm x 2 mm. That doesn&#8217;t sound 
like light force, does it? If the bracket were narrower, the force on 
the corners of the bracket would be proportionately larger. But if this 
couple only cancels the moment of the force, the periodontal ligament 
doesn&#8217;t feel anything but the force itself.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-18a.gif" resourceWidth="496" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-18a_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="88" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-23.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="249" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-23_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="69"><label>Image 2</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Torque</title><pageText><p>How do you create a couple to move a tooth root in a facio-lingual direction?
That type of movement, of course, is torque. The edgewise appliance was 
created by Edward Angle in the 1920s as a torquing device, and it&#8217;s 
still the basis of modern orthodontics because it provides torque control. 
Its basis is the placement of a rectangular arch wire that is twisted so that 
its orientation is different from the orientation of a rectangular bracket 
slot where it fits tightly. Then the twist in the wire is translated into 
torque for the tooth.</p>

<p>To create a couple within the bracket slot, the forces against the outer 
and inner edges of the bracket slot would have to be quite large, because 
the moment arm of the couple is so small. Without that heavy force within 
the bracket (which the periodontal ligament does not feel), you can&#8217;t 
create the necessary M<sub>C</sub> for torque.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-21.gif" resourceWidth="586" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-21_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="104" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Effect of Bracket Width</title><pageText><p>We already have noted the effect of bracket width on the force with which 
an archwire contacts the corners of a bracket to create a couple. The wider 
the bracket, the lower the force, because the moment arm across the bracket 
is longer.</p>

<p>If the tooth is to slide along an archwire (to close a space between the 
teeth), it tips until the archwire contacts the corners of the bracket. Then, 
if the wire doesn&#8217;t bend, a couple is created that keeps the tooth 
from tipping any further. The magnitude of the force that generates the 
couple becomes a factor in resistance to sliding. There are two 
sources of resistance to sliding: friction as the wire slides along the 
sides and base of the bracket, and  contact of the wire against the 
corners of the bracket that creates binding.</p>

<p>Brackets and wires are sized by thousandths of an inch: a typical round 
wire size might be .016&#8221; in diameter, while a rectangular one might 
be .017&#8221; in one dimension, .025&#8221; in another. It&#8217;s easier 
if we translate those numbers into mils (milli-inches), so that .016&#8221; 
becomes 16 and .017&#8221; by .018&#8221; becomes 17x25. We&#8217;ll refer 
to wires with those numbers. For rectangular brackets, only the smaller 
number usually is given&#8212;if the bracket dimensions are .022 by 
.028&#8221; or .022 by [something else], it&#8217;s just a 22 slot bracket 
because the larger dimension has little effect.</p>

<p>For sliding, the wire must be undersized relative to the bracket. Otherwise, 
friction makes movement all but impossible. With an undersized wire that 
provides .003&#8221; clearance, however, friction can be ignored as soon as 
the couple is generated, because the couple creates almost all the resistance 
to sliding. Sliding often is done on a 19x25 steel wire in a 22 slot 
bracket&#8212;that&#8217;s the way you&#8217;d read about it, with the 
numbers in mils instead of thousandths of an inch.</p>

<p>The bottom line: if you want to slide a tooth along an archwire, a wider 
bracket is better, but friction is not an important factor when an 
undersized wire is used.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-23.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="249" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-23_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="69"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>The wider the bracket, the smaller the contact angle at the bracket 
corners, and the less the binding that is the major source of resistance 
to sliding.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Effect of Bracket Slot Size</title><pageText><p>As we have noted, the edgewise appliance was developed as a torquing 
device. Sliding a tooth along the archwire was not part of 
Angle&#8217;s treatment plan. He engineered the appliance to use 
.0215 x .028&#8221; gold wires in a .022 x .028&#8221; slot, choosing the 
wire material because gold was all he had. He chose to use narrow brackets 
to increase beam length (thereby making the wire more springy and increasing 
its range), and selected the wire and slot sizes to obtain the torsional 
properties he desired. Why torsional properties? Because the rectangular 
wire was twisted, not bent, when it was placed in the rectangular slot.</p>

<p>When stainless steel became available, the wire and slot sizes for torque 
changed. A 17 x 25 steel wire has torsional properties close to a 21.5 x 28 gold 
wire if the beam length is maximized by using narrow bracket, and to be 
effective it would have to be placed into a smaller slot. An 18 slot bracket 
typically is used for torque with a rectangular steel wire.</p>

<p>From this background, it&#8217;s easy to see that undersized steel wires 
with wider 22-slot edgewise brackets would facilitate sliding, but would 
make torque more difficult because full-dimension steel wires would be 
too stiff. With narrow 18-slot brackets and steel wires, torquing properties 
would be good but sliding would be more difficult. At present, about 
one-third of American orthodontists use 18 slot brackets and two-thirds 
use 22 slot. The choice is based on the trade-offs. Which  do you want more: 
to slide on an under-sized steel wire, or torque with a full size one?. 
It&#8217;s not that one slot size is better, it&#8217;s more that they 
emphasize different properties.</p></pageText><resources/></page></pages></section><section><title>Contemporary Removable Appliances</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Functional Appliances</title><pageText><p>Three types of removable appliances are frequently used in modern 
orthodontics:</p>

<ul>
  <li>functional appliances for growth modification</li>
  <li>active plates with finger springs or screws for minor tooth 
  movement, and</li>
  <li>clear aligners for certain types of malocclusion in adults.</li>
</ul>

<p>The goal of a functional appliance is not to move teeth, but to guide the 
growth of the jaws&#8212;usually to encourage forward growth of the mandible 
in children with a Class II problem due to mandibular deficiency. Why is it 
called a functional appliance? Because the originator of this type of 
treatment thought it worked by changing muscle function (image 1). He 
called the first device of this type an activator for the same 
reason&#8212;it was supposed to activate the jaw muscles and thereby 
cause growth. That turned out to be incorrect. The effects on growth 
are the same whether or not the child has to bite forward repeatedly, 
so long as the condyles are out of the fossa, but the functional appliance 
name has persisted.</p>

<p>There are many different functional appliances, as images 2-5 show. What 
they have in common (for Class II children) is a construction bite that 
brings the mandibular condyles down and forward, out of the glenoid fossa. 
For a Class III child, the condyles stay in the fossa while the mandible is 
rotated down and back. That&#8217;s only effective if the child has a short 
face, so functional appliance treatment is almost totally for Class II 
children.</p>

<p>Adding springs to a functional appliance to move teeth is possible, but may 
be counter-productive. If you&#8217;re trying to produce forward growth of 
the mandible, reducing overjet by tipping upper incisors back and lower 
incisors forward decreases the amount of overjet reduction from growth 
that might be achieved.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_13-27cd.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="302" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_13-27cd_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="159" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>The activator caused the child to bite forward, and incorporated a spring 
to keep it from fitting tightly so that the child would have to keep biting 
to hold it in place&#8212;thus &#8220;activating&#8221; the muscles.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-03b.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-03b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>The bionator, like the activator, has acrylic between the teeth to produce 
the forward mandibular position.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-05.jpg" resourceWidth="319" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-05_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="57" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>The twin block has separate upper and lower components, with a ramp on the 
lower to bring the mandible forward. A screw for maxillary expansion usually 
is included in the upper component.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-06.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-06_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>The Frankel appliance is constructed to hold the lips and cheeks away 
from the dentition, and incorporates acrylic behind the lower incisors to 
produce a forward bite.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-8.jpg" resourceWidth="591" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-8_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="105" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 5</label><caption><p>For a patient with a jaw asymmetry, a hybrid appliance like this can be 
helpful. It has a bionator-type bite block on one side, Frankel-type 
shields on the other side, and is made using a mandibular position that 
improves or corrects the asymmetry.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Functional Appliance Effects</title><pageText><p>You&#8217;ve already been taught that functional appliances often do affect 
mandibular growth, but the major effect is an acceleration of growth rather 
than development of a mandible that&#8217;s significantly larger than it 
would have been without treatment. Let&#8217;s review that important concept.</p>

<p>When somebody talks to you about the wonders of treatment with a new 
functional appliance, keep the lesson of this graph in mind. In a child who 
wears the appliance faithfully (unfortunately, not all of them do that), the 
effect usually is faster growth of the mandible for a while, then a gradual 
tapering off of growth even if the child keeps wearing the device. In the 
long term, the mandible ends up quite close to the size it would have been 
without treatment.</p>

<p>So how do functional appliances work? The reaction of the soft tissues to 
holding the mandible forward is a backward force against the maxilla that 
tends to restrict its forward growth (in other words, a headgear effect). 
Even without springs, there&#8217;s also a force to move the lower incisors 
forward and the upper incisors back (a Class II elastics effect). The 
acceleration in mandibular growth is convenient even if it eventually tends 
to wear off. All these things contribute to the eventual result.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_8-19.gif" resourceWidth="564" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_8-19_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="100" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Active Plates</title><pageText><p>Active plates once were the major appliance in European orthodontics, but 
have never been used much in the US and Canada. Their use has declined 
everywhere at this point, simply because they are not efficient even 
though they can produce most types of tooth movement.</p>

<p>The &#8220;split plate&#8221; shown in image 1 shows a European approach to 
arch expansion, using a screw mechanism in a removable plate to produce the 
tooth movement. The spring properties of screws, of course, are almost 
nonexistent, so the screw has to be reactivated by the patient at least 
every few days. A one-quarter turn of the screw opens it 0.25 mm. With a 
split plate, the force is distributed over most of the teeth in the dental 
arch. Even so, a heavy force that decays rapidly is produced, just the 
opposite of the light continuous force that is ideal for tooth movement.</p>

<p>A finger spring extending from an active plate (image 2) produces more 
physiologic forces over a much larger range than a screw. An active plate 
of this design can be effective if the desired movement is tipping and the 
distance the tooth is to be moved is not very far (image 3).</p>

<p>Both types of active plates, however, really can&#8217;t compete with fixed 
appliances if tooth movement other than tipping is desired. We&#8217;ve 
already pointed out that to do anything else, you have to have two-point 
contact on the teeth. That&#8217;s easy with a fixed appliance, very 
difficult with finger springs or screws.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-09.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="413" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-09_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="116" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Split-plate expansion appliance (often called a Schwarz plate after the 
Austrian orthodontist who popularized it).</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_12-18c.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_12-18c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Active plate with finger springs to correct anterior crossbite in a 
mixed-dentition child.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_12-18ab.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="200" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_12-18ab_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="55"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>Tooth movement achieved with the active plate seen in image 2.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Clear Aligners: Invisalign</title><pageText><p>Clear aligners are &#8220;suckdown appliances&#8221; produced by 
vacuum-forming clear thermoplastic sheets over a dental cast. They were 
introduced into orthodontics originally as retainers, and still are used 
frequently for that purpose. But if you had a way to repeatedly move teeth a 
little on a cast, and then made a series of aligners after each small movement 
that would not quite fit intra-orally and so would move the teeth a little each 
time...</p>

<p>This patented idea has been turned into the Invisalign appliance. 
There is no way to account for growth changes in the dental occlusion with 
a series of aligners, so Invisalign is just for adults or older adolescents, 
but the fact that a clear aligner is almost invisible when it&#8217;s in the 
mouth appeals to some adults. Almost all types of tooth movement can be 
produced with clear aligners, so long as you&#8217;re willing to bond 
attachments to some teeth to improve the grip of the aligners. The attachments 
can be clear plastic, so they too are almost invisible.</p>

<p>The Invisalign technique requires a number of steps in fabricating the series 
of aligners:</p>

<ul>
  <li>accurate impressions of the teeth are sent to the Invisalign laboratory, 
  and CT scans are used to develop a digital model (image 1)</li>
  <li>with input from the doctor, the company&#8217;s software is used to 
reposition the teeth in the digital model (image 2) in a series of steps, 
with a new digital model for each step</li>
  <li>the digital models for each step are used to create a series of 
stereolithographic casts (image 3)</li>
  <li>a suckdown aligner is made to fit each of the casts (image 4)</li>
</ul></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-13a.jpg" resourceWidth="542" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-13a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="96" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Impressions being placed into the CT machine.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-13d.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="371" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-13d_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="129" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Digital models as they look on the computer screen as a maxillary central 
incisor is being repositioned (0.5 mm or less in a single step).</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-14a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-14a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>A sequence of stereolithographic casts ready for vacuum-forming the aligners.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-14c.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="274" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-14c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="76"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>A stereolithographic cast and the aligner made using it.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Invisalign (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Invisalign isn&#8217;t an automatic process in which the company&#8217;s 
technicians make all the decisions about steps in treatment. The doctor has 
to decide whether crowding of the teeth requires extraction (if so, Invisalign 
isn&#8217;t a good choice as the appliance) or can be addressed by removing 
small amounts of interproximal enamel (which is feasible with clear aligners) 
(image 1). Some types of tooth movement, especially rotation and extrusion, 
can be accomplished only if bonded attachments are used, and where these are 
placed and how many are used also is up to the doctor (image 2). The 
attachments can be small tooth-colored blocks of composite plastic, so they 
aren't obvious.</p>

<p>Do you want to use Invisalign in your future general practice? You can, just as 
you can use fixed appliances if you select the right patients and carefully 
monitor their progress. Sometimes teeth don&#8217;t move exactly as planned, 
and it becomes necessary to take a new set of impressions and start over. 
Invisalign isn&#8217;t a hands-off procedure for the clinician.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-16.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="391" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-16_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Invisalign reproximation form, showing the amount of enamel to be removed 
and the stage of treatment when the resulting space will be closed.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-15a.jpg" resourceWidth="520" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-15a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="92" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Location of bonded attachments, as viewed on the computer screen 
during treatment planning.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Invisalign (cont.)</title><pageText><p>This series of images shows Invisalign treatment of a girl with a mild 
anterior open bite and mild crowding of the incisors. For her, elongating 
the upper incisors to close the open bite was appropriate because she 
needed greater incisor display&#8212;which is somewhat unusual in open 
bite patients.</p>

<p>To accomplish the incisor extrusion, attachments on the incisors were 
necessary, and removal of interproximal enamel on multiple teeth also was 
required to obtain ideal alignment. She had 19 upper aligners and 10 lower 
aligners. Treatment required 9 &#189; months. (courtesy Dr. William Gierie)</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41a.jpg" resourceWidth="300" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>pre-treatment smile</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41b.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>pre-treatment occlusion</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41c.jpg" resourceWidth="435" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="77" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>planning for bonded attachments</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41d.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41d_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>treatment completed</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41e.jpg" resourceWidth="300" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41e_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="53" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 5</label><caption><p>post-treatment smile</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Contemporary Fixed Appliances</title><pages><page pageType="content"><title>Evolution of the Edgewise Appliance: Bonded Attachments</title><pageText><p>Angle&#8217;s edgewise appliance remains the basis for almost all current 
fixed appliances, but it has undergone a major evolution, and changes in the 
appliance are continuing to occur. In this section, we will briefly examine 
five important changes in recent years: bonded brackets rather than bands, 
prescription brackets (the straight-wire appliance), lingual appliances, 
computer-fabricated arch wires and self-ligating brackets.</p>

<p>Since bonding is used widely in all types of dentistry now, its use in 
orthodontics requires very little discussion indeed. The major difference 
between orthodontic bonding and bonding for restorative dentistry is that 
at some point the brackets have to be removed without damage to the enamel. 
Modern bonding materials now make quite possible to bond brackets so well 
they can&#8217;t be removed without fracturing the enamel&#8212;which of 
course is a major mistake.</p>

<p>A major indication for bands is that lingual as well as facial attachments 
are needed. For this reason bands often are used on first molars and sometimes 
on second molars (images 1,2), while all other teeth have bonded 
attachments&#8212;but bonded attachments for molars are quite feasible 
for many patients.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_15-18a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_15-18a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Note the use of bands on the molars, with bonded brackets on other teeth, in 
this patient for whom premolar extraction spaces are to be closed.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_15-18b.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_15-18b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Space closure completed. Loops for space closure require arch wires with a 
close fit in the bracket. For this patient, 18 slot narrow brackets were 
used, and both the force and moment for bodily movement were generated by 
loops in 16x22 steel arch wires.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Prescription Brackets: the Straight-Wire Appliance</title><pageText><p>The original edgewise appliance used the same bracket on every tooth. This 
required careful formation of the arch wires to compensate for the different 
thickness of different teeth, different inclination of the crowns, and 
control of facio-lingual root position.</p>

<p>When bonded brackets came into common use, it was feasible to produce 
different brackets for each type of tooth and to vary the thickness of 
the bracket, the inclination of the bracket slot and the torque of the 
slot. This didn&#8217;t eliminate bending wires, but it greatly reduced 
the amount of wire bending that was necessary prior to the final finishing 
stage. That, of course, greatly increased efficiency. It was the final step in 
establishing the modern edgewise appliance as the one used by almost 
all orthodontists now.</p>

<p>The effect of varying the thickness of the bracket base is shown in 
image 1&#8212;it can eliminate the in-out bends that previously had to be 
placed in every archwire. Changing the orientation of the bracket slot 
for the maxillary incisors eliminated the need to place bends in the 
wire to obtain the proper inclination of the teeth (images 2 and 3). 
The torque orientation of the slot eliminated the need to have twists in 
every rectangular wire to prevent unwanted torque movements (image 4).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-31a.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="387" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-31a_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="124" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>With the original edgewise appliance, in-out bends were needed with 
each archwire in both the upper and lower arches to compensate for the 
varying thickness of the teeth. These bends can be eliminated if the 
thickness of the bracket base is varied.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-31b.jpg" resourceWidth="510" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-31b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="91" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Bends in the archwire like these, to obtain mesio-distal inclination of 
the roots of teeth, can be eliminated if the inclination of the bracket slot 
is varied. Note that different bracket inclinations are required on the 
left and right sides.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-33.gif" resourceWidth="328" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-33_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="58" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>In the modern edgewise appliance, the bracket slot is perpendicular to the 
long axis of the tooth, not parallel to the incisal edge.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-35.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="444" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-35_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="108" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>Unless the facio-lingual orientation of the bracket slot matches the desired 
root orientation, twist bends are required in each rectangular archwire to prevent 
the teeth from being too upright.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Prescription Brackets (cont.)</title><pageText><p>The prescription of a straight-wire bracket--the bracket base thickness, 
inclination of the slot, and torque orientation--carries with it assumptions 
about the morphology of the tooth and about where the bracket will be 
placed on the tooth. A number of prescriptions have been offered by different 
manufacturers, all of which are based on measurements from a large number of 
extracted teeth. The result is what you&#8217;d expect: the prescription 
works very well for patients whose teeth closely resemble what is sometimes 
called &#8220;California average&#8221;. The major manufacturers are in 
southern California, and that&#8217;s where they collected the teeth to 
generate their average measurements. The further your patient is from that 
average, the more wire bending you&#8217;d have to do, using the standard 
prescription. There are now prescriptions based on samples of teeth from other 
areas (an Asian prescription, for instance), but it&#8217;s still the case that 
the prescription won&#8217;t work very well for individuals who are outliers 
in the normal bell-shaped curve.</p>

<p>In this era of computer-assisted fabrication of almost everything, it&#8217;s 
technically possible to produce &#8220;the ultimate straight wire 
appliance&#8221; by producing a special bracket for every tooth of a specific 
individual. This is done using a 3-D laser scan of accurate dental casts to 
produce a digital virtual model, and then using it to reset the teeth to ideal 
position (images 1-3). Then it is possible to contour the 
bracket base for a precise fit at a certain point on each tooth and cut 
the bracket slot with the exact prescription to place that tooth in ideal 
position at the end of treatment.</p>

<p>Is that the way of the future? Possibly, despite the obvious problems 
created by loss of a bracket (the records are on file at the manufacturer, 
so you can get a new one in a week or two) and by problems in getting the 
bracket in exactly the right place on the tooth (positioning jigs are 
necessary). You&#8217;d need custom arch wires from the manufacturer as 
well, but these would be shaped only to the desired arch form.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-37a.jpg" resourceWidth="579" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-37a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="103" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Virtual model with accurate dimensions for each individual tooth, made from 
a laser scan of the dental casts prior to treatment</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-37b.jpg" resourceWidth="579" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-37b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="103" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Maxillary occlusal view of virtual model with custom brackets for each tooth. 
Note the varying thickness of the brackets so that no in-out bends are needed 
in the archwire</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-37c.jpg" resourceWidth="579" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-37c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="103" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>Mandibular occlusal view of virtual model</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Lingual Appliances</title><pageText><p>Could you put an effective fixed appliance on the lingual rather than the 
facial surface of the teeth? Obviously you could&#8212;if the patient could 
tolerate it and if the doctor could get to it to adjust it.</p>

<p>A successful lingual appliance is a 21st century phenomenon, although 
efforts to develop such an appliance started many years before the turn 
of the century. Three major problems had to be overcome:</p>

<ul>
  <li>bonding a thin bracket to the variable lingual surfaces of the teeth</li>
  <li>inserting a rectangular wire into a rectangular slot without great 
  difficulty (disturbing the tonsils in doing so is not good!)</li>
  <li>forming the arch wire, which requires major bends to 
  compensate for tooth thickness and careful use of tilt and torque</li>
</ul>

<p>Computer-assisted appliance fabrication provided solutions to all 
three problems. Using laser scans of dental casts, it is possible to 
generate a bonding pad for each individual tooth (image 1). That has 
the advantage that the pad fits onto the lingual surface in only one 
position, so you can put it back accurately if it comes off. Then low-profile 
brackets are attached to the bonding pads, and the appliance is ready for 
intra-oral bonding (image 2). The brackets, which have a rectangular slot 
that opens to the top rather than the side so that the wire can be dropped 
in from the top after slipping it into a tube on the last molar, are the same 
for each tooth.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-38a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="436" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-38a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="110" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Bonding pads for each tooth, before brackets are mounted on the pads</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-38d.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="430" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-38d_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Low-profile brackets mounted on the bonding pads</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Lingual Appliances (cont.)</title><pageText><p>Now, how do you form the arch wire? The teeth are reset into ideal occlusion, 
and a wire-bending robot is used to provide the exact bends needed in the 
archwires for that individual patient (images 1 and 2).</p>

<p>The resulting appliance is at least reasonably tolerable for the patient, 
and it allows the treatment of all types of malocclusion. It&#8217;s the 
invisible appliance for patients whose problems are too severe to treat 
with Invisalign, and it is more precise and predictable than what can be 
achieved with the series of aligners. Laboratory costs are about the same 
for Invisalign and this approach to lingual orthodontics (expensive for 
both).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-40b.gif" resourceWidth="586" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-40b_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="104" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Computer-formed archwires can have complex but precisely oriented bends, as 
needed to obtain the same occlusion as the ideal set-up</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-40c.jpg" resourceWidth="590" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-40c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="105" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Rectangular lingual archwire, formed by the computer-controlled wire bending 
robot, to produce the final detailed positioning of teeth</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Computer-Fabricated Facial Arch Wires</title><pageText><p>Custom brackets for each tooth and plain arch wires that are formed only to 
the desired arch form are one way to reduce wire bending to a minimum if not 
totally eliminate it. An alternative approach, now commercially available, 
is to use &#8220;plain vanilla&#8221; brackets with no prescription (or any 
prescription, so long as it is known), and then fabricate the necessary arch 
wires with a computer robot. This is similar to the approach in lingual 
orthodontics, but the design of the brackets on the facial surface does not 
have to be altered.</p>

<p>The technique requires a digital model, and at present this is achieved via 
an intra-oral laser scan after the teeth have been brought into initial 
alignment (image 1). If a CT scan is available for the patient, it can 
substitute for the laser scan. Small round superelastic wires that have 
standard arch forms can be used for the initial alignment. The 3-D information 
from the scan is sent to the company&#8217;s laboratory, a digital model 
produced from the scan is used to set up the teeth in the desired final 
position, and a wire-bending robot (image 2) forms the rectangular arch 
wires to accomplish the changes in the digital model (images 3 and 4).</p>

<p>It seems quite likely that either the custom brackets approach or the 
computer-formed arch wire approach will win this contest between alternate 
CAD-CAM methods. At this point it&#8217;s too early to know how it will 
turn out. Which would you bet on?</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-41a.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="284" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-41a_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="79"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Intra-oral laser scan, to produce a digital model of the dental</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-41b.jpg" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-41b_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Computer-controlled wire-bending robot</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-41c.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-41c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>Computer-formed arch wire before insertion</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-41d.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-41d_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>Arch wire after insertion</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Self-Ligating Brackets: Active Clip</title><pageText><p>It&#8217;s obviously important to hold arch wires in the brackets of a 
fixed appliance. A pin across the front of the bracket was used in 
Angle&#8217;s predecessor to the edgewise appliance, and a similar system 
was used in the Begg appliance. Wire ligatures were used with the original 
edgewise appliance. In modern treatment, these have been largely superceded 
by elastomeric modules ("A-lastics).</p>

<p>Some sort of built-in cap was offered in a number of variations of the 
edgewise appliance throughout the 20th century, and this idea has been widely 
adapted recently. The current self-ligating brackets can be placed into three 
categories: active clip, active-passive clip, and passive (rigid) clip.</p>

<p>The first of the modern self-ligating brackets was the Speed appliance, 
designed in Canada in the 1980s with a spring clip to hold the wire in 
place (image 1). The springiness of the clip would add to the springiness 
of the wire, reducing the force against a tooth during initial alignment. 
The bracket is narrow to further decrease force by making the wire segment 
longer and more springy. That was more important before superelastic wires 
became available but still can be desirable.</p>

<p>Speed continues to be used widely at this point, typically with an 18 
slot. It is the major (but not the only) bracket with active self-ligation.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36f.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36f_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Speed bracket with active clip open</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Self-Ligating Brackets: Active/Passive Clip</title><pageText><p>A second category of self-ligating brackets would be those with a clip that 
is active during initial alignment, but is formed so that it does not press 
against the wire in the bracket slot after alignment is complete.</p>

<p>The leading example of this design is GAC&#8217;s InOvation bracket 
(image 1), in which the clip catches on a ledge at the bracket edge to 
keep it from being active after the arch wire is not distorted when it 
is placed into the bracket (i.e., after initial alignment). As of 
mid-2008, it was the most frequently used self-ligating bracket.</p>

<p>A variant of the active-passive type is Unitek&#8217;s SmartClip bracket, 
in which NiTi springs are used to hold the wire in place. The effect (at 
least theoretically) is the same; the springs would contact the arch wire 
if it was bent while being placed in the slot, and their elasticity might 
further reduce the force. But when a later wire was not distorted during 
placement, the springs would be passive, not pressing the wire into the slot.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/inovation_bracket.jpg" resourceWidth="450" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/inovation_bracket_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="80" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>InOvation bracket, with clip that catches on a ledge so that it is not active 
after initial alignment.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36g.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36g_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>SmartClip bracket, with NiTi springs on both ends to keep the archwire from 
slipping out of  the bracket slot.</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Passive Clip</title><pageText><p>If the clip for a self-ligating bracket is rigid, and essentially just puts 
a lid on the bracket when it is closed, it goes into the passive clip 
category. With this design, the elasticity of the arch wire provides all 
the force against the tooth. It is not surprising that brackets of this 
type were not popular until superelastic wires with excellent spring 
qualities were widely available.</p>

<p>Several passive clip brackets are now available, with the Damon bracket 
being the leader in this category. The clip locks into place when it is 
moved to the closed position, creating the equivalent of a tube to hold 
the wire in place (images 1 and 2).</p>

<p>Note that the brackets with a passive clip design, whether or not the clip 
was active during initial alignment, are about the same width as the twin 
brackets in a conventional edgewise appliance. What difference does that 
make? Remember, the width of the bracket is an important factor in resistance 
to sliding--wider brackets slide more easily because the contact angle with the 
corners of the bracket is smaller.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36ab.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="300" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36ab_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="160" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Damon bracket open and closed</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36c.jpg" resourceWidth="493" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="88" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>The rigid clipcreates the equivalent of a tube when the lid is closed</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Friction as a Component of Resistance to Sliding</title><pageText><p>Why has there been great interest in self-ligating brackets recently? The 
emphasis in marketing these brackets is  the claim that they reduce friction 
between the bracket and a wire, because there is no wire ligature or 
elastomeric fastener to push the wire against the base of the 
bracket&#8212;and that this reduces treatment time, increasing efficiency 
during treatment. A further claim in marketing rigid clip self-ligating 
brackets is that brackets with an active clip do create friction at some 
points in treatment, and that this increases treatment time.</p>

<p>It is interesting that laboratory data support the claim that passive clip 
brackets reduce friction&#8212;and demolish the claim that this makes a 
difference in resistance to sliding. The best data come from studies at 
North Carolina by Dr. Robert Kusy and co-workers. Let&#8217;s 
look first at data for friction with various brackets (image 1). In the 
laboratory set-up to measure friction, the wire is maintained in orientation 
with the bracket so that it doesn&#8217;t contact the corners of the bracket, 
as would be necessary to generate a moment and produce bodily tooth movement.</p>

<p>Note that in this laboratory setup, all the self-ligating brackets have little 
or no friction when the bracket slides along a small superelastic wire (yellow 
bars) (image 2).</p>

<p>With larger wires (red and blue bars), there still is almost no friction 
with SmartClip and Damon. The active clip produces friction with the larger 
wires, and you can see that there&#8217;s more friction with Speed than with 
the two active-passive designs (InOvation and Time) (image 3).</p>

<p>Fresh elastomeric ligatures (Alastics) produce quite a lot of friction 
(image 4), but this drops rapidly after they are in the mouth, so the 
long-term friction is probably quite similar to that with steel ligatures. 
With both, the amount of friction is noticeable even with the smallest wire 
size. So it&#8217;s correct that the passive clip reduces friction.</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/friction_v_bracket.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/friction_v_bracket_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Friction with various brackets</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/little_friction_vs_bracket.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/little_friction_vs_bracket_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>Almost no friction with small archwires and any self-ligating bracket</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/active_clip_vs_bracket.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/active_clip_vs_bracket_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>Friction with larger archwires for active-clip brackets</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/elast_friction_vs_bracket.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/elast_friction_vs_bracket_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>Heavy friction with fresh elastomeric ligatures (but this would decrease 
rapidly in the mouth)</p></caption></resource></resources></page><page pageType="content"><title>Elastic Binding in Resistance to Sliding</title><pageText><p>You already know that in the mouth it&#8217;s impossible to put force 
against a bracket that&#8217;s attached to a tooth without immediately 
tipping the tooth. There is a moment of the force, after all. So the 
tooth tips until it contacts the corners of the bracket. What happens 
when this contact occurs? Now the total resistance to sliding is a 
combination of friction and binding of the wire against the corners of 
the bracket, i.e., RS = Fr + B.</p>

<p>The data look very different when binding is allowed (image 1), With the 
smallest wire, the binding is still quite small and is about the same for 
all the brackets, including the conventional one using elastomeric 
ligatures. As the wire size goes up, so does the coefficient of binding, 
and the self-ligating brackets show no advantage at all.</p>

<p>Data from a different study in Kusy&#8217;s laboratory help to explain 
the clinical significance of the two graphs. In a study of sliding a 
large wire held with a 200 gm ligation force (so there was a lot of 
friction), you can see that very quickly almost all the resistance to 
sliding was due to binding (image 2). Above the smallest angle of 
contact with the bracket corners, the friction component was so low 
that it can be disregarded, i.e., Fr = B.</p>

<p>The bottom line: although friction is lower for self-ligating brackets 
at the very beginning of alignment (image 3), this provides little or no 
advantage clinically. Clinical trial data now show that the time to 
alignment isn&#8217;t faster with these brackets, and that the time 
to close an extraction space also isn&#8217;t reduced.</p>

<p>So what&#8217;s the advantage with self-ligating brackets? It appears to 
be primarily the amount of time (if any) saved in placing / replacing arch 
wires. With orthodontic appliances like almost anything else, a healthy 
skepticism about the advertising campaign is needed (image 4).</p></pageText><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/coeff_binding.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/coeff_binding_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 1</label><caption><p>Resistance to sliding when the bracket is allowed to tip relative to the archwire, 
as it always does in the mouth. The differences between the brackets disappears.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/friction_vs_resistance.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/friction_vs_resistance_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 2</label><caption><p>With a contact angle above 3 degrees, almost all the resistance to sliding is 
from binding.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/friction_vs_resistance_2.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/friction_vs_resistance_2_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label>Image 3</label><caption><p>At the very beginning of tooth movement, friction is a component of resistance 
to sliding. After that, friction is inconsequential--the resistance is almost totally 
due to binding.</p></caption></resource><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/dilbert.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="193" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/dilbert_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="166" thumbnailHeight="53"><label>Image 4</label><caption><p>A healthy skepticism toward advertising claims: not a bad idea!</p></caption></resource></resources></page></pages></section><section><title>Self-Test</title><pages><page pageType="test"><title>Question 1</title><pageText><p>(A) Gold wires rarely are used in modern orthodontics because (B) the price of 
gold increased greatly in the second half of the 20th century.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>You&#8217;re right, both statements are true but they aren't related. The 
strength and spring qualities of stainless steel had led to the replacement 
of gold by steel wires even before the cost difference increased greatly. At 
any price, gold is no longer competitive as a material for orthodontic wires.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. Both statements are true but they aren't related. 
The strength and spring qualities of stainless steel had led to the 
replacement of gold by steel wires even before the cost difference 
increased greatly. At any price, gold is no longer competitive as a material 
for orthodontic wires.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 2</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is the correct description of the elastic limit for 
an orthodontic arch wire? the point at which</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>it deviates from totally elastic behavior</choice><choice>it deviates at a measurable level</choice><choice>superelastic behavior is first noted</choice><choice>it begins to fail</choice><choice>it breaks</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. Yield strength, measured in the laboratory as the 
lowest point on a stress-strain curve at which a measurable amount of 
permanent bending can be observed, typically is used to describe the 
elastic limit of the wire. The proportional limit is an alternative term, 
and sometimes elastic limit and proportional limit are used interchangeably.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. Yield strength, measured in the laboratory as the 
lowest point on a stress-strain curve at which a measurable amount of 
permanent bending can be observed, typically is used to describe the elastic 
limit of the wire. The proportional limit is an alternative term, and 
sometimes elastic limit and proportional limit are used interchangeably.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-3.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="419" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-3_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="115" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 3</title><pageText><p>On a stress-strain curve, which of the following reflects the formability of 
a wire (the extent to which you can permanently deform it while bending it)?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>slope of the linear portion of the curve</choice><choice>area under the linear portion of the curve</choice><choice>distance along the stress axis (x axis) to the failure point</choice><choice>area under the curve between ultimate strength and failure point</choice><choice>area under the curve between yield strength and failure point</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, the area under the curve between yield strength (where 
permanent deformation starts, for all practical purposes) and failure point 
(where the wire breaks) describes the formability of the material.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. The area under the curve between yield strength (where 
permanent deformation starts, for all practical purposes) and failure point 
(where the wire breaks) describes the formability of the material.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-4.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="397" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-4_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="121" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 4</title><pageText><p>For a superelastic NiTi wire, what portion of a stress-strain graph represents 
the portion of the curve that contributes most of the force applied to a tooth?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>initial linear portion, loading</choice><choice>initial plateau, loading</choice><choice>second linear portion, unloading</choice><choice>second plateau, unloading</choice><choice>final linear portion, unloading</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. The superelastic plateau is the most important part of a 
graph that shows the force delivered to a tooth by a superelastic spring or 
section of an archwire&#8212;but it&#8217;s the lower of the two plateau 
curves, the unloading section of the curve.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. The superelastic plateau is the most important 
part of a graph that shows the force delivered to a tooth by a superelastic 
spring or section of an archwire&#8212;but it&#8217;s the lower of the two 
plateau curves, the unloading section of the curve.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-6.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="363" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-6_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="132" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 5</title><pageText><p>It&#8217;s quite effective to bend a helix in a finger spring to increase its 
length because (B) springiness goes up when you do this while range goes down.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s correct, the first statement is true but the second is false. 
Springiness goes up more than strength goes down when you lengthen the spring 
by bending a helix, and range also increases, not decreases.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. The first statement is true but the second is false. 
Springiness goes up more than strength goes down when you lengthen the spring 
by bending a helix, and range also increases, not decreases.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-13.gif" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="427" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-13_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="112" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 6</title><pageText><p>For any elastic material, what determines the smallest size of wire that you 
could use to form a finger spring? It&#8217;s inherent</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>strength</choice><choice>springingess</choice><choice>range</choice><choice>resilience</choice><choice>1,2 and 3 </choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That is correct. The strength of the material determines the smallest size of 
wire that you can use, because if it deforms permanently when you activate a 
spring made from it or the patient bites against it, it will be ineffective. 
Once you have a wire that&#8217;s strong enough, you can improve its spring 
properties by lengthening the beam&#8212;which of course is what is done in 
fabricating most finger springs.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. The strength of the material determines the 
smallest size of wire that you can use, because if it deforms permanently when 
you activate a spring made from it or the patient bites against it, it will be 
ineffective. Once you have a wire that&#8217;s strong enough, you can improve 
its spring properties by lengthening the beam&#8212;which of course is what is 
done in fabricating most finger springs.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-14.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="390" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-14_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="123" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 7</title><pageText><p>In 1920 gold was the preferred material for orthodontic appliances. Which of 
the following is most likely to be the preferred material in 2020?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>new precious metal alloys</choice><choice>improved stainless steel</choice><choice>titanium alloys</choice><choice> chrome-cobalt alloys</choice><choice>composite plastics</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. Already composite plastic materials offer better 
combinations of strength, springiness and range than metal alloys, and these 
new materials are being used to build the most advanced airplanes. Since 
orthodontic technology tends to follow aerospace technology by 10-15 years, it 
is highly likely that composite plastics will be the preferred material for 
orthodontic appliances in another decade or so.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That&#8217;s wrong. Already composite plastic materials offer better 
combinations of strength, springiness and range than metal alloys, and these 
new materials are being used to build the most advanced airplanes. Since 
orthodontic technology tends to follow aerospace technology by 10-15 years, it 
is highly likely that composite plastics will be the preferred material for 
orthodontic appliances in another decade or so.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 8</title><pageText><p>(A) When a single force is applied against the crown of a tooth, the center 
of resistance and center of rotation are the same because (B) the moment of 
the force is determined by the distance from the point of force application 
to the center of reistance.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="2"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. The two statements are both true, but they don&#8217;t 
have a cause-and-effect relationship. The center of resistance and center of 
rotation are the same because there is a moment of the force, not because of 
what determines its magnitude. The only way to keep a force from rotating the 
tooth around its center of resistance is to apply the moment of a couple to 
counteract the moment of the force.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. The two statements are both true, but they don&#8217;t 
have a cause-and-effect relationship. The center of resistance and center of 
rotation are the same because there is a moment of the force, not because of 
what determines its magnitude. The only way to keep a force from rotating the 
tooth around its center of resistance is to apply the moment of a couple to 
counteract the moment of the force.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-17.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-17_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="107" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 9</title><pageText><p>Which of the following is a correct ratio if you want to torque the root of an 
incisor lingually?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>M<sub>C</sub> / M<sub>F</sub> = 0.5</choice><choice>M<sub>C</sub> / M<sub>F</sub> = 0.75</choice><choice>M<sub>C</sub> / M<sub>F</sub> = 1</choice><choice>M<sub>C</sub> / M<sub>F</sub> = 1.5</choice><choice>all could be correct, depends on location of center of resistance</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, torque requires a M<sub>C</sub> / M<sub>F</sub> 
ratio greater than 1, so that the root moves more than the crown. The 
location of the center of resistance has nothing to do with it.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. Torque requires a M<sub>C</sub> / M<sub>F</sub> 
ratio greater than 1, so that the root moves more than the crown. The location 
of the center of resistance has nothing to do with it.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22ad.jpg" resourceWidth="440" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-22ad_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="78" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 10</title><pageText><p>How does the formability of a superelastic NiTi wire compare to the 
formability of a stainless steel wire? The formability of the NiTi wire is</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>much greater</choice><choice>a little greater</choice><choice>about the same</choice><choice>a little less</choice><choice>much less</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, the formability of superelastic NiTi wire is much less 
than the formability of a stainless steel wire. It&#8217;s so much less that 
for all practical purposes, you can&#8217;t really change the shape of the 
wire that you purchased from the manufacturer&#8212;quite unlike steel wire 
that you can readily bend to make orthodontic springs.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. The formability of superelastic NiTi wire is much 
less than the formability of a stainless steel wire. It&#8217;s so much less 
that for all practical purposes, you can&#8217;t really change the shape 
of the wire that you purchased from the manufacturer&#8212;quite unlike 
steel wire that you can readily bend to make orthodontic springs.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 11</title><pageText><p>When a rectangular arch wire is used to torque a tooth, how does the 
force with which the wire contacts the walls of the bracket compare to the 
force felt by the PDL?</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>much greater</choice><choice>a little greater</choice><choice>about the same</choice><choice>a little less</choice><choice>much less</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, the force with which the edges of the twisted wire contact 
the inner and outer surfaces of the bracket is much greater than the force 
felt by the periodontal ligament. The wire creates a couple within the bracket, 
and because the moment arm from one side of the wire to the other is quite 
small, the equal and opposite forces to form the couple have to be quite large.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. The force with which the edges of the twisted wire 
contact the inner and outer surfaces of the bracket is much greater than the 
force felt by the periodontal ligament. The wire creates a couple within the 
bracket, and because the moment arm from one side of the wire to the other is 
quite small, the equal and opposite forces to form the couple have to be 
quite large.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-21.gif" resourceWidth="586" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_10-21_s.gif" thumbnailWidth="104" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 12</title><pageText><p>(A) The resistance to sliding a tooth along an arch wire increases when a 
wider bracket is used because (B) the wider bracket allows an arch wire to 
create a moment across it with less force on the corners of the bracket.</p></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>A true, B true, A and B related</choice><choice>A true, B true, A and B not related</choice><choice>A true, B false</choice><choice>A false, B true</choice><choice>A and B false</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, the first statement is false but the second one is true. 
All other things being equal, resistance to sliding decreases, not increases, 
when a wider bracket is used. A wider bracket  allows creation of a moment 
to control root position with less force against the bracket corners, because 
the moment arm is longer. It's the force against the bracket corners that 
creates almost all of the resistance to sliding.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s wrong. The first statement is false but the second one is 
true. All other things being equal, resistance to sliding decreases, not 
increases, when a wider bracket is used. A wider bracket allows creation 
of a moment to control root position with less force against the bracket 
corners, because the moment arm is longer. It's the force against the bracket 
corners that creates almost all of the resistance to sliding.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 13</title><pageText><p>Which of the following types of tooth movement require 2-point contact 
with the crown of the tooth being moved?</p>

<ol>
<li>tipping</li>
<li>bodily movement</li>
<li>torque</li>
</ol></pageText><choices correctChoice="4"><choice>1 only</choice><choice>2 only</choice><choice>1 and 2</choice><choice>2 and 3</choice><choice>all require 2-point contact</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, tipping results from one-point contact, while bodily 
movement and torque require two-point contact. That means that tipping is the 
primary outcome of treatment with a removable appliance and finger springs, 
while bodily movement and torque all but require a fixed appliance.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That&#8217;s wrong. Tipping results from one-point contact, while bodily 
movement and torque require two-point contact. That means that tipping is 
the primary outcome of treatment with a removable appliance and finger 
springs, while bodily movement and torque all but require a fixed appliance.</p></incorrectResponse><resources/></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 14</title><pageText><p>When clear aligners are used for orthodontic treatment, which types of tooth 
movement require bonded attachments?</p>

<ol>
<li>tipping</li>
<li>rotation</li>
<li>extrusion</li>
<li>intrusion</li>
</ol></pageText><choices correctChoice="3"><choice>1 and 2</choice><choice>1 and 3</choice><choice>2 and 3</choice><choice>2 and 4</choice><choice>1 and 4</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. With clear aligners, rotation and extrusion are almost 
impossible without the use of a bonded attachment on the tooth so that the 
aligner can get a better grip on it. Interestingly, intrusion can be 
accomplished with an aligner without bonded attachments because light force 
is all that is needed. An aligner has enough grip to do that, and also to tip 
teeth.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>That&#8217;s wrong. With clear aligners, rotation and extrusion are almost 
impossible without the use of a bonded attachment on the tooth so that the 
aligner can get a better grip on it. Interestingly, intrusion can be 
accomplished with an aligner without bonded attachments because light 
force is all that is needed. An aligner has enough grip to do that, and 
also to tip teeth.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41c.jpg" resourceWidth="435" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_18-41c_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="77" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 15</title><pageText><p>Which of the following are part of the prescription for a modern straight-wire 
bracket?</p>

<ol>
<li>specific type of tooth</li>
<li>base thickness</li>
<li>angulation of bracket slot</li>
<li>facio-lingual orientation of bracket slot</li>
</ol></pageText><choices correctChoice="5"><choice>1 and 2</choice><choice>3 and 4</choice><choice>1, 2, and 3</choice><choice>2, 3, and 4</choice><choice>all</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right, all four of these items are part of the prescription. The 
basic idea for the modern bracket is that it is intended for a specific type 
of tooth. The thickness of the base compensates for the varying thickness of 
teeth (particularly the incisors and canines), thereby reducing the need for 
in-out bends in arch wires. The angulation of the bracket slot reduces 
the need for bends to obtain proper mesio-distal root position, and the 
facio-lingual orientation of the slot provides torque as needed to control 
facio-lingual root position.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. All four of these items are part of the 
prescription. The basic idea for the modern bracket is that it is intended 
for a specific type of tooth. The thickness of the base compensates for the 
varying thickness of teeth (particularly the incisors and canines), thereby 
reducing the need for in-out bends in arch wires. The angulation of the 
bracket slot reduces the need for bends to obtain proper mesio-distal root 
position, and the facio-lingual orientation of the slot provides torque as 
needed to control facio-lingual root position.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-31.jpg" resourceWidth="293" resourceHeight="450" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-31_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="52" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page><page pageType="test"><title>Question 16</title><pageText><p>Which of the following correctly describe active self-ligation for an 
orthodontic bracket? Springiness of a clip</p>

<ol>
<li>adds to springiness of the archwire</li>
<li>makes the wire more resilient</li>
<li>effectively makes the wire stronger</li>
</ol></pageText><choices correctChoice="1"><choice>1 only</choice><choice>1 and 2</choice><choice>2 and 3</choice><choice>1 and 3</choice><choice>all the above</choice></choices><correctResponse><p>That&#8217;s right. Active self-ligation means that the clip that holds the 
wire in place is springy and adds to the springiness of the wire during 
initial alignment. The clip, however, doesn&#8217;t change the properties 
of the archwire. Resilience and strength of the wire are independent of 
how it&#8217;s held in a bracket.</p></correctResponse><incorrectResponse><p>No, that&#8217;s incorrect. Active self-ligation means that the clip that 
holds the wire in place is springy and adds to the springiness of the wire 
during initial alignment. The clip, however, doesn&#8217;t change the 
properties of the archwire. Resilience and strength of the wire are 
independent of how it&#8217;s held in a bracket.</p></incorrectResponse><resources><resource resourceType="image" resourceLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36f.jpg" resourceWidth="600" resourceHeight="400" thumbnailLocation="controlorthoforce/images/fig_11-36f_s.jpg" thumbnailWidth="120" thumbnailHeight="80"><label/><caption/></resource></resources></page></pages></section></sections></presentation>